<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ASTRONOMY</subject><subject>VIROLOGY</subject><subject>MEDICINE</subject><subject>ECOLOGY</subject><subject>SCI POLICY</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Around the World</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>17</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6096</issue>
<fpage seq="b">782</fpage>
<lpage>783</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>In science news around the world this week, Curiosity sent its first color, 360-degree look at Gale Crater to scientists at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory; an unusual influenza virus is spreading from pigs to children in the U.S. Midwest; a pancreatic cancer therapy has failed; most people oppose using genetically engineered male mosquitoes to control wild mosquito populations; and a National Research Council report lays out a wish list from the heliophysics community.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>In science news around the world this week, Curiosity sent its first color, 360-degree look at Gale Crater to scientists at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory; an unusual influenza virus is spreading from pigs to children in the U.S. Midwest; a pancreatic cancer therapy has failed; most people oppose using genetically engineered male mosquitoes to control wild mosquito populations; and a National Research Council report lays out a wish list from the heliophysics community.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_782b_F1"></graphic>
</fig>
<boxed-text content-type="story_index">
<def-list>
<def-item><term>1 - Pasadena, California</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec1">Curiosity Takes a Look Around</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>2 - Indiana and Ohio</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2">Swine Flu Virus in Midwest</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>3 - Thousand Oaks, California</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3">Amgen Pulls Cancer Drug</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>4 - Raleigh</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec4">U.S. Public Wary of GM Mosquitoes</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>5 - Washington, D.C.</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec5">To Our Star and Beyond While Staying Within a Budget</xref></p></def></def-item>
</def-list>
</boxed-text>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec1">
<title>Pasadena, California</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Curiosity Takes a Look Around</title>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_782b_F2"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: NASA/JPL-CALTECH/MSSS</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Three days after landing on Mars, Curiosity sent its first color, 360-degree look at Gale Crater (above) to scientists at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, California, late in the day on 8 August. The panorama, composed of 130 thumbnail images taken with the rover's Mast Camera, shows some targets for future exploration: gray patches in the foreground, where rocket engines blasted the ground during the rover's descent, and in the distance, reddish-brown dunes cut across by a gray layer. Over the next 2 years, Curiosity will cross the rocky surface of the crater on its way to Mount Sharp, the crater's interior mountain.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec2">
<title>Indiana and Ohio</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Swine Flu Virus in Midwest</title>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_782b_F3"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: LYA CATTEL/ISTOCKPHOTO.COM</attrib>
</fig>
<p>An unusual influenza virus spreading from pigs to children has caught the attention of public health officials. The virus, H3N2v, first surfaced in July 2011 and seasonally infects humans but has not caused severe disease. According to the 10 August issue of the <italic>Morbidity and Mortality Report</italic>, which is published by the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), the country has had 153 cases since 12 July.</p>
<p>More than 90% of the H3N2v cases occurred in children, most of whom had direct or indirect contact with pigs, and all but two were in Indiana and Ohio. Researchers are intrigued because H3N2v has an internal &#x201C;M&#x201D; gene that matches one found in H1N1; this M gene may play a role in the current transmissions, by giving it an advantage for circulating in pigs, says CDC virologist Michael Shaw. &#x201C;And if it becomes more common in pigs, it gives more of a chance to jump into humans,&#x201D; Shaw says. However, there's no evidence that this M gene alone leads to human-to-human transmission.</p>
<p>Studies have shown that the current flu vaccine likely will not protect against this strain, but adults may have immunity from exposure to &#x201C;wild type&#x201D; strains of influenza as well as previous vaccines. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scim.ag/swineflu2"><bold>http://scim.ag/swineflu2</bold></ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec3">
<title>Thousand Oaks, California</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Amgen Pulls Cancer Drug</title>
<p>The failure of a pancreatic cancer therapy, announced last week by its maker Amgen, is another sign that a once-promising class of cancer treatments that target a particular hormone isn't helping as hoped. The latest therapy to flop, called ganitumab, targets type 1 insulin-like growth factor receptor (IGF-1R). After a phase III clinical trial of the therapy, the company concluded it wouldn't help patients live longer and pulled the plug.</p>
<p>IGF-1R was deemed a promising target after researchers found that higher levels in a person's blood were linked to a slightly greater risk of cancer. Overexpressing the hormone in the lab seemed to cause tumors in cells and animals that shrank when treated with an IGF-1R blocker.</p>
<p>But in patients, the drugs are &#x201C;a serial failure,&#x201D; says Vuk Stambolic, a cancer researcher at Princess Margaret Hospital and the Ontario Cancer Institute in Toronto, Canada. One problem is that it may not be enough to go after IGF-1R alone, especially in patients with very advanced disease. The work in animals and cells also may not fully mimic real life. &#x201C;I think that the model is probably only partially representative of what happens in cancer,&#x201D; Stambolic says. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scim.ag/IGF1Rpulled"><bold>http://scim.ag/IGF1Rpulled</bold></ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec4">
<title>Raleigh</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>U.S. Public Wary of GM Mosquitoes</title>
<p>Most people oppose using genetically engineered male mosquitoes to control wild mosquito populations&#x2014;when they learn the potential risks, a survey released on 8 August by researchers from North Carolina State University suggests. The mosquitoes have been released in other countries to control mosquito-borne diseases, but have not yet been used in the United States. The survey, which polled 1211 people, is the first to gauge U.S. public opinion on the technology.</p>
<p>People were most receptive to the idea when the mosquitoes were described as &#x201C;sterile,&#x201D; rather than &#x201C;genetically modified&#x201D; or &#x201C;transgenic,&#x201D; says political scientist Michael Cobb, who supervised the survey. But using the word &#x201C;sterile&#x201D; in public information campaigns could be misleading, he says: When genetically engineered male mosquitoes breed with wild females, they pass on a defective gene which causes their offspring to die early.</p>
<p>Approval increased when people learned more technical information, but when potential risks were explained&#x2014;such as the possibility that the altered genes in any surviving female offspring might cause a new allergy, or that a more noxious animal might fill the mosquito's ecological niche&#x2014;approval plummeted to 33% for &#x201C;sterile&#x201D; and 17% for &#x201C;genetically engineered&#x201D; mosquitoes.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec5">
<title>Washington, D.C.</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>To Our Star and Beyond While Staying Within a Budget</title>
<fig id="F4" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_782b_F4"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: NASA/SDO/AIA</attrib>
</fig>
<p>The latest pitch for doing science in space takes a decidedly budget-wise approach. Released on 15 August, the report by the National Research Council (NRC) of the U.S. National Academies lays out a wish list from the heliophysics community. It calls for exploration in the next decade of what drives solar activity and how that activity affects the solar system, especially Earth and its inhabitants. And most of it would be done within the slowly increasing $650-million-per-year budget specified by NASA for heliophysics.</p>
<p>A key to the decadal plan is a redefinition of medium-size heliophysics space missions. Three proposed missions would be conceived by the community, led by a principal investigator, and constrained to a cost of $520 million each. &#x201C;This is the single best way we've found to contain costs,&#x201D; says the committee's chair, Daniel Baker of the University of Colorado, Boulder.</p>
<p>Not that heliophysics has no grand ambitions: A recommended billion-dollar mission later in the decade&#x2014;a constellation of spacecraft to investigate how Earth's atmosphere absorbs solar wind energy&#x2014;would require a budget boost if it is to be in service by the next solar maximum in 2024.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
</article>