<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1224870</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1224870</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Books <italic>et al.</italic></subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>books</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI HISTORY PHILO</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Philosophy of Biology</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Ending Microbial Myopia</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Villabona-Arenas</surname><given-names>Christian Julian</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff id="aff1">The reviewer is at the Laboratory of Molecular Evolution and Bioinformatics, Department of Microbiology, Biomedical Sciences Institute, University of S&#x00E3;o Paulo, Avenida Professor Lineu Prestes 1734, CEP: 05508&#x2013;000, S&#x00E3;o Paulo, Brazil.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>cj.villabona@usp.br</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>17</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6096</issue>
<fpage>800</fpage>
<lpage>801</lpage>
<product product-type="book"><bold>Processes of Life</bold> Essays in the Philosophy of Biology <bold><italic>by John Dupr&#x00E9;</italic></bold> Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2012. 360 pp. $55, &#x00A3;30. ISBN 9780199691982.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Through considerations of developmental systems perspectives, epigenetics, and microbial life, Dupr&#xE9; challenges widely held assumptions about biology and evolution.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Through considerations of developmental systems perspectives, epigenetics, and microbial life, Dupr&#xE9; challenges widely held assumptions about biology and evolution.</p></abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sherman J. Suter</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Lauren Kmec</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A self-described &#x201C;philosophical naturalist,&#x201D; John Dupr&#x00E9; aims &#x201C;to draw&#x2014;or at least support&#x2014;philosophical conclusions from science&#x201D; and to provide critical perspectives on it. In the 16 essays (published over the past decade) collected in <italic>Processes of Life</italic>, he applies his approach to contemporary biology. The volume stresses three points Dupr&#x00E9; sees as crucial to understanding biology and evolution: the developmental systems perspective, epigenetics, and the importance of microbes. In its concluding section, he explores how the biological ideas he has discussed affect our conception of human nature.</p>
<p>Dupr&#x00E9; (a philosopher of science at the University of Exeter) begins with a trio of chapters that survey his broader view of science, which he sees as produced by people in interaction with nature. He advocates a methodological pluralism and highlights the pitfalls of a purely reductionist enterprise. Given the variety of scientific activities, he wonders how they could be, in any sense, all about the same thing. Because methodologies have been developed in ways as diverse as the kinds of problems researchers pursue, the author outlines a set of epistemic virtues and advises practitioners to try to meet as many of them as possible.</p>
<p>One fundamental argument Dupr&#x00E9; offers against reductionism is that biology works with concepts that depend not only on their constituents but also on the larger systems of which they are part. Debates over the nature of species have generated a substantial fraction of the evolutionary biology literature; less attention has been placed on the definition of genes. In addition to the concerns around such issues, there is the central question of what constitutes the individual organism. (With 90% of the cells within our bodies belonging to microbes, there is much to be said for considering that bacterial community as a single composite entity.) The author reminds us &#x201C;that theoretical considerations are insufficient to determine unequivocally the boundaries of biological objects. Sometimes, perhaps always, this must be done relative to a purpose.&#x201D; Altogether, Dupr&#x00E9; encourages trying to understand life as a hierarchy of dynamic and constantly changing processes. A living world where none of the entities that constitute an organism are static implies an interactive flux subtly different in every iteration but similar enough to be a distinctive process. Because biological concepts are static abstractions from life processes and different abstractions provide different perspectives on these processes, we face considerable difficulties in reconciling satisfactory general concepts.</p>
<p>Although their scientific importance remains generally unappreciated, microbes surpass macrobes (a term Dupr&#x00E9; advocates for those organisms that are not bacteria, archaea, or protists) in their contribution to evolutionary history: the first three billion years of life on Earth were overwhelmingly microbial. Even today, they include most living things, exhibit a greater metabolic diversity, and inhabit a wider range of environments (including extremely harsh ones); their collaborative enterprise is so extensive that at the heart of every interface between multicellular eukaryotes and the external environment lies a complex multispecies microbial community. In three essays, Dupr&#x00E9; and coauthor Maureen A. O'Malley (University of Sydney) present a strong case for ending the myopia that leads us to undervalue microbes.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Boundary-blurring biofilms.</title>
<p>If bacteria in dental plaque (shown here in an SEM) &#x201C;function as a coordinated, spatially organized and fully metabolically integrated microbial community&#x201D; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>), Dupr&#x00E9; wonders why we would &#x201C;not consider this community, the organized functional whole, to constitute an organism.&#x201D;</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_800_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: STEVE GSCHMEISSNER/PHOTO SCIENCE LIBRARY/ALAMY</attrib>
</fig>
<p>As Dupr&#x00E9; and O'Malley note, paying proper attention to microbes has already yielded observations that may force us to rethink fundamental ideas about evolution. In light of the extent of lateral gene transfer, the &#x201C;tree of life&#x201D; seems better considered as a net. Studies of cooperation, development, competition, and communication among unicellular organisms have revealed that they can possess many of the characteristics used to define multicellularity. Given that the entities that form lineages are not always the same as those that form metabolic wholes, collaboration may be the central characteristic of living matter. Traditional organisms cannot be seen as &#x201C;&#x2018;the&#x2019; biological individuals on which selection operates.&#x201D; Abandoning some theoretical commitments will open the way for further understanding nature.</p>
<p>The author's reasons for recognizing the importance of the environment accentuate the relevance of epigenetics and developmental systems theory, areas that for a long time attracted little interest but have now become very active. Beyond doubt, Dupr&#x00E9; emphasizes, the perpetuation of life from one generation to the next requires much more than simply the passage of DNA. He concludes that genomes do not merely store information. Because of their constant dynamic interaction with other constituents of the cell, their capacities depend not only on their sequence of base pairs. More important, those capacities are determined by the systems of which the DNA molecules are only part.</p>
<p>Turning his attention to humans, Dupr&#x00E9; criticizes &#x201C;Evolutionary Psychology.&#x201D; He argues that evolution has had ample time since the Stone Age to shift our behavior and that &#x201C;the complexity of the developmental interactions between a wide variety of internal and external factors&#x201D; (processes such as epigenetics, niche construction, and cultural evolution) means our genes cannot produce a &#x201C;fixed and constant&#x201D; human nature. He applies similar reasoning in rejecting claims of genes for race, highlighting the mistake made in thinking of strings of DNA as having specific functions defined only in terms of phenotypic outcomes. For such reasons, he rejects genetic determinism.</p>
<p>Through their thorough arguments, the essays in <italic>Processes of Life</italic> challenge widely held assumptions about biology and evolution. Dupr&#x00E9; provides a view of life grounded in recent research and current understanding. His perspective also reminds us how much we do not know.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Caries Res.</source> <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>204</fpage> (<year>2004</year>).</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>