<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="other" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>New Products</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Products &amp; Materials</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>products</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>New Products</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>17</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6096</issue>
<fpage seq="a">865</fpage>
<lpage>865</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>A weekly roundup of information on newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of potential interest to researchers.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary">
<p>A weekly roundup of information on newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of potential interest to researchers.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>UV LAMP </title>
<fig id="F1" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="337_865a_F1"><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text></graphic></fig>
<p>The Spectroline MiniMAX UV-5G is the perfect compact lamp for many laboratory applications including ultraviolet (UV) sanitizing of disease-causing microorganisms and UV degradation studies. The UV-5G model is a battery-operated, 5 W, short-wave (254 nm) UV lamp. It combines mini size with maximum power, making this lamp extremely portable and highly effective. The UV-5G lamp weighs only 11 oz (312 g) and it measures just 9 in x 2.25 in x 1.25 in (22.9 cm x 5.7 cm x 3.2 cm). It comes with a wrist strap to reduce hand fatigue and can be easily slipped into a pocket for convenient transport. The lamp is powered by four 1.5 V AA alkaline batteries (not included), which provide four to six hours of use. An AC adapter and nylon travel pouch are also included.</p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Spectroline</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-274-8888      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.spectroline.com">www.spectroline.com</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>LIPID BILAYER CONDUCTANCE READER</title>
<p>The tethaPod reader provides a direct read of conductance of lipid bilayer membranes containing peptides and ion channels, offering an alternative or additional experimental approach to traditional patch clamp techniques. The lipids are supplied as a stable monolayer, chemically tethered to a flat gold surface. A bilayer is readily formed by the addition of lipids in alcohol solution or liposomes to the monolayer. Peptides and proteins can be incorporated into the bilayer as part of this process resulting in a stable format for ligand and voltage gating studies. The tethaPod has been successfully applied to the study of the Chloride Intracellular Channel (CLIC) family, the bacterial sodium channel (NaBaCh), the potassium channel KvaP, and peptides such as the Magainins, Gramicidin, Valinomycin, and Alamethicin.</p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>SDx Tethered Membranes    </bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info:  888-965-6086      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sdxtetheredmembranes.com">www.sdxtetheredmembranes.com </ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>HPLC COLUMNS</title>
<p>Available in analytical, micro, and nano formats, the new Accucore 150-C18 and Accucore 150-C4 columns are designed to improve protein and peptide assay robustness by enhancing peak capacity and run times at moderate operating pressures. The 150 &#x00C5;pore diameter of the solid core particles is designed to provide the optimal combination of retention time and resolution for peptides and proteins. The Accucore 150-C18 has been further optimized for biomolecules and protein digests through bonding of C18 ligands onto the porous outer layer of the particles. The low hydrophobicity C4 ligand used in the Accucore 150-C4 column enables fast protein separations. Accucore columns are based on Core Enhanced Technology, featuring solid core particles engineered to an average size distribution of 1.12. A result is high-resolution separations with backpressures significantly lower than those of UHPLC. Advanced bonding technology produces excellent peak shapes through high bonding coverage and minimized secondary interactions.</p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Thermo Fisher Scientific</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-532-4752      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.thermoscientific.com/accucore150">www.thermoscientific.com/accucore150</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>DUCTLESS FUME HOODS</title>
<p>Patriot ductless fume hoods feature the easy-to-use AirSafe Touch automatic safety controller for added operator safety. This color touchscreen controller automatically increases or decreases blower speed to maintain the user's preset face velocity, ensuring airflow is within standard operating parameters. The current face velocity is displayed at all times. AirSafe Touch also monitors the bonded carbon filtration bed, alerting the user audibly and visually should filter saturation occur. Patriot features a unique 'application confirmation' sequence that is required with every use of the hood. AirSafe Touch displays the approved chemical class for the hood, and waits for a confirmation from the user before allowing the hood to be used. All electronics and blowers are postfilter, so they are never exposed to chemicals used in the hood. In addition to safety features, AirSafe Touch also provides a multilanguage and multiunit capability not found in most ductless hoods. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>AirClean Systems</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-849-0472      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aircleansystems.com">www.aircleansystems.com</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>BIOLUMINESCENT ENZYME</title>
<p>A novel luciferase that is smaller, brighter, and more versatile than any current bioluminescent enzyme. These attributes of the NanoLuc Luciferase provide new capabilities in reporter assays with potential in biologically complex applications that require greater sensitivity. NanoLuc technology includes a novel substrate, furimazine, which has an unparalleled small size allowing for enhanced viral delivery and protein fusion applications, and it is easily secreted from cells. The enzyme is two orders of magnitude brighter than either firefly (<italic>Photinus pyralis</italic>) or <italic>Renilla</italic> reniformis luciferases resulting in better performance in hard to transfect cells. Also, NanoLuc performs in more physiologically relevant models including complex biological samples. With add and measure simplicity and a stable signal, NanoLuc Luciferase can be scaled from benchtop to high throughput screening applications with no modifications. To meet the many application needs in a next-gen genetic reporter, 12 plasmid versions of NanoLuc Luciferase are available. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Promega</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 608-274-4330      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.promega.com/nanoluc">www.promega.com/nanoluc</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="product-submission-instructions"><p>Electronically submit your new product description or product literature information! Go to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/products/newproducts.dtl">www.sciencemag.org/products/newproducts.dtl</ext-link> for more information.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="disclaimer"><p><italic>Newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of interest to researchers in all disciplines in academic, industrial, and governmental organizations are featured in this space. Emphasis is given to purpose, chief characteristics, and availabilty of products and materials. Endorsement by </italic>Science<italic> or AAAS of any products or materials mentioned is not implied. Additional information may be obtained from the manufacturer or supplier.</italic></p></fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
