<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI COMMUN</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Random Sample</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>17</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6096</issue>
<fpage seq="a">783</fpage>
<lpage>784</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Researchers with the Sloan Digital Sky Survey III last week released the largest three-dimensional map of black holes and massive galaxies yet produced, which pinpoints the locations and distances to more than 1 million galaxies. A bioinformatician has begun a crowdfunding effort, hoping to raise $20,000 to sequence his own and his family's entire genomes. And this week's numbers quantify coral depth, research funding in sub-Saharan Africa, and the extinction rate for freshwater fish species in North America from 1900&#x2013;2010 compared with the rate found in the fossil record.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Researchers with the Sloan Digital Sky Survey III last week released the largest three-dimensional map of black holes and massive galaxies yet produced, which pinpoints the locations and distances to more than 1 million galaxies. A bioinformatician has begun a crowdfunding effort, hoping to raise $20,000 to sequence his own and his family's entire genomes. And this week's numbers quantify coral depth, research funding in sub-Saharan Africa, and the extinction rate for freshwater fish species in North America from 1900&#x2013;2010 compared with the rate found in the fossil record.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec>
<title>The Universe in 3D</title>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_783a_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: M. A. ARAG&#x00D3;N (JHU), M. SUBBARAO (ADLER PLANETARIUM), A. SZALAY (JHU), Y. YAO (LBNL, NERSC), AND THE SDSS-III COLLABORATION</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Researchers with the Sloan Digital Sky Survey III last week released the largest three-dimensional map of black holes and massive galaxies yet produced, which pinpoints the locations and distances to more than 1 million galaxies (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sdss3.org/press/dr9.php">http://www.sdss3.org/press/dr9.php</ext-link>). Mapping these galaxies will enable scientists to retrace the history of the universe for the last 6 billion years, the team says, thereby allowing astronomers to make better estimates for how much of it is composed of the &#x201C;dark matter&#x201D; that can&apos;t be directly seen, and &#x201C;dark energy,&#x201D; the mysterious force that&apos;s driving the expansion of the universe. The survey, which recently completed its second year, has so far covered about 8% of the sky. By the time the 6-year project is completed, researchers will have mapped all massive galaxies outside of the dust-clogged plane of our Milky Way galaxy that are visible from the Northern Hemisphere&#x2014;altogether, about one-fourth of the sky that&apos;s visible from Earth.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Family Matters</title>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_783a_F2"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: BEN LANDAU</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Look closely: Each intersection of warp and weft in this blanket represents a single point of genetic data. When taken as a whole, the blanket displays an entire genome&#x2014;that of the sister of bioinformatician Manuel Corpas of the Genome Analysis Centre in Norfolk, U.K.</p>
<p>On 20 June, Corpas began a crowdfunding effort, hoping to raise $20,000 to sequence his own and his family&apos;s entire genomes. The project, he says, was part of his ongoing effort to raise awareness of a coming revolution in personal genomics. &#x201C;My vision is about accessibility,&#x201D; he says. &#x201C;Anyone in the world who would like to know about their genetic data should have the resources to learn about it.&#x201D; As a part of that, he plans to develop free software that can help people interpret their own genomes.</p>
<p>After raising only one-fifth of the money he hoped for, last week Corpas called off the funding campaign&#x2014;but he hasn&apos;t given up his plans to raise awareness. He had already sequenced and published 1 million base pairs for each of his participating relatives through the genetic testing company 23andMe, and thanks to his crowdfunding effort, he says he&apos;s now raised enough to sequence the exomes&#x2014;protein-coding sequences of DNA&#x2014;of his sister and his parents.</p>
<p>Textile artist Ben Landau, who created the blanket, is among those who have uploaded the Corpas family&apos;s free genetic data. In an age when parents may soon be able to alter the genes of their offspring, Landau says his blanket is meant to &#x201C;highlight the sanctity&#x201D; of our unique individual genomes. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scim.ag/corpasgen"><bold>http://scim.ag/corpasgen</bold></ext-link></p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>By the Numbers</title>
<p><bold>799 meters</bold> Record depth in the Gulf of Mexico for the coral <italic>Lophelia pertusa</italic>, found on energy platforms by a team of federal and university scientists.</p>
<p><bold>&#x00A3;15.3 million</bold> Amount of funding, announced on 14 August, for the Royal Society and the U.K. Department for International Development&apos;s Africa Capacity Building Initiative to support research in sub-Saharan Africa.</p>
<p><bold>877 times higher</bold> The extinction rate for freshwater fish species in North America from 1900&#x2013;2010, compared with the rate found in the fossil record (one species per 3 million years), according to U.S. Geological Survey scientists reporting in <italic>BioScience</italic>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>