<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1225538</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1225538</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Books <italic>et al.</italic></subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>books</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI HISTORY PHILO</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Science and Culture</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>#FramingTheArtofScience</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>Melissa A. C.</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff id="aff1">The reviewer is at the Department of Genetics, Cell Biology, and Development, Institute for Translational Neuroscience, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN 55414, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>corn0156@umn.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>17</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6096</issue>
<fpage seq="a">801</fpage>
<lpage>801</lpage>
<product product-type="book"><bold>Epigenetics in the Age of Twitter</bold> Pop Culture and Modern Science <bold><italic>by Gerald Weissmann</italic></bold> Bellevue Literary Press, New York, 2012. 256 pp. Paper, $18.95. ISBN 9781934137390.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>In this collection of essays, Weissmann explores the web of connections linking science and culture.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>In this collection of essays, Weissmann explores the web of connections linking science and culture.</p></abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sherman J. Suter</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Lauren Kmec</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Gerald Weissmann's <italic>Epigenetics in the Age of Twitter</italic> is a compilation of essays that intertwine the profound connections of science and art in the context of our modern era, with its rapid proliferation of mobile apps and instantaneous digital chatter. Weissmann (New York University) uses epigenetics, short-term heritable changes in gene expression that are influenced by our environment, to illustrate the selective pressures in the real social network of Western civilization. An avid reader of <italic>The FASEB Journal</italic> may recognize portions of these chapters, as Weissmann has modified his editorials to create a cohesive and entertaining book. It describes current scientific and cultural trends, using little-known stories of obscure scientists as well as common mysteries (such as the correlation between stress and graying hair and whether early Coca-Cola contained cocaine) to illuminate the ongoing challenges scientists face in dealing with scrutiny and criticism, from colleagues and from our broader society.</p>
<p>The book begins with an introduction to the revolution of digital social media, with the growing presence of wikis and Twitter, the formatting of scientific papers, and how tradition is morphing as journals such as PLoS encourage comments and tweets. In a particularly entertaining section, Weissmann treats us to a fictitious set of reactions, including Rosalind Franklin's &#x201C;YOU PEEKED,&#x201D; inserted into Watson and Crick's iconic 1953 publication. Elsewhere, he presents other scientific communication issues, such as the relentless need to publish and the gender gap in authorship and editor positions.</p>
<p>Weissmann also does a fantastic job of highlighting the role of women in both the arts and sciences. He offers excerpts about many prominent women, such as Hypatia, who in fifth-century Alexandria was the only female member of the academy, taught mathematics and philosophy, and was murdered by the mob for all she represented and political jealousy. Other examples&#x2014;including Marie Curie, Carol Greider, and Elizabeth Blackburn, who have broken the Nobel Prize glass ceiling and inspired women all over the world&#x2014;call attention to the accomplishments and struggles of women in the sciences.</p>
<p>Each essay provides its fair share of wit and satire, poignantly illustrating faults or curiosities in current scientific thought or public discourse of the scientific realm. Weissmann, an immunologist obviously well versed in vernacular, even pokes fun at his own field. In the essay &#x201C;Inflammation Is Complicated: From Metchnikoff to Meryl Streep,&#x201D; he satirizes the notoriously complex role of inflammation and self-destruction. &#x201C;Our cells in combat are bathed by evil humors with acronyms worthy of the Pentagon&#x2014;C5a, C3a, IFN, IL, MIF, etc.&#x2014;to which they can react in both pro- and anti-inflammatory modes. Signals from &#x2018;helper&#x2019; and &#x2018;suppressor&#x2019; lymphocytes trigger cellular signals via JAKs and the STATs, the NF-kBs and so forth and so on. The CIA would indeed have trouble deciphering the battle orders.&#x201D;</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Electronic nerves.</title>
<p>From Fritz Kahn's <italic>Das Leben des Menschen</italic> (Kosmos, Stuttgart, 1926).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_801a_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: COURTESY BELLEVUE LITERARY PRESS</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Interspersed within are subtle warnings that we ought not be so distracted by the speed of digital chats or the plethora of blogs that we fail to learn from the lessons of the past. Weissmann reminds both current and future scientists how easy it can be to make a difference: &#x201C;a single observation, by a single scientist, can have a profound impact. It's a gift, so to speak, that's ours for the taking.&#x201D; The author also cautions readers that while social media and pop culture may influence opinions of science, pop culture is not science&#x2014;&#x201C;the bottom line is that the world is round, humans evolved from an extinct species and Elvis is dead.&#x201D;</p>
<p>This is the age of Twitter, where unrelated ideas, erratic thoughts, and momentary feelings come together to summarize a life story. Or in this collection of Weissmann's essays, how modern science is evolving in the face of ever-increasing social awareness and scrutiny.</p>
</body>
</article>