<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1225091</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1225091</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Report</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Reports</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>reports</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>CHEMISTRY</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Mixed-Phase Oxide Catalyst Based on Mn-Mullite (Sm, Gd)Mn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> for NO Oxidation in Diesel Exhaust</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Weichao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>&#x2020;</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCool</surname><given-names>Geoffrey</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>&#x2020;</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>Neeti</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Guang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>Bin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>Matt</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>Uschi M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Burtron H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>Gary</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Kyeongjae</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Xianghong (Kelly)</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Nanostellar Inc., 3696 Haven Avenue, Redwood City, CA94063, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>State Key Laboratory of Materials Processing and Die and Mould Technology and School of Materials Science and Engineering, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan 430074, Hubei, China.</aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Center for Applied Energy Research, University of Kentucky, 2540 Research Park Drive, Lexington, KY 40511, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Materials Science and Engineering and Department of Physics, University of Texas at Dallas, Richardson, TX 75080, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>WCU Multiscale Mechanical Design Division, School of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, Seoul National University, Seoul 151-742, Republic of Korea.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:href="wwang@nanostellar.com">wwang@nanostellar.com</email> (W.W.); <email xlink:href="kjcho@utdallas.edu">kjcho@utdallas.edu</email> (K.C.); <email xlink:href="xhao@nanostellar.com">xhao@nanostellar.com</email> (X.H.)</corresp>
<fn id="afn1" fn-type="equal"><label>&#x2020;</label>
<p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>17</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6096</issue>
<fpage>832</fpage>
<lpage>835</lpage>
<history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>05</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>07</month><year>2012</year></date></history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="editor"><title>Cleaning Diesel Exhaust</title><p>One strategy for removing pollutants from diesel engine exhaust is to trap the unburned carbon soot and then to combust the soot with the NO<sub>2</sub> that is generated from NO; the two pollutants are then converted to N<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>. Diesel exhaust is relatively cold, compared to gasoline engine exhaust, and conversion of NO to NO<sub>2</sub> has required the use of platinum catalysts. <bold>W. Wang <italic>et al.</italic></bold> (p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="337" page="832">832</related-article>) now report that a more earth-abundant catalyst, based on Mn-mullite (Sm, Gd)Mn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> metal oxides was able to oxidize NO in simulated diesel exhaust at temperatures as low as 75&#x00B0;C. Spectroscopic studies and quantum chemical modeling suggested that Mn-nitrates formed on Mn-Mn dimer sites were the key intermediates responsible for NO<sub>2</sub> formation.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Costly platinum catalysts for removing nitrogen oxide pollutants could potentially be replaced with metal oxide catalysts.</p></abstract>
<abstract>
<p>Oxidation of nitric oxide (NO) for subsequent efficient reduction in selective catalytic reduction or lean NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> trap devices continues to be a challenge in diesel engines because of the low efficiency and high cost of the currently used platinum (Pt)&#x2013;based catalysts. We show that mixed-phase oxide materials based on Mn-mullite (Sm, Gd)Mn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> are an efficient substitute for the current commercial Pt-based catalysts. Under laboratory-simulated diesel exhaust conditions, this mixed-phase oxide material was superior to Pt in terms of cost, thermal durability, and catalytic activity for NO oxidation. This oxide material is active at temperatures as low as 120&#x00B0;C with conversion maxima of ~45% higher than that achieved with Pt. Density functional theory and diffuse reflectance infrared Fourier transform spectroscopy provide insights into the NO-to-NO<sub>2</sub> reaction mechanism on catalytically active Mn-Mn sites via the intermediate nitrate species.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Phillip D. Szuromi</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Harry Jach</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Diesel engines are attractive because of their higher fuel efficiency than gasoline engines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). However, their lean exhaust with high oxygen (O<sub>2</sub>) content requires specialized devices to reduce the engine-generated nitrogen oxide (NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic>) pollutants, mostly nitric oxide (NO), to environmentally benign nitrogen (N<sub>2</sub>). One popular strategy is the use of selective catalytic reduction (SCR) of NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> with ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>) through the reaction: 2NH<sub>3 </sub>+ NO + NO<sub>2</sub>&#x2192;2N<sub>2 </sub>+ 3H<sub>2</sub>O. The rate of this reaction is maximized (fast SCR) when the NO:NO<sub>2</sub> ratio approaches unity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). A lean NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> trap (LNT) adsorbs NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> under lean conditions and reduces NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> to N<sub>2</sub> under fuel-rich regeneration cycles. NO oxidation products such as nitrogen dioxide (NO<sub>2</sub>) have a higher trapping efficiency on LNT materials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>). In addition to the NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic>-based pollutants, diesel engines also generate black soot with polynuclear aromatic content. One process to remove carbon soot is a continuous regenerable trap (CRT), which uses NO<sub>2</sub> as an oxidant (2NO<sub>2 </sub>+ C&#x2192;CO<sub>2</sub> + 2NO, NO<sub>2 </sub>+ C&#x2192;CO + NO). Oxidation of engine-generated NO to NO<sub>2</sub> is critical in diesel engine emission control for reducing NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> and carbon soot from the tail-pipe exhaust.</p>
<p>To date, no thermally stable material has matched platinum&#x2019;s catalytic performance under diesel exhaust temperatures, despite a substantial amount of work that has been undertaken in search for catalysts based on metal oxides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). Here, we report a class of hydrothermally stable, mixed-phase oxides based on Mn-mullite, (Sm, Gd)Mn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>. This catalyst demonstrates activity at temperatures as low as 120&#x00B0;C and has a ~64% increase in NO oxidation catalytic performance over 2% Pt on &#x03B3;-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> at 300&#x00B0;C. The catalytic behavior is mainly linked to the Mn-Mn dimers on the mullite surface based on characterization methods and quantum-mechanical simulations.</p>
<p>Mixed-phase oxide catalysts were prepared by a coprecipitation method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>). Transition metal, alkaline earth, and rare earth precursors were dissolved in water with a non-ionic surfactant. The pH was adjusted to between 9 and 10 with tetramethylammonium hydroxide, followed by the addition of oxalic acid and hydrogen peroxide. The precipitate was filtered, dried, calcined, and hydrothermally aged (materials and methods S-I).</p>
<p>To evaluate catalytic performance, we exposed the aged sample Mn<sub>7</sub>CeSmSrO<sub>14.83</sub>, labeled MnCe-7:1, to the reactant gas mixture (450 parts per million NO and 10% O<sub>2</sub>) while ramping the temperature up to 350&#x00B0;C to test for NO conversion (materials and methods S-II). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> demonstrates that aged MnCe-7:1 offers improved NO oxidation over the aged 2% Pt on &#x03B3;-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> catalyst, and pure SmMn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> displays reasonable activity during the ramp-down cycle. Furthermore, MnCe-7:1 is active at low temperature (120&#x00B0;C), with a higher NO conversion maximum of ~45% over Pt on the ramp-up cycle. BET measurements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>) revealed that the sample maintained a surface area of ~26 m<sup>2</sup>/g before and after hydrothermal aging.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption>
<p>NO conversion versus ramp-up and ramp-down temperatures for MnCe-7:1 (&#x25CF;), SmMn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> (&#x25A1;), GdSrCeMn<sub>7</sub>O<sub>14.83</sub> (&#x25A0;), and Pt (&#x25CB;).</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_832_F1"></graphic></fig>
<p>X-ray diffraction (XRD) was used to characterize the phases, composition, and average crystallite size of MnCe-7:1 (materials and methods S-III). The XRD spectrum in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref> shows three crystalline phases: mullite [Sm(Ce, Sr)Mn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>], spinel(Mn<sub>3O4</sub>), and fluorite(CeO<sub>2</sub>), with corresponding concentrations of 65.9, 8.2, and 25.9% by weight, respectively. To explore the microstructure and the particle distribution in MnCe-7:1, scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and high-resolution transmission electron microscopy (HRTEM) were used (materials and methods S-IV). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>, SEM results display average particle sizes of ~50 nm, which is consistent with the XRD line-broadening results (SmMn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>, 47.4 nm; Mn<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, 34.9 nm; CeO<sub>2</sub>, 19.0 nm). These particles form interfaces as displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2, C to E</xref>. HRTEM images (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2, D and E</xref>) reveal the crystallite orientations of SmMn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> (110), Mn<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> (021), and CeO<sub>2</sub> (200) and show that CeO<sub>2</sub> forms an interface with the amorphous zone adjacent to the mullite. Within the amorphous region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>), a high concentration [14.8 weight percent (wt %)] of Sr is detected by energy-dispersive x-ray spectroscopy (EDS). Comparatively, a lower Sr concentration, ~0.7 wt %, was identified in the SmMn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> mullite phase.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption>
<p>Microanalysis of catalyst MnCe-7:1. (<bold>A</bold>) XRD patterns corresponding to (a) mullite [Sm (Ce, Sr)Mn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>], (b) spinel Mn<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, and (c) flourite CeO<sub>2</sub>; (<bold>B</bold>) SEM image of MnCe-7:1; (<bold>C</bold>) HRTEM image of MnCe-7:1; (<bold>D</bold> to <bold>E</bold>) crystallite orientations, amorphous regions, and interface information; (<bold>F</bold>) side view of the ideal and stepped mullite (110) surface; (<bold>G</bold> and <bold>H</bold>) atomistic models for ideal and stepped (110) SmMn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> surfaces, respectively. Red, pink, and light green balls represent O, Mn, and Sm, respectively, while the vertices represent subsurface atoms with the same color scheme.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_832_F2"></graphic></fig>
<p>To understand the NO oxidation reaction, we performed diffuse reflectance infrared Fourier transform spectroscopy (DRIFTS) on MnCe-7:1 (materials and methods S-V). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> depicts the time evolution of NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> species at 200&#x00B0;C in NO and NO + O<sub>2</sub> gas environments. Density functional theory (DFT) calculations (materials and methods S-VI) were conducted to determine the wavenumbers of nitrosyl (NO), nitrite (NO<sub>2</sub>), and nitrate (NO<sub>3</sub>) on the relevant (110) mullite surface (supplementary text S-VIII). Wavenumbers of NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> species on manganese oxides have been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>). Gas-phase NO exhibits N-O stretching frequencies at 1911 and 1846 cm<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. Bands located at 1630 and 1600 cm<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> likely correspond to bidentate Mn-nitrate and monodentate Mn-nitrite on the mullite surface, respectively. Also, the NO<sub>2</sub> (g) molecular stretching mode (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>) is 1628 to 1654 cm<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, which overlaps with NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> species on the surface. NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> species on Sm sites are found at 1553 cm<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> (nitrate) and 1309 cm<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> (nitrite). Ce-correlated bands, centered at 1400 cm<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>), are not found. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, with only NO flowing through the sample, bands positioned at 1600 and 1630 cm<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> (Mn-nitrite) diminish over time, indicating the consumption of surface oxygen on the mullite. When O<sub>2</sub> is introduced with the existing NO feed gas, these two specific bands are restored. This displays an equilibrium between Mn-NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> formation and conversion into gas-phase NO<sub>2</sub>. Hence, these DRIFTS spectra provide evidence for NO-to-NO<sub>2</sub> conversion on Mn-catalytic sites.</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption>
<p>Evolution of DRIFTS spectra at 200&#x00B0;C on MnCe 7:1 during exposure to NO and NO + O<sub>2</sub> feed gases with time.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_832_F3"></graphic></fig>
<p>The aim of DFT atomistic modeling is to apply first principles to elucidate the likely reaction mechanism and possible intermediate species participating in the catalytic cycle. Here, we focus on the NO oxidation reaction occurring on the (110) surface of SmMn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> on the basis of information from HRTEM images. Weak NO and O<sub>2</sub> adsorption (&lt;0.24 eV) was determined by DFT calculations on this ideal (110) surface, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2G</xref>. In addition, lattice oxygen is unlikely to react because oxygen-vacancy formation on this ideal surface requires 2.2 to 4.0 eV. Owing to the catalytic inertness of the ideal (110) surface, (110) stepped surfaces were investigated. DFT-based screening established that Mn-Mn dimers on the stepped surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2H</xref>) are responsible for activating oxygen molecules. Spontaneous dissociation of O<sub>2</sub> at the dimer sites leads to surface mobile atomic oxygen with a diffusion energy barrier of 0.55 eV (supplementary text S-IX). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> displays a potential NO oxidation reaction route on the stepped mullite surface. On the O-covered Mn-Mn sites, incident NO (g) adsorbs on the O site to form Mn-nitrite (-NO<sub>2</sub>). Monodentate Mn-nitrite (-NO<sub>2</sub>) undergoes a transformation to bidentate Mn-nitrate (-NO<sub>3</sub>) with an energy barrier of 0.72 eV. NO<sub>2</sub> is subsequently released via a distorted monodentate Mn-nitrate transition state by overcoming an energy barrier of 0.90 eV, leaving behind a bridged O atom. Two adjacent Mn-Mn sites with a bridged O energetically prefer to adsorb O<sub>2</sub> compared to NO by 0.66 eV. In the last step of the reaction cycle, O<sub>2</sub> gas molecules decompose into atomic O (energy barrier of 0.83 eV), thereby restoring the surface to fully O-covered Mn-Mn sites, which become available for the next cycle of NO conversion. As a result, we propose NO<sub>2</sub> desorption from manganese nitrates as the rate-limiting step with an energy barrier of 0.90 eV.</p>
<fig id="F4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption>
<p>Proposed reaction mechanism of NO conversion into NO<sub>2</sub> (g) on the stepped mullite (110) surface. TS, transition state.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_832_F4"></graphic></fig>
<p>By comparison, the activation energy of NO oxidation on fresh Pt particles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13"><italic>13</italic></xref>) is 0.82 to 0.87 eV, but aged and sintered Pt displays a lower activity than aged MnCe-7:1. Moreover, the asymmetry of the SmMn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> NO oxidation curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> suggests that there is NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> inhibition to NO oxidation during ramp-up, corroborating that the rate-determining step involves NO<sub>2</sub> desorption. MnCe-7:1 shows less inhibition for the ramp-up and ramp-down cycles.</p>
<p>Four key factors contribute to the overall catalytic activity of MnCe-7:1. Mn dimer sites are established as the main source of activity on SmMn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>. Addition of Sr increases the surface area, exposing more active sites. Ceria adsorbs and dissociates O<sub>2</sub> such that O* can diffuse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>) to Mn-Mn dimers at the interface. Lastly, the stabilized spinel Mn<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> phase results in additional high-temperature (330&#x00B0; to 350&#x00B0;C) catalytic activity. Deviating too far from the reported composition (Mn<sub>7</sub>SrSmCeO<sub>14.83</sub>) may result in lower catalytic activity. For instance, an excessive amount of Sr leads to poor NO conversion because of the potential formation of Sr-perovskite&#x2013;based oxides.</p>
<p>To determine how MnCe-7:1 performs in simulated diesel exhaust, we added MnCe-7:1 as a top layer to a commercial-style PtPd diesel oxidation catalyst (materials and methods S-VII). Coated cores were aged and subjected to a gaseous mixture of NO, CO, CO<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>6</sub>, C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>8</sub>, <italic>n-</italic>decane, steam, and O<sub>2</sub> in He. The results show that the additional MnCe-7:1 layer was not detrimental to CO and HC performance and that NO oxidation was enhanced (supplementary text S-X).</p>
</body>
<back><app-group><app>
<title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/337/6096/832/DC1">www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/337/6096/832/DC1</ext-link></p>
<p>Materials and Methods (S-I to S-VII)</p>
<p>Supplementary Text (S-VIII to S-X)</p>
<p>Fig. S1 to S6</p>
<p>Tables S1 to S3</p>
<p>References (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19"><italic>19</italic></xref>)</p></supplementary-material></app></app-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="book">C. H. Bartholomoew, R. J. Farrauto, <italic>Fundamentals of Industrial Catalytic Process</italic> (Wiley, Hoboken, NJ, ed. 2, 2006).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tas</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Hardeveld</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Veldhuizen</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Plasma Chem. Plasma Process.</source> 
<volume>17</volume>, 
<fpage>371</fpage> (<year>1997</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1021818313047</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niessen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schruft</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neiger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The influence of ethene on the conversion of in a dielectric barrier discharge</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. D</source> 
<volume>31</volume>, 
<fpage>542</fpage> (<year>1998</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0022-3727/31/5/011</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>NO and NO <sub>2</sub> Adsorption on barium oxide: Model study of the trapping stage of NO <italic><sub>x</sub></italic> conversion via lean NO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic> Traps</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. B</source> 
<volume>106</volume>, 
<fpage>4172</fpage> (<year>2002</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp0133992</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahlberg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Strontium-doped perovskites rival platinum catalysts for treating NOx in simulated diesel exhaust</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>327</volume>, 
<fpage>1624</fpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1184087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20339068</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teraoka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Catalytic oxidation of nitrogen monoxide over La1&#x2212;xCexCoO3 perovskites</article-title>. <source>Catal. Today</source> 
<volume>126</volume>, 
<fpage>400</fpage> (<year>2007</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cattod.2007.06.032</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="book">P. Patnaik, <italic>Dean's Analytical Chemistry Handbook</italic> (McGraw-Hill, New York, ed. 2, 2004.).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunauer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emmett</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teller</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Adsorption of gases in multimolecular layers</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source> 
<volume>60</volume>, 
<fpage>309</fpage> (<year>1938</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja01269a023</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Mechanism study of NO catalytic oxidation over MnO<italic><sub>x</sub></italic>/TiO<sub>2</sub> Catalysts</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. C</source> 
<volume>115</volume>, 
<fpage>8214</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp200920z</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chemistry WebBook</surname><given-names>NIST</given-names></name></person-group>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://webbook.nist.gov/">http://webbook.nist.gov/.</ext-link></citation></ref>
<ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fornasiero</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaspar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Infrared study of nitric oxide (NO) adsorption and conversion on CeO2-ZrO2 mixed oxide</article-title>. <source>Collect. Czech. Chem. Commun.</source> 
<volume>66</volume>, 
<fpage>1287</fpage> (<year>2001</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1135/cccc20011287</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mulla</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Reaction of NO and O<sub>2</sub> to NO<sub>2</sub> on Pt: Kinetics and catalyst deactivation</article-title>. <source>J. Catal.</source> 
<volume>25</volume>, 
<fpage>389</fpage> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcat.2006.05.016</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tritsaris</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greeley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossmeisl</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x00F8;rskov</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Atomic-scale modeling of particle size effects for the oxygen reduction reaction on Pt</article-title>. <source>Catal. Lett.</source> 
<volume>141</volume>, 
<fpage>909</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10562-011-0637-8</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skorodumova</surname><given-names>N. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simak</surname><given-names>S. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundqvist</surname><given-names>B. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrikosov</surname><given-names>I. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Quantum origin of the oxygen storage capability of ceria</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source> 
<volume>89</volume>, 
<fpage>166601</fpage> (<year>2002</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.89.166601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12398742</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.crystalimpact.com/pcd/">www.crystalimpact.com/pcd/</ext-link></citation></ref>
<ref id="R16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Becke</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parr</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Density functional theory of electronic structure</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem.</source> 
<volume>100</volume>, 
<fpage>12974</fpage> (<year>1996</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp960669l</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henkelman</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x00F3;nsson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Improved tangent estimate in the nudged elastic band method for finding minimum energy paths and saddle points</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source> 
<volume>113</volume>, 
<fpage>9978</fpage> (<year>2000</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.1323224</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kagomiya</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchiyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Structure and ferroelectricity of RMn 2 O 5</article-title>. <source>Ferroelectrics</source> 
<volume>280</volume>, 
<fpage>131</fpage> (<year>2002</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00150190214799</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guelachvili</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>High resolution wavenumber standards for the infrared</article-title>. <source>Spectrochim. Acta A Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc.</source> 
<volume>52</volume>, 
<fpage>717</fpage> (<year>1996</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0584-8539(96)01717-5</pub-id></citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title><p>DFT calculations were performed at the Texas Advanced Computer Center (TACC). The authors acknowledge Nanostellar for supporting this work. A provisional patent application for MnCe-7:1 has been filed on Nanostellar&#x2019;s behalf: U.S. Provisional Patent No 61/561,771. K.C. was supported by the NRF of Korea through WCU program (Grant No. R-31-2009-000-10083-0).</p>
</ack></back>
</article>