<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="article-commentary" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1224869</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1224869</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Perspective</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>perspective</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Chemistry</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>CHEMISTRY</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Molecule Formation in Ultrahigh Magnetic Fields</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Schmelcher</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff id="aff1">Zentrum f&#x00FC;r Optische Quantentechnologien, Universit&#x00E4;t Hamburg, 22761 Hamburg, Germany.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>pschmelc@physnet.uni-hamburg.de</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage>302</fpage>
<lpage>303</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>An extreme magnetic field applied perpendicular to a diatomic or linear molecule increases its bond strength through a paramagnetic interaction.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="excerpt">
<p>Strong electric and magnetic fields tend to have opposite effects on the formation and structure of molecules. Strong electric fields always tend to separate the oppositely charged particles (electrons and nuclei), which causes molecules to ionize and dissociate. However, for strong homogeneous and static magnetic fields, binding can be strengthened. For hydrogen, the simplest atom, a certain class of its quantum states, including the ground state, becomes increasingly bound with increasing magnetic field strength (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). The electronic cloud shrinks transverse to the magnetic field, and because of the immediate proximity of the attractive nucleus, the overall energy decreases. This feature transfers to diatomic and linear-chain molecules, where the chemical binding energy increases and the corresponding bond distances decrease. The field strengths needed are far beyond the strongest available in the laboratory (30 to 40 T) but can be encountered in the atmospheres of magnetic white dwarfs (10<sup>2</sup> to 10<sup>5</sup> T) and neutron stars (&gt;10<sup>7</sup> T). On page 327 of this issue, Lange <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) show that, in addition to this diamagnetic enhanced binding, there exists an elementary paramagnetic bonding mechanism that occurs for the perpendicular orientation of a diatomic molecule with respect to the external magnetic field.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Phillip D. Szuromi</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Jeff Cook</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Strong electric and magnetic fields tend to have opposite effects on the formation and structure of molecules. Strong electric fields always tend to separate the oppositely charged particles (electrons and nuclei), which causes molecules to ionize and dissociate. However, for strong homogeneous and static magnetic fields, binding can be strengthened. For hydrogen, the simplest atom, a certain class of its quantum states, including the ground state, becomes increasingly bound with increasing magnetic field strength (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). The electronic cloud shrinks transverse to the magnetic field, and because of the immediate proximity of the attractive nucleus, the overall energy decreases. This feature transfers to diatomic and linear-chain molecules, where the chemical binding energy increases and the corresponding bond distances decrease. The field strengths needed are far beyond the strongest available in the laboratory (30 to 40 T) but can be encountered in the atmospheres of magnetic white dwarfs (10<sup>2</sup> to 10<sup>5</sup> T) and neutron stars (&gt;10<sup>7</sup> T). On page <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="337" page="327" issue="6092">327</related-article> of this issue, Lange <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) show that, in addition to this diamagnetic enhanced binding, there exists an elementary paramagnetic bonding mechanism that occurs for the perpendicular orientation of a diatomic molecule with respect to the external magnetic field.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Stronger against the field.</title>
<p>A schematic illustration of (<bold>A</bold>) a rotating diatomic molecule in field-free space and (<bold>B</bold>) the parallel and orthogonal configuration of the molecule in the presence of a high magnetic field. Lange <italic>et al.</italic> show that the bond strength increases for the perpendicular case through paramagnetic interactions.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_302_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: P. HUEY/<italic>SCIENCE</italic></attrib>
</fig>
<p>Strong magnetic fields cause novel effects in molecular structures and dynamics mainly because of the pronounced anisotropic character of the magnetic forces. Accounting for these effects requires the development of innovative computational approaches for their theoretical description (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). In the absence of electric and magnetic fields (a field-free space), the binding of the nuclei via the electrons depends only on the internuclear distance. In a magnetic field, however, the orientation of the internuclear axis of a diatomic molecule with respect to the external field plays a crucial role, and the electronic binding energy becomes a two-dimensional potential energy surface (see the figure).</p>
<p>For a diatomic or linear molecule, the lowest-energy configuration is typically that of the molecular axis parallel to the magnetic field. The corresponding angular motion of the molecular axis changes from free rotation in zero field to a hindered rotation and finally pure vibrational motion in strong fields. This response is found by Lange <italic>et al.</italic> for the ground state of <sup>1</sup>&#x2211;<sub>g</sub> symmetry of H<sub>2</sub>. With increasing field strength, the spin-triplet states (unpaired spins) decrease their energy gap to the spin-singlet states through the corresponding Zeeman shift. Finally, above a certain critical field strength, the <sup>3</sup>&#x2211;<sub>u</sub> state represents the ground state of H<sub>2</sub>, which is then, for even stronger fields, replaced by the <sup>3</sup>&#x220F;<sub>u</sub> state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>The <sup>3</sup>&#x2211;<sub>u</sub> state in field-free space cannot accommodate any vibrational states, nor can it even for strong fields for molecular and magnetic field axes aligned parallel. However, for a perpendicular magnetic field, dramatic changes were found by Lange <italic>et al.</italic> through extensive quantum chemical computations. The antibonding orbitals responsible for the unbound character of the <sup>3</sup>&#x2211;<sub>u</sub> state undergo a metamorphosis for a perpendicular field that stabilizes the molecule. The field-induced bonding in this case is neither of covalent nor of ionic nature, but represents a different bonding mechanism with paramagnetic character. The latter is based on the lowering of the kinetic energy and the antiparallel orientation of the acquired spatial angular momentum in the presence of a strong magnetic field. A simple model for the field-dependent molecular orbitals confirms this basic mechanism.</p>
<p>The paramagnetic bonding mechanism is not based on the correlations of the electronic motion, although they slightly change it quantitatively. It already appears within Hartree-Fock theory, in which the electrons move in their respective averaged field. To confirm the appearance of this mechanism beyond the hydrogen molecule, Lange <italic>et al.</italic> have explored the He<sub>2</sub> spin-singlet ground state that is weakly bound by dispersion forces if there is no external field. In a strong field on the order of a few 10<sup>5</sup> T, He<sub>2</sub> exhibits a perpendicular orientation while its bond distance decreases by a factor of 3 and its dissociation energy increases several hundred times. Here, the same mechanism is at work as in the case of the <sup>3</sup>&#x2211;<sub>u</sub> state of H<sub>2</sub>, triggered by the change of character of the antibonding orbitals.</p>
<p>Atoms, molecules, and condensed matter systems exposed to strong magnetic fields represent a fascinating topic, and the work by Lange <italic>et al.</italic> has added a key bonding mechanism. The competition between the anisotropy-introducing magnetic field and the attractive and repulsive Coulomb forces is responsible for an enormous complexity and diversity of the microscopic behavior. Indeed, the existing investigations show that different excited states of a molecule, or ground states of similar molecules, can behave in a vastly different manner, and provide a first look at a largely unexplored area: the world of magnetized matter.</p>
<p>It might seem that this world is hidden from us by the requirement of enormous laboratory field strengths. However, available field strengths are progressively increasing, in particular for pulsed magnetic fields in the milli- or microsecond regime that are already achieving fields of hundreds of teslas. Besides this, standard laboratory magnetic fields of a few teslas are sufficient to introduce novel magnetic properties into highly excited Rydberg states (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>), for which the weakened Coulomb force is comparable to the paramagnetic or diamagnetic forces, or both. In this respect, the very weakly bound Rydberg molecules with a huge bond length and a large electric dipole moment, originally predicted by Greene <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>) and recently found for a specific class experimentally by Pfau and co-workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>), are of particular interest and might be an ideal system to probe strong magnetic field effects in the laboratory.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruder</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herold</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Atoms in Strong Magnetic Fields</source> (<publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>, <year>1994</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Schmelcher</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweizer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>, Eds., <source>Atoms and Molecules in Strong External Fields</source> (<publisher-name>Plenum</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <year>1998</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wintgen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Phys. Rep.</source> <volume>183</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage> (<year>1989</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Science</source> <volume>337</volume>, <fpage>327</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmelcher</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cederbaum</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Phys. Rev. A</source> <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>672</fpage> (<year>1988</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tellgren</surname><given-names>E. I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source> <volume>129</volume>, <fpage>154114</fpage> (<year>2008</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kravchenko</surname><given-names>Yu. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liberman</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Phys. Rev. A</source> <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>R2510</fpage> (<year>1997</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Detmer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Phys. Rev. A</source> <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>1767</fpage> (<year>1998</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Rydberg Atoms</source> (<publisher-name>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>, <year>1994</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source> <volume>85</volume>, <fpage>2458</fpage> (<year>2000</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bendkowsky</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Nature</source> <volume>458</volume>, <fpage>1005</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>