<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1224877</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1224877</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Books <italic>et al.</italic></subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>books</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>COMP/MATH</subject><subject>SCI HISTORY PHILO</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Computers</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>MANIACal Roots</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>McCusker</surname><given-names>James P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>The reviewer is at the Tetherless World Constellation, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, and Department of Pathology, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, CT 06510, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>james.mccusker@yale.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage seq="a">297</fpage>
<lpage>297</lpage>
<product product-type="book"><bold>Turing's Cathedral: The Origins of the Digital Universe.</bold> George Dyson. Pantheon, New York, 2012. 443 pp. $29.95, C$34. ISBN 9780375422775. Allen Lane, London. &#x00A3;25. ISBN 9780713997507.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Dyson's discussion of the foundations of computer science and computer modeling highlights work at the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Dyson's discussion of the foundations of computer science and computer modeling highlights work at the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton.</p></abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sherman J. Suter</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Cynthia Howe</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>There's a certain vertiginous rush that new programmers experience when they make that transition from being barely able to get a computer to do their bidding to genuine mastery of the machine. It's the rush of vast possibilities opening up. <italic>Turing's Cathedral</italic> captures that feeling of possibility while recounting the path of computer science from groundwork mathematics to the realization of the first computing engines. George Dyson follows the stories of John von Neumann and other members of the Institute for Advanced Study (IAS) at Princeton from the theoretical foundations of computing to the invention of the first general-purpose computer.</p>
<p>Technology writer Dyson does an excellent job showing how most modern sciences, from nuclear physics to the beginnings of meteorology and genetics, have been driven and influenced by computational models. Nuclear weapons and the computer essentially enabled each other's invention. A roll call of notable scientists from Robert Oppenheimer and Martin Schwarzschild to Albert Einstein make their impact on&#x2014;and are impacted by&#x2014;the computer project. Dyson also records the creation of computer science as a separate discipline from mathematics.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>MANIAC, the IAS computer.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_297a_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: ALAN RICHARDS/SHELBY WHITE AND LEON LEVY ARCHIVES CENTER, INSTITUTE FOR ADVANCED STUDY, PRINCETON, NJ</attrib>
</fig>
<p>The foundations of computer science came from something of a crisis in traditional mathematics. Kurt G&#x00F6;del, who later joined the IAS, proved that no logical system (including mathematics) can prove its own consistency. Dyson traces how this problem directly led from the incompleteness theorem to the halting problem to the first working general-purpose computers. The halting problem (which asks whether it is possible to predict if a Turing machine running a particular program will finish in less than infinite time), it turns out, offers a key distinction between conventional mathematics and computer science. It essentially means that many things in computer science cannot be proven but must be determined through experimentation.</p>
<p>That they were witnessing the birth of a new science went unappreciated by most mathematicians at the IAS. The tension between them and the engineers and scientists who were designing and building the computer is clearly illustrated in the story of Julian Bigelow, von Neumann's chief engineer and computer architect. Dyson also records how Kl&#x00E1;ri von Neumann, John's wife, became one of the world's first computer programmers when she was recruited from population research to perform the first Monte Carlo simulations on the critical mass reactions in atomic weapons.</p>
<p>Dyson is at his weakest when relating some older ideas to potential modern counterparts. For instance, he draws a line from the pioneering ideas of artificial life that drove some early experiments on computers to modern apps, which are simply well-packaged computer applications. A better comparison might have been to computer worms and viruses, which serve as software agents that infiltrate computers to particular ends. But these are quibbles. Dyson offers a wonderful description of the worlds of possibility that opened up as computer science first established itself in a corner of Olden Farm in New Jersey.</p>
</body>
</article>