<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ECOLOGY</subject><subject>SCI COMMUN</subject><subject>SCI POLICY</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Around the World</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage seq="b">274</fpage>
<lpage>275</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>In science news around the world this week, the Australian government has designated 10 million hectares of land in the Tanami Desert as a conservation zone; the U.K. government has accepted the recommendations of a report that encouraged greater open-access publishing of publicly funded research; a U.S. panel has suggested scaling down an agro-defense lab; three researchers received a life sciences award sponsored by Teodoro Obiang Nguema Mbasogo, the dictator of Equatorial Guinea; and more than 2000 scientists protested what organizers called a &#x22;systemic attack on science&#x22; by Canada's Conservative government.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>In science news around the world this week, the Australian government has designated 10 million hectares of land in the Tanami Desert as a conservation zone; the U.K. government has accepted the recommendations of a report that encouraged greater open-access publishing of publicly funded research; a U.S. panel has suggested scaling down an agro-defense lab; three researchers received a life sciences award sponsored by Teodoro Obiang Nguema Mbasogo, the dictator of Equatorial Guinea; and more than 2000 scientists protested what organizers called a &#x22;systemic attack on science&#x22; by Canada's Conservative government.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_274b_F1"></graphic>
</fig>
<boxed-text content-type="story_index">
<def-list>
<def-item><term>1 - Tanami Desert, Australia</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec1">Conservation in the Desert</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>2 - London</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2">U.K. Moves Toward Open Access</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>3 - Washington, D.C.</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3">Panel Pushes to Scale Down Agro-Defense Lab</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>4 - Paris</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec4">Researchers Receive Controversial UNESCO Awards</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>5 - Ottawa, Canada</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec5">Scientists Protest Canada&apos;s Budget Cuts as Antiscience</xref></p></def></def-item>
</def-list>
</boxed-text>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec1">
<title>Tanami Desert, Australia</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Conservation in the Desert</title>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_274b_F2"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: &#x00A9; THEO ALLOFS/CORBIS; (INSET) &#x00A9; GREG HAROLD/AUSCAPE/MINDEN PICTURES/CORBIS</attrib>
</fig>
<p>The Australian government has designated 10 million hectares of land in the Tanami Desert of the Northern Territory as a conservation zone&#x2014;the largest in the country. The Tanami Desert is home to many endangered species, including the bilby, a long-eared marsupial (shown), and the great desert skink, a burrowing lizard that builds elaborate tunnel systems. The animals have been threatened by feral cats and foxes, as well as brush fires and cattle grazing.</p>
<p>The region will be administered as an Indigenous Protected Area, under the supervision of indigenous communities. The government plans to spend $1.6 million over the next 2 years to fund the rangers; the Nature Conservancy will also contribute $500,000 to help manage the area.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec2">
<title>London</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>U.K. Moves Toward Open Access</title>
<p>The U.K. government has accepted the recommendations of a report released last month that encouraged greater open access publishing of publicly funded research. Officials announced on 16 July that over the next year, they will work to require studies wholly or partly funded by tax-payers to be published in journals that are free to readers. The government&apos;s decision means that by 1 April 2013, all papers from government-funded research must be published in an open access journal; if not, the journal must make the paper open access after 6 months.</p>
<p>The original report, chaired by sociologist Janet Finch, recommended the open access publication requirement because it would maximize the economic benefit of government-funded research. But the move is getting a critical response from some researchers and universities who fear it could increase costs. The government&apos;s decision could also mean extra costs for U.K. universities, critics say, because in addition to paying article processing charges, research and university libraries will also have to continue paying for subscriptions until other countries adopt similar policies. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scim.ag/Finchrep"><bold>http://scim.ag/Finchrep</bold></ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec3">
<title>Washington, D.C.</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Panel Pushes to Scale Down Agro-Defense Lab</title>
<p>Earlier this year, the Obama Administration suspended plans for a $1 billion, highly secure laboratory for studying dangerous animal diseases, called the National Bio and Agro-Defense Facility (NBAF). Now, a new study from the U.S. National Academies suggests rescuing the facility by scaling it down.</p>
<p>NBAF was intended as a replacement for the aging Plum Island Animal Disease Center in New York. But amid controversies&#x2014;including environmental groups&apos; concerns for the site&apos;s planned location in Manhattan, Kansas, over the potential release of pathogens&#x2014;the Department of Homeland Security (DHS) has struggled to secure funding from Congress, and the estimated cost of the facility grew from $450 million to more than $1 billion.</p>
<p>DHS had asked the National Academies to study whether NBAF&apos;s mission could be achieved by continuing with the Plum Island center or relying on biocontainment labs in other countries. The study concludes that neither option can enable the United States to protect animal and public health in the long term; instead, it recommends reducing the price tag for NBAF by scaling down activities such as training, research on small animals, and vaccination research, and outsourcing them to existing animal pathogen labs. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scim.ag/AgroLab"><bold>http://scim.ag/AgroLab</bold></ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec4">
<title>Paris</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Researchers Receive Controversial UNESCO Awards</title>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_274b_F3"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: REBECCA BLACKWELL/AP PHOTO</attrib>
</fig>
<p>A tumultuous and divisive episode at the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) ended Tuesday when three researchers received a life sciences award sponsored by Teodoro Obiang Nguema Mbasogo, the dictator of Equatorial Guinea. A broad coalition of human rights advocates, scientists, and health experts had fought almost until the last minute to prevent the ceremony from happening. They say the award is an attempt by Obiang to buy credibility for his regime, which stands accused of human rights violations.</p>
<p>The winners of the prize are Maged Al-Sherbiny from Egypt, for his research on vaccines and diagnostics against hepatitis C and schistosomiasis; plant scientist Felix Dapare Dakora from Tshwane University of Technology, Pretoria, in South Africa for his work on legumes and soil bacteria; and Rossana Arroyo of the Centre for Research and Advanced Studies of Mexico&apos;s National Polytechnic Institute, who studies trichomoniasis, a parasitic disease. All three were at the ceremony, which was boycotted by many Western countries. UNESCO Director-General Irina Bokova, who opposed the prize but was overruled in March by UNESCO&apos;s 58-member Executive Board, didn&apos;t attend either. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scim.ag/Obiangaward"><bold>http://scim.ag/Obiangaward</bold></ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec5">
<title>Ottawa, Canada</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Scientists Protest Canada&apos;s Budget Cuts as Antiscience</title> 
<fig id="F4" position="float"> 
<graphic xlink:href="337_275a_F1"/> 
<attrib>CREDIT: MICHAEL &amp; RICHARD WEBSTER</attrib> 
</fig> 
<p>Led by the Grim Reaper, a mock funeral procession of more than 2000 scientists marched on Canada&apos;s Parliament last week to protest what organizers called a &#x201C;systemic attack on science&#x201D; by the country&apos;s Conservative government. The &#x201C;Death of Evidence&#x201D; rally was organized by students at the University of Ottawa to protest budget cuts that will close the Experimental Lakes Area in northwestern Ontario and the Polar Environment Atmospheric Research Laboratory, two key environmental research programs; eliminate funding for a national science adviser; and convert the mandatory long form of the Canadian national census into a voluntary one, among other changes (<italic>Science</italic>, 29 June, p. 
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/336/6089/1627.full">1627</ext-link>).</p> 
<p>The rally was timed to coincide with a large, international meeting of evolutionary biologists, many of whom joined the march. &#x201C;Recent actions by the federal government suggest that our state is frightened by evidence and is retreating into a fantasy world,&#x201D; says Arne Mooers, a biologist at Simon Fraser University, Burnaby. The Canadian government says the cuts are necessary to balance the budget and fund other, more-applied areas of science.</p> 
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
</article>