<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1224872</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1224872</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Books <italic>et al.</italic></subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>books</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ECOLOGY</subject><subject>NEUROSCIENCE</subject><subject>PHYSIOLOGY</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Physiology</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Finding Their Place In the World</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yamahachi</surname><given-names>Homare</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>The reviewer is at the Kavli Institute for Systems Neuroscience and Centre for the Biology of Memory, Medical Technical Research Centre, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, 7030 Trondheim, Norway.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>homare.yamahachi@ntnu.no</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage seq="a">294</fpage>
<lpage>294</lpage>
<product product-type="book"><bold>Nature's Compass: The Mystery of Animal Navigation.</bold> James L. Gould and Carol Grant Gould. Princeton University Press, Princeton, NJ, 2012. 310 pp. $29.95, &#x00A3;19.95. ISBN 9780691140452.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>The Goulds survey the means by which animals navigate around their neighborhoods and across the globe.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>The Goulds survey the means by which animals navigate around their neighborhoods and across the globe.</p></abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sherman J. Suter</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Harry Jach</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Headed home. Rock pigeon (<italic>Columba livia</italic>).</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_294a_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: ERNIE JANES/ALAMY</attrib>
</fig>
<p>For most of human history, the clear understanding of the position of the Sun, the Moon, and stars and their movements across the sky was invaluable to human navigation. Sailing, especially on the open ocean without any visible landmarks, posed serious challenges to early civilizations. Nowadays, with the help of technologies such as Global Positioning Systems (GPS), navigation has become seemingly trivial. However, many nonhuman animals (including birds, turtles, and butterflies) can migrate thousands of kilometers and locate places with a precision we have only recently achieved. In <italic>Nature's Compass</italic>, evolutionary biologist James Gould (Princeton University) and science writer Carol Grant Gould discuss how animals carry out such extraordinary feats using only their senses.</p>
<p>While focusing mostly on honey bees and homing pigeons (which they have studied extensively in their own lab), the authors provide nonspecialists with a clear introduction to animal navigation. They warn that in analyzing animals' abilities to know locations and directions, we are prone to &#x201C;imagining that animals see challenges&#x201D; and &#x201C;use the same strategies to solve the problems&#x201D; as we do. In fact, the mechanisms used&#x2014;the position of the sun and stars, polarized light and color gradients, endogenous timers, landmark memory and cognitive maps, magnetic fields, and more&#x2014;vary both among taxa and within individuals (depending on context and age).</p>
<p>The Goulds guide readers through the multiple ways in which honey bees illuminate animals' navigation systems. In one intriguing example, forager bees were trained to a food location on a boat in a lake. Even though their dances back at the hive were vigorous, no recruits came to the boat. However, once the boat was moved close to the far shore, new bees began to appear. Bees do not usually fly over water, and the authors suggest that the bees at the hive decoded the direction and distance cues. But when positioning the food source in their mental maps located it in the middle of the lake, they decided not to act on the information.</p>
<p>Having been bred to return to their loft quickly and directly, homing pigeons provide a means for addressing essential questions that would be difficult to answer when working with &#x201C;wide-ranging, twice-a-year migrants.&#x201D; The authors describe how the disruptive effects of solar storms on homing ability led Gould and others to propose that the pigeons have magnetic maps. Further testing revealed that the birds' location sense is greatly perturbed by magnetic-field anomalies. Using a magnetic map to return requires that the birds be able to sense small differences in field strength and direction. The Goulds mention the putative detector (a magnetite-rich organ in the beak), but they also note recent alternative findings. In addition to birds, sea turtles, spiny lobsters, and newts have been shown to use magnetic information to orient themselves.</p>
<p>The authors conclude with a short consideration of how understanding migration and its evolution may prove crucial for conservation in the face of habitat loss and changing climate.</p>
<p><italic>Nature's Compass</italic> provides a wonderful account of efforts to unravel the mysteries of animal migration. Effectively drawing on their own experiences and the extensive scientific literature in the field, the Goulds explain what we currently know about how animals locate their positions. Their survey also offers an accessible starting point for those who might wish to improve our understanding of the topic.</p>
</body>
</article>