<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI COMMUN</subject><subject>GENETICS</subject><subject>MEDICINE</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Profile: Bert Vogelstein</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Cancer Genetics With an Edge</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>Jocelyn</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage>282</fpage>
<lpage>284</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Their lab helped reveal how faulty genes cause cancer, but Bert Vogelstein and Kenneth Kinzler sometimes irk colleagues with their &#x201C;reality check&#x201D; comments on genomic medicine.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Bert Vogelstein and Kenneth Kinzler, who co-direct a lab at the Johns Hopkins University medical campus, helped lay the foundation of cancer genetics by revealing how mutations in key genes lead to a tumor. Their work helped inspire others to use genetics to predict cancer risks and develop personalized cancer treatments. Yet today, Vogelstein often offers what he calls a &#x22;reality check&#x22; on such efforts. In the past few years, Vogelstein and Kinzler have shifted away from discovering new cancer genes to a less glamorous pursuit: using genetic tests to detect common tumors as early as possible, when they are easiest to cure. This is not mainstream work, they say. But it's a natural progression of earlier research, the two said in a recent interview. Their research was never driven by curiosity about biology, Vogelstein says, but by &#x22;an overwhelming desire to empty the cancer clinics across the street.&#x22;</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Gene wizard.</title>
<p>Bert Vogelstein helped launch modern cancer genetics after discovering key mutations.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_282_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: JOE RUBINO</attrib>
</fig>
<p>In April, as scientists at a cancer meeting in Chicago were wowing audiences with their new DNA studies, geneticist Bert Vogelstein stood by with a bucket of cold water. At a briefing, he told a roomful of reporters that his own work shows how little value a key genetic approach&#x2014;whole-genome sequencing&#x2014;will have for preventing cancer. Using data from identical twins, his team estimated how well whole-genome tests could spot individuals at risk. Most people, the model showed, would get a negative result because inherited mutations very rarely predispose us to cancer. Yet about one-third of those who test negative will still develop cancer, triggered by environmental factors and bad luck. &#x201C;It would be great if we could determine who will and will not get cancer from sequencing their DNA, but the reality is, we won't,&#x201D; Vogelstein said later.</p>
<p>Vogelstein's sobering message, picked up by <italic>The New York Times</italic> and other publications, irritated some scientists: They claimed the study had flaws and wasn't saying anything new. True, papers with similar findings had been published before, unnoticed by the press. But Vogelstein says that although the bottom line may have been familiar to some scientists, his study used a novel model to quantify the limits of personal genomes for public health. He says he also wanted to drive home the message that the only sure way to reduce cancer is through screening and a healthy lifestyle.</p>
<p>Some colleagues say the paper was a typical dart thrown by Vogelstein, who is known as a contrarian. Vogelstein (a longtime member of <italic>Science</italic>'s board of reviewing editors) and collaborator Kenneth Kinzler, who co-directs their lab at the Johns Hopkins University medical campus, helped lay the foundation of cancer genetics by revealing how mutations in key genes lead to a tumor. Their work helped inspire others to use genetics to predict cancer risks and develop personalized cancer treatments. Yet today, Vogelstein often offers what he calls a &#x201C;reality check&#x201D; on such efforts. Last month, for example, his team warned about a flaw in so-called targeted drugs that dramatically shrink tumors: They inevitably fail when resistant tumor cells take over.</p>
<p>&#x201C;He sees things in very interesting and provocative ways,&#x201D; says cancer geneticist Stephen Chanock of the U.S. National Cancer Institute (NCI) in Bethesda, Maryland. Vogelstein &#x201C;wants to make a quick difference and a quick hit. I would guess he thinks his job is to push the field along,&#x201D; says cancer geneticist Joe Gray of Oregon Health &amp; Science University in Portland. Gray adds: &#x201C;But whenever Bert talks, I listen.&#x201D;</p>
<p>In the past few years, Vogelstein and Kinzler have shifted away from discovering new cancer genes to a less glamorous pursuit: using genetic tests to detect common tumors as early as possible, when they are easiest to cure. This is not mainstream work, they say: &#x201C;Society is fixated on curing advanced cancer. It's considered a success even if you're just reducing patients' cancer burden for a few months, not prolonging their lives for a long time,&#x201D; Vogelstein says. But it's a natural progression of earlier research, the two said in a recent interview at their upper-floor lab in downtown Baltimore, Maryland, two blocks from where Vogelstein was born.</p>
<p>Vogelstein, 63, small and trim with a grizzled beard, irreverent and humorous, wore his usual jeans and a white dress shirt. Kinzler, a tall, boyish-looking 50, was in khakis. Their research was never driven by curiosity about biology, Vogelstein says, but by &#x201C;an overwhelming desire to empty the cancer clinics across the street.&#x201D;</p>
<sec>
<title>Cancer genes</title>
<p>After studying mathematics at the University of Pennsylvania, Vogelstein went to medical school at Johns Hopkins, becoming a pediatric oncologist. His frustration at being unable to explain cancer&#x2014;to tell parents why their 4-year-old daughter had leukemia, for example&#x2014;inspired him to pursue research. In 1989, while working with colon tumor tissue, which they could obtain for different cancer stages, his group showed that the mutated <italic>TP53</italic> gene was not a cancer driver as had been thought but a tumor suppressor. Mutations that cause the gene to lose its function occur often in many different cancer types. Vogelstein says his decision to work with &#x201C;messy&#x201D; human tumors, not cell lines or animals, might be the reason why it took him three tries to get a grant from NCI.</p>
<p>In the late 1980s, Vogelstein also unveiled what's now a textbook model of how colorectal cancer develops. He and Kinzler, who joined the lab as a graduate student, later showed how the slow accumulation of mutations in specific genes leads to tumor growth. They went on to discover a string of major colon cancer genes. These studies all started by analyzing human tumors for mutations. Their guiding principle was that if a gene drives cancer, it will often be mutated. Trying to figure out a gene's importance by studying its function, they say, can be misleading. Just because the mutation alters a disease process doesn't mean it's the cause. It was &#x201C;a completely different view&#x201D; from what many other scientists believed, Vogelstein says.</p>
<p>The two built a highly competitive lab whose members played as hard as they worked. They installed a Ping-Pong table near the postdocs' desks; the lab held basketball and tennis tournaments. They had a rock band, Wild Type, composed of cancer biologists, with Vogelstein on keyboard and Kinzler on drums. Lab members got free use of a beach house. A quirky tradition arose in interviews of prospective postdocs: Candidates were asked to wear a Burger King crown when they spoke about their graduate work. &#x201C;If you were not willing to wear the crown, you were probably a little too high-strung for the lab,&#x201D; says Devin Dressman, a former Vogelstein postdoc who is now at Life Technologies in Beverly, Massachusetts.</p>
<p>Vogelstein and Kinzler rarely travel to speak at meetings. They prefer to stay involved in their lab's experiments and avoid being swayed by what's popular, or the &#x201C;herd effect,&#x201D; Vogelstein says. Instead, Vogelstein keeps up on the latest science by devouring the literature: &#x201C;He reads more than any other human I know,&#x201D; Dressman says.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Cancer's own genome project</title>
<p>After human DNA was fully sequenced in 2003, cancer geneticists around the world began to envision their own genome project. Instead of homing in only on suspected cancer genes, they would do a more sweeping search and systematically sequence the entire genome of patients' tumors and compare the results to DNA in normal cells to find all possible cancer genes. Vogelstein and Kinzler declined to join the pilot phase of a proposed $1 billion project funded by NCI called The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA). Instead, using private funding, they set out to sequence the first &#x201C;cancer genome&#x201D; in a handful of breast and colorectal tumor samples&#x2014;enough, according to their theory, to find the most important genes. They narrowed the search to focus on protein-coding DNA, the so-called exome.</p>
<p>It was an ambitious goal, especially because high-throughput sequencing machines weren't available. They accomplished it by brute force, performing about 200,000 polymerase chain reaction experiments on each of 22 patient tumor sample to amplify 13,000 or so genes. They sent the DNA to a commercial lab for traditional Sanger sequencing. Then they waited for results.</p>
<p>The gamble paid off: In 2006, Vogelstein's group published the first rough exomes for breast and colorectal cancers in <italic>Science</italic> (13 October 2006, p. 
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/314/5797/268.full">268</ext-link>). Data revealed both known and new cancer genes in varying frequencies&#x2014;the authors called them mountains and hills&#x2014;as well as daunting variations in patterns from one tumor to the next. Some researchers were critical: In Technical Comments in <italic>Science</italic>, TCGA leader and genome researcher Eric Lander of the Broad Institute in Cambridge, Massachusetts, among others, argued that the Johns Hopkins team had used faulty statistical methods and tested too few tumors to yield meaningful results.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Reality check.</title>
<p>Vogelstein and Kenneth Kinzler have identified flaws in some plans to use cancer genomics for treatment and risk prediction. They aim to develop a blood screening test to find early cancers.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_282_F2"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: KEITH WELLER</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Vogelstein and Kinzler moved on to glioblastoma exomes in 2008 and found an important new oncogene, <italic>IDH1</italic>. This was a slight embarrassment for the NCI collaboration, whose glioma project sequenced only a set of candidate cancer genes in a large number of tumors and missed <italic>IDH1</italic>.</p>
<p>Reviewing work by his group and others in his talks, Vogelstein seems ambivalent about the value of tumor DNA scans. More than 1000 of these surveys have added only a few dozen new cancer-driver genes to the 80 or so that were previously known, Vogelstein says. This includes some intriguing new genes, however. He and Kinzler agree that the more comprehensive NCI-backed genome atlas work is &#x201C;invaluable&#x201D; because it will find rare mutations and fill in gaps in our knowledge about the pathways that lead to uncontrolled tissue growth. But their own lab is moving on to other things after sequencing exomes for 20 cancer types. &#x201C;We're focusing on different questions now&#x2014;applications as opposed to discovery,&#x201D; Kinzler says.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Twins and cancer</title>
<p>One question that drew the Johns Hopkins group was: What fraction of the population would benefit from whole-genome sequencing? They had already used exome sequencing in 2009 to look for genes linked to pancreatic cancer common in one family. (Researchers compared the genomes of affected and nonaffected family members to pinpoint a responsible gene, <italic>PALB2</italic>.) Like screening for the <italic>BRCA</italic> breast cancer genes, identifying individuals with rare but high-risk pancreatic cancer genes might help some avoid death from the disease. This work led the group to wonder what might be gained if everyone's entire genome were sequenced, Vogelstein says. If a major fraction of the population carried high-risk genes, then sequencing everyone might make sense.</p>
<p>Because homozygous twins have identical genomes, the researchers could learn about their inherited disease risks without DNA sequencing, by comparing health records. Data on nearly 54,000 twin pairs, most in Europe, allowed the Johns Hopkins group to model how risks were distributed across the population. They found that genome testing had potential value. With a positive result defined as an overall disease risk of 10%, the average person would likely test positive for at least one disease, such as heart disease or diabetes. But genome scans would not help much with identifying risks for common cancers, they reported in <italic>Science Translational Medicine</italic> and at the meeting of the American Association for Cancer Research (AACR) in Chicago in April. For most people, the risks associated with inherited DNA are small or nonexistent, they found&#x2014;and trivial compared to risks from random mutations and factors such as smoking and obesity.</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Then and now.</title>
<p>Vogelstein today and with Kinzler (<italic>inset top row, middle and right</italic>) during the heyday of their band, Wild Type.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_282_F3"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDITS (TOP TO BOTTOM): JOE RUBINO; (INSET) ZUHAIR KAREEM, THE JOHNS HOPKINS HOSPITAL</attrib>
</fig>
<p>NCI's Chanock suggests that the twins data included too few cases of specific cancers to yield definitive results: &#x201C;I would not take this as the final word on the value of the genome,&#x201D; he says. But Lander, despite his criticism of the group's work on tumor exomes, says the twins study &#x201C;makes an important point&#x201D; even if it just &#x201C;confirms what we have known all along: Genes are not everything.&#x201D; Lander says his own view has always been that genetic risk studies are most useful for pointing to the biology underlying diseases, not for predicting personal risks.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Antihype</title>
<p>Vogelstein seems to enjoy pricking balloons. Recently, he has focused on a new target: exuberance over targeted cancer drugs. He says he got interested after seeing a paper last year on melanoma therapy. It included photos of the torso of a man with melanoma who had received a new drug aimed at a mutated gene called <italic>BRAF</italic>. Before treatment, the patient's skin was riddled with metastatic tumors; soon after treatment, the tumors vanished, and the man looked perfectly healthy. Five months later, the tumors reappeared in exactly the same locations. The photos &#x201C;blew my mind,&#x201D; Vogelstein says. &#x201C;Why do the tumors all return at roughly the same time? It's almost as miraculous as when they disappear.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Targeted drugs for other cancers usually stop working after about the same number of months, presumably because rare resistant cells in the tumors continue to grow and ultimately proliferate. To investigate, Luis Diaz and others in the Vogelstein-Kinzler lab drew on a sensitive technique they had developed for detecting mutations in the very small amount of tumor DNA present in a cancer patient's blood. They collected a series of these &#x201C;liquid biopsy&#x201D; measurements from patients with advanced colorectal cancer whose tumors had become resistant to a targeted cancer drug. With Harvard University computational biologist Martin Nowak, they devised a model showing that even before the patient begins treatment, some tumor cells always carry genes with random mutations that can support resistance to targeted drugs. This form of resistance, they wrote last month in <italic>Nature</italic>, is therefore &#x201C;a fait accompli.&#x201D;</p>
<p>But the modeling study also suggested that this resistance can be delayed by combining two drugs that target different pathways. Indeed, Vogelstein and colleagues suggest that once a targeted drug has passed initial safety trials, it's so clear that single-drug therapy will fail that they consider it unethical to give patients just one such drug. &#x201C;Why shouldn't you design a large, very expensive trial to incorporate more than one agent?&#x201D; Vogelstein asks.</p>
<p>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center cancer researcher Charles Sawyers, who helped develop Gleevec, the leukemia drug that paved way the way for other targeted therapies, says he agrees with Vogelstein's message: &#x201C;We have to move to combinations as quickly as possible.&#x201D;</p>
<p>The Vogelstein-Kinzler lab is attacking cancer from several new angles, including an unusual clinical trial that involves destroying tumors by injecting them with bacteria. But the project closest to Vogelstein's heart right now is an effort to develop the liquid biopsy method as a general cancer-screening test. The aim is to look for a set of mutations commonly found in tumors that can be isolated from circulating blood.</p>
<p>Vogelstein and Kinzler argue that DNA mutations offer &#x201C;clarity&#x201D; compared to other blood-sampling approaches that focus on more complex protein or gene-expression markers. At the AACR meeting, Vogelstein described his group's latest blood test results for 304 patients with several types of cancer. Nearly all with metastatic tumors had detectable mutations in their circulation; more than 50% of those whose cancer had not yet metastasized had them; and none of 82 controls. &#x201C;I think we're getting very close with the technology,&#x201D; says Vogelstein, who owns stock in a German company, Inostics, that is commercializing the test.</p>
<p>Although Vogelstein seems as passionate about research as ever, he has stepped back in recent years, others say. He now goes on vacations. Lately, he's been spending two afternoons a week with his two grandchildren, a time that Johns Hopkins neuroscientist Joshua Vogelstein (their uncle) thinks is probably &#x201C;the best part of his week.&#x201D; The lab has gotten &#x201C;leaner and meaner,&#x201D; Kinzler says: It's down from a peak of about 40 lab workers (including six faculty members) to perhaps 30&#x2014;one reason is that sequencing now involves less lab work. Wild Type hasn't picked up their instruments since Kinzler's wife fell ill with leukemia 10 years ago and died 6 months later. &#x201C;We had to stop and we never started up again,&#x201D; Vogelstein says.</p>
<p>Vogelstein has no plans to retire: &#x201C;I was born here and when I die they'll wheel me out on a cart,&#x201D; he says. Before that, he says, he has one overriding goal: that a cancer-screening test based on mutations in tumors will become a routine part of everyone's annual physical exam. &#x201C;I just want one of those tests to be the standard of care. That's the one thing.&#x201D;</p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>