<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ANTHRO</subject><subject>SOCIOLOGY</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>European Association for South Asian Archaeology and Art Meeting</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Diving Into the Indian Ocean's Past</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lawler</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage seq="b">288</fpage>
<lpage>289</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Researchers studying what appears to be the oldest known shipwreck in the Indian Ocean say it promises to remake our understanding of the region and era.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Nearly 15 years ago, two fishers in the waters off the southern coast of Sri Lanka hauled up a stone slab etched with ancient Hindu symbols. During a brief 2008 dive, archaeologists retrieved pottery and glass ingots. Then, in December 2011, researchers began the first systematic dives to examine what appears to be the oldest known shipwreck in the Indian Ocean, radiocarbon dated to between the 2nd and 1st centuries B.C.E. Because almost nothing was known about seafaring in this time and place, the wreck promises to remake our understanding of the region and era, team members say.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Nearly 15 years ago, two fishers in the waters off the southern coast of Sri Lanka hauled up a stone slab etched with ancient Hindu symbols. During a brief 2008 dive, archaeologists retrieved pottery and glass ingots. Then, in December 2011, with funding from the U.S. National Endowment for the Humanities and other sources, researchers began the first systematic dives to examine what appears to be the oldest known shipwreck in the Indian Ocean, radiocarbon dated to between the 2nd and 1st centuries B.C.E. Because almost nothing was known about seafaring in this time and place, the wreck promises to remake our understanding of the region and era, says team member Osmund Bopearachchi, a historian at the University of Paris, Sorbonne.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Clear sailing.</title>
<p>Divers explore an ancient Sri Lankan wreck that could offer clues to early Indian Ocean trade.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_288b_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: SHEILA MATTHEWS/DEPARTMENT OF ARCHAEOLOGY OF SRI LANKA AND THE INSTITUTE OF NAUTICAL ARCHAEOLOGY</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Archaeologists suspected that traders crisscrossed the Indian Ocean at this time, but the evidence was slim. Just a century or so later, merchants from India and the Roman Empire plied the Indian Ocean, trading cotton, glass, and spices. But textual references and archaeological evidence of earlier maritime trade are extremely rare; the only known South Asian shipwrecks date from medieval times. Indians and Arabs dominated the medieval trade, which connected Europe and China, but its origins are murky.</p>
<p>The Sri Lankan wreck offers the first good look at such trade. The island, which lies off the southeastern coast of India, was an important Buddhist kingdom that eventually became a wealthy port of call. The ship remains lie near the estuary of Walawe Ganga, one of the nation's few navigable rivers. Just upstream lies Godavaya, a recently excavated monastery dating to the 2nd century B.C.E.; monastic settlements often played an important economic role at this time. Other nearby settlements go back to the 4th century B.C.E., says Bopearachchi, who works with underwater archaeologist Deborah Carlson of Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, as well as the maritime unit of the Sri Lanka Department of Archaeology.</p>
<p>Only surface surveys have been done to date, examining artifacts spread across 40 meters of ocean floor that mark it as the site of a sunken ship. Massive glass ingots, used to make expensive vessels, were part of the ship's cargo and provide what Bopearachchi calls &#x201C;the best physical evidence for the early exchange of raw glass in South Asia.&#x201D; Samples from both the glass and nearby pieces of metal point to an Indian origin, and the ship may have been bound for the port, he says.</p>
<p>Its remains lie in 34 meters of water amid strong currents, but the water is crystal clear, and conditions are good for diving during the winter monsoon. Archaeologists hope that the ship itself may lie below the bottom, providing evidence of shipbuilding technology. The team plans to begin excavating at the end of this year. The results &#x201C;might lead to a rewriting of the economic, social, religious, and cultural history of the area,&#x201D; Bopearachchi says. Others agree that the find will shed needed light on a critical trade route. &#x201C;This is the Silk Road of the sea,&#x201D; says Hans-Joachim Weisshaar of the German Archaeological Institute in Bonn.</p>
</body>
</article>