<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI COMMUN</subject><subject>SCI POLICY</subject><subject>PHYSICS</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Science Funding</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Stability at Last for Australian Synchrotron?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Finkel</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn id="FN1">
<label>*</label>
<p>Elizabeth Finkel is the author of <italic>The Genome Generation</italic>.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage>278</fpage>
<lpage>278</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>The Australian government is expected to announce next month that the Australian Nuclear Science and Technology Organisation will take the troubled Australian Synchrotron under its wing.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Roiled by management disputes, the Australian Synchrotron, brought online in 2007, was set to run out of funding last month before the federal and state governments rode in with a 4-year rescue package. Now, the facility may find long-term stability. The federal government is expected to announce next month that the Australian Nuclear Science and Technology Organisation will take the troubled facility under its wing.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><bold>MELBOURNE, AUSTRALIA</bold>&#x2014;&#x201C;Last week I was on Europa,&#x201D; says Helen Maynard-Casely. The planetary scientist, based here at the Australian Synchrotron, wasn&apos;t just imagining a trip to the jovian moon. She has been using the third-generation machine&apos;s intense x-rays to probe the structure of water and sulfate minerals at high pressure and low temperature, simulating the composition and conditions of Europa&apos;s ice sheet.</p>
<p>A few months ago, Maynard-Casely&apos;s virtual voyages to Europa were in jeopardy. Roiled by management disputes, the Australian Synchrotron, brought online in 2007, was set to run out of funding last month before the federal and state governments rode in with a 4-year rescue package. Now, the facility may find long-term stability. The federal government is expected to announce next month that the Australian Nuclear Science and Technology Organisation (ANSTO) in Sydney will take the troubled facility under its wing. &#x201C;I have great expectations,&#x201D; says William Thomlinson, former director of the Canadian Light Source and a former adviser to the Australian Synchrotron. &#x201C;ANSTO will bring the synchrotron up to speed. I&apos;ve seen them in action.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Thomlinson and others hope ANSTO&apos;s stewardship will close a woeful chapter in the young synchrotron&apos;s history. The saga began in October 2009, when the facility&apos;s governors sacked Director Robert Lamb (<italic>Science</italic>, 1 January 2010, p. 
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/327/5961/20.full">20</ext-link>). Staff protested Lamb&apos;s removal by staging a 3-month work slowdown: They ran the facility on a 9-to-5 schedule instead of the usual round-the-clock. In the meantime, seven of nine members of the synchrotron&apos;s International Scientific Advisory Committee resigned.</p>
<p>Another blow came when the $248.5 million facility was deprived of its champion, Victoria State Premier John Brumby. In November 2010, Brumby&apos;s party lost elections and the government changed hands. Victoria&apos;s new leadership did not offer ongoing operating funds nor did the federal government pick up the bill, leaving the synchrotron&apos;s fate after June 2012 uncertain.</p>
<p>The management turmoil happened despite the machine&apos;s admirable performance. In 2006, it set a world record for the fastest time for a synchrotron to start producing x-rays and set another record for reliability. Research highlights include solving the elusive structures of perforin and the pre-T-cell antigen receptor. &#x201C;We&apos;re getting a lot of firsts,&#x201D; says Tom Caradoc-Davies, leader of the macromolecular crystallography team.</p>
<p>What faltered instead was the synchrotron&apos;s complex governance. It was managed by a board reporting to five state governments, the federal government, the New Zealand government, 30 universities, and 41 other organizations. ANSTO&apos;s Richard Garrett, architect of the organization&apos;s proposal to operate the synchrotron, recalls intricate white-board diagrams of the Australian Synchrotron&apos;s management structure. &#x201C;I remember wondering, &#x2018;Where&apos;s the synchrotron?&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
<p>Fissures in the ungainly alliance began to appear when it was time for the machine to grow. When it opened, the Australian Synchrotron had eight beamlines and a ninth in development for diverting x-rays and infrared light to experimental setups. But the machine was designed for 38 beamlines, each of which costs up to $10 million and requires major design input. &#x201C;There was no one clearly charged with strategizing future growth, spending time with the government and so on,&#x201D; says ANSTO Chief Executive Adi Paterson. As a result, the synchrotron has added no new beamlines since number nine.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Under pressure.</title>
<p>Helen Maynard-Casely uses the synchrotron to simulate conditions on Europa.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_278_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: AUSTRALIAN SYNCHROTRON</attrib>
</fig>
<p>The synchrotron user community in Australia, meanwhile, has been growing at a rate of 600 per year. That has forced some scientists to go overseas for beam time. Keith Nugent, the director of the Australian Synchrotron, says it &#x201C;has a 20-year lifetime as a state-of-the-art machine. We&apos;re already 5 years in and well behind.&#x201D; By comparison, he says, the Canadian Light Source is barely 3 years older than Australia&apos;s but already has 17 beamlines.</p>
<p>The first ray of hope came last March, when Federal Science Minister Chris Evans announced a $103 million rescue package, of which the lion&apos;s share will come from the Australian Research Council and universities. Welcome as it was, the package required a 10% spending cut, forcing the facility to let several staff go, Nugent says.</p>
<p>Now a lasting solution is at hand. Under an agreement that is still being finalized, an ANSTO-operated company will operate the synchrotron. If the deal goes through, Maynard-Casely plans to make the most of her time at the facility, where she has 1 year left on her contract. Earlier this week, another beam run would bring her deep under the surface of Europa&apos;s ice sheet, where, she says, &#x201C;the pressure is equivalent to five elephants standing on a stiletto.&#x201D; It&apos;s up to ANSTO to remove the real-world pressure Maynard-Casely and her colleagues have been enduring.</p>
</body>
</article>