<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1224878</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1224878</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Books <italic>et al.</italic></subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>books</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ATMOS</subject><subject>SCI HISTORY PHILO</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Climate</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Hot Seat in Our Warming World</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ocko</surname><given-names>Ilissa B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>The reviewer is at the Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences Program, Princeton University, 300 Forrestal Road, Sayre Hall, Princeton, NJ 08544, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>iocko@princeton.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage seq="a">296</fpage>
<lpage>296</lpage>
<product product-type="book"><bold>The Hockey Stick and the Climate Wars: Dispatches from the Front Lines.</bold> Michael E. Mann. Columbia University Press, New York, 2012. 413 pp. $28.95, &#x00A3;19.95. ISBN 9780231152549.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Mann offers a personal account of the acrimonious attacks on climate change science.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Mann offers a personal account of the acrimonious attacks on climate change science.</p></abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sherman J. Suter</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Jeff Cook</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Just as the tobacco industry long denied that cigarettes are bad for human health, stakeholders in the fossil-fuel industry have disputed that humans cause climate change&#x2014;and often that climate is changing&#x2014;in order to protect their extremely profitable business. They have poured immense amounts of money into campaigns that have influenced politicians, media, the public, and even scientists, fueling the perception that the science remains in dispute. However, the strong consensus within the scientific community is that we are witnessing substantial shifts in climate and that those changes are largely due to human activities.</p>
<p>Climate change deniers have sought to discredit the scientific consensus by isolating researchers and attacking their credibility. Perhaps their hardest-hit target in the United States is Michael Mann, codeveloper of the hockey stick, a graph of Northern Hemisphere temperatures over the past millennium. Few have dealt with the contrarians more than Mann, the recipient of false accusations (such as fabricating data and conspiring with colleagues) for over a decade and a victim of Climategate. In <italic>The Hockey Stick and the Climate Wars</italic>, Mann seeks to share his experiences and science with the public and to expose the climate change deniers' fraudulent disinformation campaigns.</p>
<p>Anecdotes from Mann's childhood reveal a bright, passionate, and somewhat nerdy character. Whereas fellow high schoolers partied on the weekends, for instance, Mann was determined to develop a tic-tac-toe game on the computer. In addition to bringing out the author's personality, these stories introduce concepts that crucially help readers understand subsequent events. For example, while programming the tic-tac-toe game, Mann eventually discovered a clever shortcut, something often referred to as a trick in math and science. Years later, the discovery of the word &#x201C;trick&#x201D; in the hacked e-mails of prominent climate scientists would lead climate change skeptics to incorrectly accuse scientists of hiding data.</p>
<p>Mann's comprehensive rendition of every event&#x2014;including names of all individuals involved&#x2014;builds credibility for his account, as do the 100-plus pages of supporting notes with references. The author covers both sides of the debate, drawing details from scientific publications, blog posts, media coverage, letters from congressmembers, political decisions, courtroom trials, and investigations. Mann presents most of the events through the lens of his personal experiences, but the book also recounts various incidents experienced by other climatologists. Additionally, he complements the stories with accessible explanations of scientific tools and processes.</p>
<p>Dissecting numerous well-orchestrated attacks on climate science, Mann refutes each denialist argument with a wealth of broadly accepted evidence. He clearly demonstrates how science is a self-correcting process and that thousands of independent studies from various institutions and countries build on one another to form our current state of knowledge. Through an approach more humorous than accusatory, Mann lets the mistakes of the skeptics speak for themselves. For example, the Wegman report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>) highly regarded by contrarians is mostly plagiarized from works of credible climate scientists, with words twisted intermittently to support the views of the skeptics. Furthermore, Mann painstakingly explains how every phrase highlighted in the Climategate scandal&#x2014;&#x201C;one of the best-coordinated &#x2018;swiftboat&#x2019; campaigns in modern history&#x201D;&#x2014;was taken out of context.</p>
<p>The book's thoroughness seems essential to accomplishing its goals. Still, <italic>The Hockey Stick and the Climate Wars</italic> may be difficult for some to read because of dense, unfamiliar terminology; the extensive name-dropping; and various distracting technical tangents. One can forget who is who, what is what, and who did what. Nevertheless, Mann's honest and thorough testimony on the attacks against climate science is a critical step toward resolving the climate change debate.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://republicans.energycommerce.house.gov/108/home/07142006_Wegman_report.pdf">http://republicans.energycommerce.house.gov/108/home/07142006_Wegman_report.pdf</ext-link></comment>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>