<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Findings</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Findings</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>findings</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ECOLOGY</subject><subject>OCEANS</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Fertilized Blooms Deposit Carbon To Deep Sea</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage seq="b">275</fpage>
<lpage>275</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="findings.pdf" />
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>For the first time, scientists have direct evidence that carbon formed from algal blooms fertilized with iron does sink to the deep ocean&#x2014;a finding that might renew interest in using iron fertilization as a way to sequester carbon dioxide and possibly mitigate climate change.</p><fig id="F1" position="anchor">
<caption>
<p>Diatom <italic>Chaetoceros atlanticus</italic>, a type of plankton in the Southern Ocean.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_275b_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: CHAETOEROS - MARINA MONTRESOR, SZN/ALFRED WEGENER INSTITUTE</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Iron is a limiting nutrient in many parts of the ocean. Previous studies have shown that adding iron to the upper ocean stimulates blooms of phytoplankton, which in turn take up increased amounts of carbon dioxide from the atmosphere. But it was unclear whether that carbon would then be prevented from interacting with the atmosphere by sequestering it away in the deep ocean.</p>
<p>As part of the 2004 European Iron Fertilization Experiment, oceanographer Victor Smetacek of the Alfred Wegener Institute for Polar and Marine Research in Bremerhaven, Germany, and colleagues tracked particles of phytoplankton biomass in the Southern Ocean as they sank from the surface to the ocean floor. More than half of the carbon captured by the algal bloom during the iron fertilization experiment sank more than 1000 meters, they reported this week in <italic>Nature</italic>.</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scim.ag/ironfert"><bold>http://scim.ag/ironfert</bold></ext-link></p>
</body>
</article>