<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1224868</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1224868</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Books <italic>et al.</italic></subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>books</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>NEUROSCIENCE</subject><subject>PSYCHOLOGY</subject><subject>SCI COMMUN</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Mind Inside Our Skull</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>Ricardo Basso</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>The reviewer is at the  Departamento de Psicologia (PG-Psicobiologia), Faculdade de Filosofia, Ci&#x00EA;ncias e Letras de Ribeir&#x00E3;o Preto, Universidade de S&#x00E3;o Paulo, Avenida Bandeirantes 3900. CEP 14040-901, Ribeir&#x00E3;o Preto, SP, Brasil. </aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>rbgarcia@pg.ffclrp.usp.br</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage seq="c">293</fpage>
<lpage>294</lpage>
<product product-type="book"><bold>Neuromania: On the Limits of Brain Science.</bold> Paolo Legrenzi and Carlo Umilt&#x00E0;; translated by Frances Anderson. Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2011. 132 pp. $29.95, &#x00A3;14.99. ISBN 9780199591343.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>In this concise overview of brain science, Legrenzi and Umilt&#xE0; emphasize the broad perspective and sociopolitical implications.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>In this concise overview of brain science, Legrenzi and Umilt&#xE0; emphasize the broad perspective and sociopolitical implications.</p></abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sherman J. Suter</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Harry Jach</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>It was noon, and church bells were ringing as a doctor carefully examined a patient who had traumatic lesions in the frontal cranial bone. He noticed that pulsations in the cerebral arteries had become stronger, but, curiously, that change was not linked to changes in pulse rate and blood pressure measured on the patient's arm. The patient then confirmed his doctor's somewhat weird suspicion: the ringing bells reminded him it was time to say a prayer. This experience led the Italian physiologist Angelo Mosso (1846&#x2013;1910) to the first attempt to relate variations of blood flow in the brain to mental activity, a link that is at the core of modern neuroimaging techniques such as functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). Such techniques have allowed scientists to shed some light on the neural substrates underlying ongoing mental processes.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Angelo Mosso.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_293c_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: COURTESY NATIONAL LIBRARY OF MEDICINE</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Mosso's research is one of several important contributions that 19th-century neurologists made toward establishing the relationship between the mind and the brain and that are reviewed in <italic>Neuromania</italic>. In this brief book, neuropsychologists Paolo Legrenzi (Ca'Foscari University, Venice) and Carlo Umilt&#x00E0; (University of Padua) bring a welcome appraisal of brain research to a broad audience. They provide an insightful and comprehensible overview of methods and techniques from the origins of brain science to today's MRI scanners. However, rather than emphasizing state-of-the-art procedures and technologies, they focus on the limitations of the field, covering methodological aspects and controversial assumptions that are commonly unknown to the general public.</p>
<p>Legrenzi and Umilt&#x00E0; put brain science in a broader perspective and discuss its sociopolitical implications, something scientists often neglect when presenting their own fields. The advent of neuroimaging opened many new lines of research. Because the question &#x201C;what happens in the brain when &#x2026;?&#x201D; fits practically any aspect of human activity, fMRI has been applied to a wide range of issues&#x2014;from people's artistic or religious experiences to their preferences for specific products or political parties. As a consequence, many established concepts in the social sciences gained the prefix &#x201C;neuro-&#x201D; and a profusion of new disciplines emerged (neuroaesthetics, neurotheology, and neuropolitics, to mention a few). Putting these disciplines under scrutiny, Legrenzi and Umilt&#x00E0; highlight that old knowledge may have been presented as novel just by changing &#x201C;mind&#x201D; to &#x201C;brain,&#x201D; without bringing actual scientific progress.</p>
<p>In the authors' reading, the brain has become the system of reference in explanations of human mind and behavior, relegating to the background an alternative approach that emphasized the social and cultural aspects of the human mind. A word of caution: The important issue is not a matter of which perspective should prevail but that many decisions regarding human life depend on how society defines the mind-body relationship. If only one aspect appears in the foreground, there may be drastic differences when dealing with thorny topics such as abortion and euthanasia. Answers to the complex questions raised by technological and scientific progress toward controlling life and death depend on ethical and ideological choices. To think about such issues from a strictly biological point of view may be misleading&#x2014;after all, inside our skull there is more than just a brain.</p>
</body>
</article>