<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="introduction" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Introduction to Special Issue</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Introduction to Special Issue</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>special/intro</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Introduction</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Anatomy</subject><subject>Anthropology</subject><subject>Materials-Science</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Mosaic Nature of <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>Lee R.</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff>Evolutionary Studies Institute, University of the Witwatersrand, Private Bag 3, Wits 2050, South Africa.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>profleeberger@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>12</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
    <issue-title content-type="special-issue"><italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></issue-title>
<fpage>163</fpage>
<lpage>165</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<boxed-text content-type="sci-custom 6129-sediba"><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/site/extra/sediba/index.xhtml">Index to <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic> special section</ext-link></p></boxed-text>
<p>The site of Malapa, South Africa, has yielded perhaps the richest assemblage of early hominin fossils on the continent of Africa. The fossil remains of <italic>Au. sediba</italic> were discovered in August of 2008, and the species was named in 2010 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>) and given a provisional age of &#x223C;1.78 to 1.95 Ma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). In 2011, detailed studies of four critical areas of anatomy of these remains were published (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>), and a refined date of &#x223C;1.977 to 1.98 Ma was proposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>). The six articles presented in full in the online edition of <italic>Science</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/site/extra/sediba">www.sciencemag.org/site/extra/sediba</ext-link>), with abstracts in print (pp. 164&#x2013;165), complete the initial examination of the prepared material attributed to three individuals: the holotype and paratype skeletons, commonly referred to as MH1 and MH2, and the adult isolated tibia referred to as MH4. They, along with the cumulative research published over the past 3 years, provide us with a comprehensive examination of the anatomy of a single species of early hominin.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<p>Composite reconstruction of <italic>Au. sediba</italic> based on recovered material from MH1, MH2, and MH4 and based on the research presented in the accompanying manuscripts. Because all individuals recovered to date are approximately the same size, size correction was not necessary. Femoral length was established by digitally measuring a complete femur of MH1 still encased in rock. For comparison, a small-bodied female modern <italic>H. sapiens</italic> is shown on the left and a male <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> on the right.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_163_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: LEE R. BERGER AND THE UNIVERSITY OF THE WITWATERSRAND</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Irish <italic>et al.</italic> examine highly heritable nonmetric dental traits in <italic>Au. sediba</italic>. The species appears phylogenetically distinct from East African australopiths but close to <italic>Au. africanus</italic>, forming a southern African australopith clade. The latter shares some derived states with a clade comprising four fossil samples of the genus <italic>Homo</italic>. This result has implications for our present understanding of hominin phylogeny through the terminal Pliocene and suggests a possibility that <italic>Au. sediba</italic>, and perhaps <italic>Au. africanus</italic>, did not descend from the <italic>Au. afarensis</italic> lineage. De Ruiter <italic>et al.</italic> examine mandibular material attributable to MH2, including the previously unknown mandibular incisors and premolars of <italic>Au. sediba</italic>. As seen elsewhere in the cranium and skeleton, these mandibular remains share similarities with those of other australopiths but differ from <italic>Au. africanus</italic> in both size and shape, as well as in their ontogenetic growth trajectory. These results further support the claim that <italic>Au. sediba</italic> is taxonomically distinct from <italic>Au. africanus</italic>. Where the <italic>Au. sediba</italic> mandibles differ from those of <italic>Au. africanus</italic>, they appear most similar to those of representatives of early <italic>Homo</italic>.</p>
<p>Churchill <italic>et al.</italic> explore the upper limb elements of <italic>Au. sediba</italic>, describing the most complete and undistorted humerus, radius, ulna, scapula, clavicle, and manubrium yet described from the early hominin record, all associated with one individual. With the exception of the hand skeleton (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>), the upper limbs of the Malapa hominins are largely primitive in their morphology. <italic>Au. sediba</italic> thus shares with other australopiths an upper limb that was well suited for arboreal climbing and possibly suspension, although perhaps more so than has previously been suggested for this genus.</p>
<p>Remains of the rib cage of <italic>Au. sediba</italic> are described by Schmid <italic>et al.</italic> and reveal a mediolaterally narrow upper thorax like that of the large-bodied apes and unlike the broad cylindrical chest seen in humans. In conjunction with the largely complete remains of the shoulder girdle, the morphological picture that emerges is one of a conical thorax with a high shoulder joint (producing an ape-like &#x201C;shrugged&#x201D; shoulder appearance) and thus a configuration that is perhaps uniquely australopith and would not have been conducive to human-like swinging of the arms during bipedal striding and running. The less well-preserved elements of the lower rib cage suggest a degree of human-like mediolateral narrowing to the lower thorax, indicating a rather unsuspected mosaic anatomy in the chest that is not like that observed in <italic>Homo erectus</italic> or <italic>H. sapiens</italic>.</p>
<p>Williams <italic>et al.</italic> analyze elements of the cervical, thoracic, lumbar, and sacral regions of the vertebral column, showing that <italic>Au. sediba</italic> had the same number of lumbar vertebrae as modern humans but possessed a functionally longer and more flexible lower back. Morphological indicators of strong lumbar curvature suggest that <italic>Au. sediba</italic> was derived in this regard relative to <italic>Au. africanus</italic> and was more similar to the Nariokotome <italic>H. erectus</italic> skeleton.</p>
<p>Finally, DeSilva <italic>et al.</italic> describe the lower limb anatomy of <italic>Au. sediba</italic> and propose a specific biomechanical hypothesis for how this species walked. In isolation, the anatomies of the heel, midfoot, knee, hip, and back are unique and curious, but in combination they are internally consistent for a biped walking with a hyperpronating gait. The implications are that multiple forms of bipedalism were once practiced by our early hominin ancestors.</p>
<p>This examination of a large number of associated, often complete and undistorted elements gives us a glimpse of a hominin species that appears to be mosaic in its anatomy and that presents a suite of functional complexes that are different from both those predicted for other australopiths and those of early <italic>Homo</italic>. Such clear insight into the anatomy of an early hominin species will clearly have implications for interpreting the evolutionary processes that affected the mode and tempo of hominin evolution and the interpretation of the anatomy of less well-preserved species.</p>
<sec>
<title>More Articles in this Section:</title>
<p> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/340/6129/1233062">Dental Morphology and the Phylogenetic &#x201C;Place&#x201D; of <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></ext-link></p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/340/6129/1232997">Mandibular Remains Support Taxonomic Validity of <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></ext-link></p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/340/6129/1233477">The Upper Limb of <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></ext-link></p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/340/6129/1234598">Mosaic Morphology in the Thorax of <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></ext-link></p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/340/6129/1232996">The Vertebral Column of <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></ext-link></p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/340/6129/1232999">The Lower Limb and Mechanics of Walking in <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></ext-link></p>
<p>Additional <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic> research, news, and multimedia can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/extra/sediba">www.sciencemag.org/extra/sediba</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p><sup>1</sup>Research Centre in Evolutionary Anthropology and Palaeoecology, School of Natural Sciences and Psychology, Liverpool John Moores University, Liverpool L3 3AF, UK. <sup>2</sup>Department of Anthropology and Department of Evolution, Ecology, and Organismal Biology, Ohio State University, Columbus, OH 43210, USA. <sup>3</sup>Department of Anthropology, Macalester College, St. Paul, MN 55105, USA. <sup>4</sup>Department of Anthropology, Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, TX 77843, USA. <sup>5</sup>Evolutionary Studies Institute, University of the Witwatersrand, Private Bag 3, Wits 2050, South Africa. <sup>6</sup>Department of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences, Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, TX 77843, USA. <sup>7</sup>Department of Anthropology, Loyola University, Chicago, IL 60660, USA. <sup>8</sup>Department of Archaeology, University of Cape Town, Rondebosch 7701, South Africa. <sup>9</sup>Department of Evolutionary Anthropology, Box 90383, Duke University, Durham, NC 27708, USA. <sup>10</sup>Department of Anthropology, Tulane University, New Orleans, LA 70118, USA. <sup>11</sup>Department of Anthropology, Indiana University, Bloomington, IN 47405, USA. <sup>12</sup>Georgian National Museum, 0105 Tbilisi, Georgia. <sup>13</sup>Anthropological Institute and Museum, University of Z&#x00FC;rich, Winterthurerstrasse 190, CH-8057 Z&#x00FC;rich, Switzerland. <sup>14</sup>Department of Human Anatomy and Physiology, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Johannesburg, Johannesburg, South Africa. <sup>15</sup>Center for the Study of Human Origins, Department of Anthropology, New York University, 25 Waverly Place, New York, NY 10003, USA. <sup>16</sup>New York Consortium in Evolutionary Primatology, New York, NY 10024, USA. <sup>17</sup>Department of Anthropology, Boston University, 232 Bay State Road, Boston, MA 02215, USA. <sup>18</sup>Department of Physical Therapy and Athletic Training, Sargent College, 635 Commonwealth Avenue, Boston University, Boston, MA 02215, USA. <sup>19</sup>Bernard Price Institute for Palaeontological Research, School of Geosciences, University of the Witwatersrand, Private Bag 3, Wits 2050, South Africa.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <article-title><italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic>: a new species of <italic>Homo</italic>-like australopith from South Africa</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>328</volume>, <fpage>195</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dirks</surname><given-names>P. H. G. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <article-title>Geological setting and age of <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic> from southern Africa</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>328</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kivell</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kibii</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title><italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic> hand demonstrates mosaic evolution of locomotor and manipulative abilities</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>333</volume>, <fpage>1411</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kibii</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <article-title>A partial pelvis of <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>333</volume>, <fpage>1407</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <article-title>The endocast of MH1, <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>333</volume>, <fpage>1402</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <article-title>The foot and ankle of <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>333</volume>, <fpage>1417</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <article-title><italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic> at 1.977 Ma and implications for the origins of the genus <italic>Homo</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>333</volume>, <fpage>1421</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>