<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Planetary-Science</subject><subject>Computer-Science</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>GEOCHEM PHYS</subject><subject>PLANET SCI</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Lunar and Planetary Science Conference</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Mystery of Our Moon's Gravitational Bumps Solved?</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>12</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage seq="a">138</fpage>
<lpage>139</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>A group of researchers reported how over millions of years, the moon's subtle adjustment to an impact might eventually create a high spot in the moon's bumpy gravitational field.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Much to geophysicists' consternation, the first space probes to orbit the moon were showing up in the wrong places at the wrong times. Something about the gravitational pull of the moon was throwing off their orbits. But what? In 1968, two NASA scientists found the culprit, or rather culprits: The moon's great basins were exerting an unexpected extra pull on passing satellites. At the meeting, a group of researchers reported how over millions of years the moon's subtle adjustment to an impact might eventually create a high spot in the moon's bumpy gravitational field.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Mottled moon.</title>
<p>In this GRAIL gravity map, mascon basins are red, circular, and blue-ringed.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_138a_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: NASA/JPL-CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY/GSFC/MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Much to geophysicists' consternation, the first space probes to orbit the moon were misbehaving badly, showing up in the wrong places at the wrong times. Something about the gravitational pull of the moon was throwing off their orbits. But what? In 1968, two NASA scientists found the culprit, or rather culprits: The moon's great basins were exerting an unexpected extra pull on passing satellites.</p>
<p>That made no sense, of course. Those basins are low spots where huge impacts have gouged out megatons of rock, not added mass. Somehow, there is hidden extra mass under many lunar basins, making them basins with mass concentrations or mascon basins. How did the extra mass get there? At the meeting, a group of researchers reported how over millions of years the moon's subtle adjustment to an impact might eventually create a high spot in the moon's bumpy gravitational field.</p>
<p>Two developments in planetary science have helped finally generate a solution to the mascon mystery. One was the advent of stunningly detailed lunar observations. NASA's twin-spacecraft Gravity Recovery and Interior Laboratory (GRAIL) mission mapped the subtle variations of gravitational pull with a resolution of 10 kilometers or so over the entire moon (<italic>Science</italic>, 7 December 2012, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-publication" vol="338" page="1272" issue="6112">1272</related-article>). That painted a clear gravity picture of mascons: a bull's-eye pattern of higher-than-expected gravity across a basin hundreds of kilometers wide, ringed by a band of lower gravity and an outermost ring of higher gravity.</p>
<p>The other development came back on Earth. Computer modelers had managed to inject such realism into their models that they could hope to match their simulated mascon formation to the GRAIL gravity map. So at the meeting, physicist Brandon Johnson of Purdue University in West Lafayette, Indiana, and 10 colleagues showed how they simulated the impact of a 50-kilometer-diameter rock plunging vertically into the moon at 54,000 kilometers per hour. In the model, the collision le ft behind a broad, shallow basin, a ring of reduced gravity where less dense ejecta had piled on the crust, and a central pool of melted mantle rock more than 100 kilometers deep.</p>
<p>In the next talk, planetary scientist Andrew Freed of Purdue, speaking for the same group, reported on their modeling of the next 100 million years of an impact basin's life: This is when all that hot rock slowly cools, a rigid lid of mostly mantle rock forms over top, and relatively dense or light chunks of rock can slowly sink or float in the still-viscous mantle. Both simulations had to get many steps right, Freed said. Most critically, the rigid lid must form and lock the temporarily elevated central basin in place before the ring of thickened crust&#x2014;which is floating up&#x2014;sucks mantle rock from beneath the central basin. Losing that mass would rob the central basin of the mass responsible for the mascon.</p>
<p>Freed reported that their two-step modeling produced the same bull's-eye gravity pattern seen in GRAIL data at two impact basins, even though the two sites had different preimpact crustal thicknesses. The same modeling approach even duplicated the mascon of the humongous 960-kilometerdiameter Orientale basin, the group reported at a poster the same day. The modeling includes physical "mechanisms we know are there," Freed said. "If we model those mechanisms well, the mascons pop out. It's really hard to mess this calculation up."</p>
<p>Planetary geophysicist William McKinnon of Washington University in St. Louis calls the results "very interesting and a nice step forward" but notes that the studies so far leave out some potentially important mechanisms, such as the flow of pulverized rock in an impact. He will be looking for another round of modeling.</p>
</body>
</article>