<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Oceanography</subject><subject>Planetary-Science</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>GEOCHEM PHYS</subject><subject>PLANET SCI</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Lunar and Planetary Science Conference</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>More Support for An Ocean in Enceladus</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>Richard A.</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>12</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage seq="a">139</fpage>
<lpage>139</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Researchers argued that the latest Cassini observations make sense if liquid water is escaping from a deep ocean through cracks in Enceladus's outer ice shell.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Now that the Cassini spacecraft has made its last close-up observations of Saturn's moon Enceladus, mission team members are pushing to prove once and for all that the 500-kilometer-diameter moon harbors a salty&#x2014;and habitable&#x2014;ocean far below its icy surface. They aren't there yet, but at the meeting, researchers argued that the latest Cassini observations make the most sense if liquid water is escaping from a deep ocean through cracks in Enceladus's outer ice shell to produce the plume spewing from the moon's south polar region.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <caption>
            <title>Cracked up.</title>
            <p>The four bluish, parallel lines mark cracks on Enceladus from which a deep ocean may vent.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="340_139a_F1"></graphic>
        <attrib>CREDIT: CASSINI IMAGING TEAM/SSI/JPL/ESA/NASA</attrib>
    </fig>
<p>Now that the Cassini spacecraft has made its last close-up observations of Saturn's moon Enceladus, mission team members are pushing to prove once and for all that the 500-kilometer-diameter moon harbors a salty&#x2014;and habitable&#x2014;ocean far below its icy surface. They aren't there yet, but at the meeting, researchers argued that the latest Cassini observations make the most sense if liquid water is escaping from a deep ocean through cracks in Enceladus's outer ice shell to produce the plume spewing from the moon's south polar region.</p>
<p>Some planetary scientists had thought that they had figured out the mechanics of Enceladus's plume. It appeared to them that Saturn's varying tidal pull on Enceladus was pushing on opposing sides of four great cracks running across the south pole region, moving them back and forth. The resulting frictional h eat would melt some ice, sending plumes into the vacuum of space&#x2014;no deep ocean required.</p>
<p>But at the meeting, Carolyn Porco of the Space Science Institute in Boulder, Colorado&#x2014;Cassini's camera team leader&#x2014;and colleagues suggested a scenario that better fits the observations. Saturn's tides are, in fact, working on the fractures, they found, but individual plume jets tend to occur where tidal stresses are calculated to be pulling cracks apart, rather than where they create frictional heat. And tidal opening of cracks tends to coincide with the times when the south polar plume is seen to intensify, suggesting that the opening cracks are letting something escape.</p>

<p>That something, Porco and colleagues conclude, is warm water from a deep ocean. If it were meltwater from any frictional heating in the cracks, their calculations show the surrounding ice would be noticeably heated for several kilometers along a crack. But researchers on Cassini's heat-sensing imager team reported last fall that hot spots on cracks are no bigger than a few tens of meters. So it looks as if tidal stresses are opening cracks through kilometers of ice and letting ocean water escape to space.</p>
<p>"That's definitely a possibility," says planetary physicist David Stevenson of the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena. Frictional heating doesn't seem to be working out, he says, so "instead they are tapping heat from the ocean." Next up, he adds, is showing how such a plumbing system could keep going for millennia. Still, Stevenson says, "progress is being made."</p>
</body>
</article>