<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1235208</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1235208</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Report</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Reports</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>reports</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>IMMUNOLOGY</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Immunology</subject><subject>Virology</subject><subject>Genetics</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Blockade of Chronic Type I Interferon Signaling to Control Persistent LCMV Infection</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Elizabeth B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Douglas H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Elsaesser</surname><given-names>Heidi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Herskovitz</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Jane</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Genhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aronow</surname><given-names>Bruce J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>Christopher L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>David G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x2020;</xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Microbiology, Immunology and Molecular Genetics and the UCLA AIDS Institute, David Geffen School of Medicine, University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA), Los Angeles, CA 90095, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Division of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, David Geffen School of Medicine, UCLA, Los Angeles, CA 90095, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Division of Biomedical Informatics and Division of Developmental Biology, Cincinnati Children&#x2019;s Hospital Research Foundation and the University of Cincinnati College of Medicine, Cincinnati, OH 45267, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Division of Molecular Immunology, Cincinnati Children&#x2019;s Hospital Research Foundation and the University of Cincinnati College of Medicine, Cincinnati, OH 45267, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn id="afn1" fn-type="present-address"><label>*</label>
<p>Present address: The Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, Seattle, WA 98109, USA.</p></fn>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x2020;</label>Corresponding author. E-mail: <email xlink:href="dbrooks@microbio.ucla.edu">dbrooks@microbio.ucla.edu</email></corresp></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>12</day><month>04</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage>202</fpage>
<lpage>207</lpage>
<history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>01</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>02</month><year>2013</year></date></history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="editor"><title>INTERFER(ON)ing Persistence</title><p>During persistent viral infections, a dysregulated immune response fails to control the infection. <bold>Wilson <italic>et al.</italic></bold> (p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="340" issue="6129" page="202">202</related-article>) and <bold>Teijaro <italic>et al.</italic></bold> (p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="340" issue="6129" page="207">207</related-article>; see the Perspective by <bold><related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="340" page="155" issue="6129">Odorizzi and Wherry</related-article></bold>) show this occurs because type I interferons (IFN I), critical for early responses to viral infection, contribute to the altered immunity seen during persistent infection. Antibody blockade of IFN I signaling during chronic lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus (LCMV) in mice resulted in reduced viral titers at later stages of infection, reduced expression of inhibitory immune molecules and prevented the disruptions to secondary lymphoid organs typically observed during persistent infection with LCMV. Whether type I IFNs are also detrimental to persistent viral infection humans, such as HIV and hepatitis C virus, remains to be determined.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Blockade of type I interferons leads to better control of persistent lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus infection. <named-content content-type="related-content">[Also see Perspective by <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="340" page="155" issue="6129">Odorizzi and Wherry</related-article>]</named-content></p></abstract>
<abstract>
<p>Type I interferons (IFN-I) are critical for antiviral immunity; however, chronic IFN-I signaling is associated with hyperimmune activation and disease progression in persistent infections. We demonstrated in mice that blockade of IFN-I signaling diminished chronic immune activation and immune suppression, restored lymphoid tissue architecture, and increased immune parameters associated with control of virus replication, ultimately facilitating clearance of the persistent infection. The accelerated control of persistent infection induced by blocking IFN-I signaling required CD4 T cells and was associated with enhanced IFN-&#x03B3; production. Thus, we demonstrated that interfering with chronic IFN-I signaling during persistent infection redirects the immune environment to enable control of infection.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Kristen Mueller</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Trista Wagoner</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Despite initially robust antiviral immune activity, some viruses, including HIV and hepatitis C virus (HCV) in humans and lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus (LCMV) in mice, outpace the immune response and establish persistent infections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). Besides virus-mediated evasion tactics, the host initiates an immunosuppressive program that actively suppresses antiviral T cell responses and facilitates persistent infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>). The expression of suppressive factors is tightly linked to viral burden (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>), suggesting the presence of an immunologic sensory system that continually measures the magnitude and duration of viral replication and then dynamically modulates the balance between antiviral immunity and immune exhaustion.</p>
<p>In order to identify the mechanisms orchestrating the immunosuppressive program during virus infection, we performed RNA microarray&#x2013;based splenic network analysis. We compared mice infected with one of two LCMV strains: the Armstrong (Arm) strain, which induces a robust T cell response that resolves infection within 8 to 10 days, or the clone 13 (Cl13) strain, which generates a persistent infection because of the sustained expression of an immunosuppressive program, including production of interleukin (IL)-10 and expression of the inhibitory molecule PD-L1 (programmed cell death 1 ligand 1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13"><italic>13</italic></xref>). PD-L1 and IL-10 are similarly expressed at the onset of both acute and persistent infection; however, expression of these molecules wanes with resolution of acute infection, whereas they are maintained or elevated in persistent infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>). Similarly, antigen-presenting cell (APC) populations expressing multiple suppressive factors with the ability to inhibit T cell responses are present early in acute infection but are elevated in the context of persistent infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>). We focused our microarray analysis to identify factors exhibiting a similar kinetic that might be used to sense virus replication dynamics and control immunosuppressive programs. Tissue-wide cytokine expression patterns were similar in acute and persistent infections (fig. S1A). However, analogous to virus clearance kinetics, type I interferon (IFN-I) receptor (IFNR)&#x2013;stimulated genes, signal transducer and activator of transcription (STAT) genes, and IFN-I regulatory factors were initially similarly expressed in LCMV-Arm and LCMV-Cl13 infections but then rapidly dissipated as acute LCMV-Arm infection resolved, whereas they remained elevated in LCMV-Cl13 infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref> and table S1). In total spleen, the expression of IFN-&#x03B1; and IFN-&#x03B2; was not elevated above uninfected mice (fig. S1B); however, at day 9 postinfection IFN-&#x03B1; and IFN-&#x03B2; transcripts were still present in dendritic cells (DCs) from LCMV-Cl13&#x2013;infected mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). Analysis of IL-10&#x2013;green fluorescent protein (GFP) (Vert-X) reporter mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>) revealed that <italic>OAS</italic> and <italic>Mx1</italic> (genes directly stimulated by IFNR signaling) expression levels were specifically enriched in the immunoregulatory APCs that coexpress the highest levels of PD-L1 and IL-10 and can suppress antiviral T cell responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>), suggesting a link between prolonged IFN-I signaling and immunosuppression. Expression of <italic>IRF3</italic>, a gene involved in the IFN-I response but whose expression is not directly regulated by IFNR signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>), was not differentially increased in immunoregulatory APCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption>
<title>Prolonged IFN-I signaling during persistent infection.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Splenic virus titers &#x00B1; SD after acute LCMV-Arm (black) and persistent LCMV-Cl13 (red) infection (left). Gene expression kinetics by microarray analysis of the indicated IFNR-inducible, STAT, and IFN-I regulatory factors (IRFs) in whole spleen tissue after LCMV-Arm (black) or LCMV-Cl13 (red) relative to na&#x00EF;ve (uninfected) mice. Each value indicates the average of three to four mice per group per time point. Values are shown without error bars for clarity, and the <italic>P</italic> values for each gene are indicated in table S1. PFU, plaque-forming units. (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>IFN</italic>&#x03B1; (left) and <italic>IFN</italic>&#x03B2; (right) mRNA expression relative to a control gene, <italic>HPRT</italic>, in splenic DCs from na&#x00EF;ve or LCMV-Arm&#x2013; or LCMV-Cl13&#x2013;infected mice (day 9). N.D. indicates that <italic>IFN</italic>&#x03B1; or <italic>IFN</italic>&#x03B2; transcripts were not detected after 40 cycles of amplification. <italic>HPRT</italic> mRNA expression was measurable in all samples. (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>Mx1</italic>, <italic>OAS</italic>, and <italic>IRF3</italic> mRNA expression relative to <italic>HPRT</italic> in the indicated IL-10+ (GFP+, green) or IL-10&#x2013; (GFP&#x2013;, black) splenic DCs (top) or macrophages (bottom) 9 days after LCMV-Cl13 infection of Vert-X IL-10 reporter mice. For (B) and (C), each group is a pool of cells from six to eight mice and is representative of two independent experiments.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="340_202_F1"></graphic></fig>
<p>We next determined the impact of IFN-I signaling on the immunosuppressive program in vivo. Although levels of virus replication usually correlate with expression of suppressive factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>), <italic>Ifnar1<sup>&#x2212;/&#x2212;</sup></italic> mice exhibited decreased expression of PD-L1 and IL-10 compared with wild-type mice at day 9 after LCMV-Cl13 infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref> and fig. S2A) despite elevated levels of viral replication and viral antigen (fig. S2, A and B). Furthermore, treatment of splenocytes with IFN&#x03B2; stimulated increased PD-L1 and IL-10 expression (fig. S2C). Taken together, these data suggest that IFN-I signaling drives the immunosuppressive program in vivo. <italic>Ifnar1<sup>&#x2212;/&#x2212;</sup></italic>mice failed to clear LCMV-Arm by day 9 after infection (fig. S2D), consistent with the antiviral and immune stimulatory effect of IFN-I during viral infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16"><italic>16</italic></xref>).</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption>
<title>The immunosuppressive program during persistent infection is dependent on IFN-I signaling.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative histograms and summarized quantification of geometric mean fluorescence intensity (GMFI) show PD-L1 on splenic DCs and macrophages 9 days after LCMV-Cl13 infection in wild-type (WT, black) and <italic>Ifnar1<sup>&#x2212;/&#x2212;</sup></italic> (red) mice. Scatter plots show plasma IL-10 levels on day 9 after LCMV-Cl13 infection. Bar graphs measure IL-10 production by cultured splenocytes (in the absence of exogenous stimulation) isolated 9 days after LCMV-Cl13 infection from WT or <italic>Ifnar1<sup>&#x2212;/&#x2212;</sup></italic> mice. Plasma viral titers in WT or <italic>Ifnar1<sup>&#x2212;/&#x2212;</sup></italic> mice on day 9 after LCMV-Cl13 infection are shown to the far right. Dashed lines indicate the level of detection of the plaque assay (200 PFU). (B to D) WT mice were treated with isotype or IFNR1 blocking antibody beginning 1 day before LCMV-Cl13 infection. (<bold>B</bold>) Graphs indicate GMFI of PD-L1 on splenic CD45+ cells (left), plasma levels of IL-10 (middle), and plasma viral titers (right) of untreated mice (B6), isotype-treated mice, IFNR1 blocking antibody (&#x03B1;IFNR1)&#x2013;treated mice, and untreated <italic>Ifnar1<sup>&#x2212;/&#x2212;</sup></italic> mice. Plasma IL-10 levels on day 15 after LCMV-Cl13 infection are shown on the far right. (<bold>C</bold>) Flow cytometry plots of IL-10 reporter expression (GFP) in splenic DCs from Vert-X mice treated with isotype or IFNR1 blocking antibody. Bar graphs show the frequency of IL-10 expression and the GMFI of PD-L1 expression by splenic DCs. The ratio of IL-10&#x2013;nonproducing to IL-10&#x2013;producing DCs is shown on the far right. (<bold>D</bold>) Hematoxylin and eosin staining of spleens from na&#x00EF;ve mice (left) or on day 9 after LCMV-Cl13 infection of mice treated with isotype (middle) or IFNR1 blocking antibody (right). Symbols represent individual mice with bars indicating the mean of the group. In bar graphs, the data represent the average &#x00B1; SD of three to six mice per group. All data are representative of two or more independent experiments. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="340_202_F2"></graphic></fig>
<p>To resolve the role of IFN-I in induction of the immunosuppressive program separate from potential abnormalities of life-long genetic deficiency in <italic>Ifnar1<sup>&#x2212;/&#x2212;</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17"><italic>17</italic></xref>), we treated wild-type mice with an IFNR1-blocking antibody beginning 1 day before LCMV-Cl13 infection. IFNR1 blockade diminished <italic>Mx1</italic>, <italic>OAS</italic>, and <italic>IRF7</italic> expression in multiple tissues and cell types (fig. S3A), indicating the ability to inhibit IFN-I signaling in vivo. Analogous to persistently infected <italic>Ifnar1<sup>&#x2212;/&#x2212;</sup></italic> mice, IFNR1 antibody blockade led to decreased PD-L1 and IL-10 expression and elevated virus titers compared with isotype antibody&#x2013;treated LCMV-Cl13&#x2013;infected mice on day 9 after infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). IL-10 levels rebounded when IFNR1 blocking antibody treatment was withdrawn (day 15; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>), indicating sensitive surveillance and rapid modulation of the immunosuppressive state through IFN-I signaling. Heightened IFN-I signaling can inhibit inflammasome activity in some situations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18"><italic>18</italic></xref>). However, despite higher levels of virus replication and LCMV antigen in splenic APCs from persistently infected mice treated with IFNR1 blocking antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref> and fig. S2B), reduced amounts of IL-1, IL-18, and inflammasome activation were observed (fig. S3B), indicating that blockade of IFN-I signaling decreases chronic inflammation during persistent infection. The reduced levels of inhibitory factors and chronic activation after IFNR1 blockade were not indicative of global down-regulation of proinflammatory cytokines, and in fact expression of IFN-&#x03B3;, a factor critical for control and therapeutic resolution of persistent LCMV infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16"><italic>16</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19"><italic>19</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20"><italic>20</italic></xref>), was elevated after IFNR1 blockade (fig. S3B). Thus, IFNR blockade during persistent infection diminishes immunosuppressive signals and chronic inflammation during persistent infection.</p>
<p>IFNR1 antibody blockade before infection also decreased the level of IL-10&#x2013; and PD-L1&#x2013;expressing immunoregulatory DCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>), leading to an enhanced ratio of stimulatory to immunoregulatory DCs. Moreover, IFNR1 antibody blockade prevented the splenic disorganization associated with impaired immune cell interactions and the inability to control persistent infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21"><italic>21</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23"><italic>23</italic></xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref> and fig. S3C). Thus, immune cells are likely better positioned to interact with one another, and, because of the decrease in immunoregulatory DC frequency, those interactions are more likely to be stimulatory.</p>
<p>We next determined how blockade of IFN-I signaling before infection contributed to control of persistent infection. Although virus titers were initially increased in mice treated with IFNR1 blocking antibody, by 30 days postinfection viremia was reduced compared with isotype treatment, and many of the mice had already controlled infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Furthermore, virus titers were decreased in multiple compartments, including the kidney (a life-long reservoir of LCMV-Cl13) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). Mirroring findings in <italic>Ifnar1<sup>&#x2212;/&#x2212;</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16"><italic>16</italic></xref>), IFNR1 blockade in wild-type mice led to persistent infection with LCMV-Arm (fig. S2D), demonstrating the antiviral activity of IFN-I and its requirement to control acute viral infection.</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption>
<title>IFNR1 blockade enhances control of persistent infection.</title>
<p>WT mice were treated with isotype or IFNR1 blocking antibody beginning 1 day before LCMV-Cl13 infection. (<bold>A</bold>) Plasma virus titers at the indicated time points after infection. (<bold>B</bold>) Viral titers in plasma, liver, and kidney 30 days after infection. (<bold>C</bold>) Graphs indicate total numbers of IFN-&#x03B3;&#x2013;expressing and of multicytokine-producing (polyfunctional) LCMV-GP<sub>61-80</sub>&#x2013;specific CD4 T cells and LCMV-GP<sub>33-41</sub>&#x2013;specific CD8 T cells. (<bold>D</bold>) Plasma viral titers at day 30 after LCMV-Cl13 infection in mice that were either undepleted of cells and treated with isotype (iso/iso) or IFNR1 (&#x03B1;IFNR1/iso) blocking antibody or depleted of CD4 T cells (&#x03B1;CD4) or NK cells (&#x03B1;NK) before infection and IFNR1 blocking antibody treatment. (<bold>E</bold>) Plasma virus titers at the indicated time point after LCMV-Cl13 infection in mice that were either treated with isotype or IFNR1 blocking antibody with or without anti&#x2013;IFN-&#x03B3; (&#x03B1;IFN-&#x03B3;). <italic>x</italic> axis labels indicate (top) IFNRI or isotype and (bottom) cell or IFN-&#x03B3; depleting antibody treatments. Each symbol in the scatter plots represents an individual mouse with bars indicating the mean of the group. Dashed lines indicate the level of detection of the plaque assay (200 PFU). Data are representative of two or more independent experiments. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="340_202_F3"></graphic></fig>
<p>We next sought to understand the immune mechanisms through which IFNR1 blockade enables control of persistent viral infection. IFNR1 blockade before infection induced a numerical increase in many immune subsets 9 days after infection including the total number of functional virus-specific CD4 T cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref> and fig. S4A). However, despite an overall increase in B cells and CD4 T cells, LCMV-specific antibody titers were not elevated in IFNR1 blocking antibody&#x2013;treated mice at day 9 or 30 after infection (fig. S4B). Unlike virus-specific CD4 T cells, virus-specific CD8 T cell numbers and cytokine production were similar or slightly reduced when IFN-I signaling was blocked (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref> and fig. S4C). On the basis of the increase in natural killer (NK) cells, virus-specific CD4 T cells, and systemic IFN-&#x03B3; levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref> and figs. S3B and S4A), we sought to examine the role of each of these factors in accelerating virus clearance after IFNR1 blockade. CD4 depletion before infection abrogated the accelerated virus control engendered by IFNR1 blockade, whereas NK cell depletion did not affect IFNR1 blockade&#x2013;mediated clearance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). To assess the role of increased IFN-&#x03B3; in IFNR1 blockade&#x2013;induced virus clearance, we treated mice with IFNR1 blocking antibody with or without IFN-&#x03B3; blocking antibodies at the time of LCMV-Cl13 infection. The accelerated clearance of persistent infection after IFNR1 blockade was abrogated in mice cotreated with IFN-&#x03B3; blocking antibody (anti&#x2013;IFN-&#x03B3;) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref>). Although occurring later than in IFN-&#x03B3; knockout mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24"><italic>24</italic></xref>), mice treated with anti&#x2013;IFN-&#x03B3; alone died ~35 days after infection, whereas mice receiving IFNR1 blocking antibody plus anti&#x2013;IFN-&#x03B3; survived and cleared infection similar to untreated mice. Together, these results indicate that IFNR1 antibody stimulates accelerated clearance of persistent virus infection through CD4 T cell and IFN-&#x03B3;&#x2013;dependent mechanisms.</p>
<p>We next determined whether therapeutic blockade of IFN-I signaling affected an established LCMV-Cl13 infection. Blockade of IFNR1 beginning 25 days after infection accelerated control of persistent infection in multiple compartments compared with isotype treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4, A and B</xref>). The enhanced control of infection occurred despite the initial increase in virus titers immediately after IFNR1 blocking antibody therapy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Blockade of IFNR1 beginning 25 days after infection reduced the IFN-I gene expression signature and decreased IL-10 and PD-L1 levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4, C and D</xref>), demonstrating that IFN-I continues to be a key component of an immunologic surveillance system and stimulator of the immunosuppressive program throughout persistent infection. Thus, therapeutically ablating chronic IFN-I immune activation in vivo enhances control of persistent LCMV infection.</p>
<fig id="F4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption>
<title>Therapeutic IFNR1 antibody blockade dampens the immunosuppressive program and facilitates clearance of persistent infection.</title>
<p>WT mice were treated with isotype or IFNR1 blocking antibody beginning on day 25 after LCMV-Cl13 infection. (<bold>A</bold>) Plasma viral titers at the indicated time points. The percent of mice at each time point exhibiting detectible virus titers is summarized in the kinetic graph to the right, with the shaded area representing the time of treatment. The data are combined from two experiments. (<bold>B</bold>) Viral titers in the plasma, liver, and kidney at day 46 after LCMV-Cl13 infection. (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>OAS</italic>, <italic>Mx1</italic>, and <italic>IRF7</italic> mRNA expression relative to <italic>HPRT</italic> in splenocytes from na&#x00EF;ve mice (white) or on day 30 after LCMV-Cl13 infection in mice treated with isotype (black) or IFNR1 (red) blocking antibody. (<bold>D</bold>) Graphs indicate GMFI of PD-L1 on splenic dendritic cells (left) and plasma IL-10 levels (right) on day 30 after LCMV-Cl13 infection in mice treated with isotype or IFNR1 blocking antibody. Each symbol in the scatter plot represents an individual mouse, and bar graphs indicate the average value &#x00B1; SD. All data are representative of two to five independent experiments. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="340_202_F4"></graphic></fig>
<p>Our results demonstrate that chronic IFN-I signaling during persistent infection drives the immunosuppressive program and that interfering with IFN-I signaling restores multiple parameters of productive immunity, allowing for viral clearance. IFN-I treatment in combination with the antiviral drug ribavirin is often effective at eradicating HCV infection. However, some patients fail to have a sustained virologic response. A characteristic of patients that fail IFN-I/ribavirin therapy is a heightened IFN-I signature before treatment that fails to substantially increase with therapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25"><italic>25</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26"><italic>26</italic></xref>). Thus, the initially high IFN-I signature may lead to enhanced immune dysfunction, and consequently adding more IFN-I is ineffective. These results highlight the duality of IFN-I during viral infection: Acute IFN-I signals possess antiviral and immune stimulatory potential required for clearance of infection, but when virus cannot be controlled, acutely sustained IFN-I signaling induces immunosuppression that facilitates persistent virus infection. Considering that HIV and HCV infections are also associated with immune activation driven by chronic IFN-I signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23"><italic>23</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29"><italic>29</italic></xref>), a similar blockade of IFN-I may improve control of these infections. In total, our data support IFN-I as a central rheostat and regulator of the immunosuppressive program and the possibility that it may be feasible to redirect entire immunologic programs by modulating activity of a single pathway: IFN-I.</p>
</body>
<back><app-group><app>
<title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/340/6129/202/DC1">www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/340/6129/202/DC1</ext-link></p>
<p>Materials and Methods</p>
<p>Figs. S1 to S4</p>
<p>Table S1</p>
<p>Reference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30"><italic>30</italic></xref>)</p></supplementary-material></app></app-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Translating insights from persistent LCMV infection into anti-HIV immunity</article-title>. <source>Immunol. Res.</source> 
<volume>48</volume>, 
<fpage>3</fpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12026-010-8162-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20725865</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Visualizing antigen-specific and infected cells in situ predicts outcomes in early viral infection</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>323</volume>, 
<fpage>1726</fpage> (<year>2009</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1168676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19325114</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Restoring function in exhausted CD8 T cells during chronic viral infection</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>439</volume>, 
<fpage>682</fpage> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16382236</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Interleukin-10 determines viral clearance or persistence in vivo</article-title>. <source>Nat. Med.</source> 
<volume>12</volume>, 
<fpage>1301</fpage> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm1492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17041596</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ejrnaes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Resolution of a chronic viral infection after interleukin-10 receptor blockade</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source> 
<volume>203</volume>, 
<fpage>2461</fpage> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20061462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17030951</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>PD-1 expression on HIV-specific T cells is associated with T-cell exhaustion and disease progression</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>443</volume>, 
<fpage>350</fpage> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16921384</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brockman</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>IL-10 is up-regulated in multiple cell types during viremic HIV infection and reversibly inhibits virus-specific T cells</article-title>. <source>Blood</source> 
<volume>114</volume>, 
<fpage>346</fpage> (<year>2009</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2008-12-191296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19365081</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Emergence of distinct multiarmed immunoregulatory antigen-presenting cells during persistent viral infection</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source> 
<volume>11</volume>, 
<fpage>481</fpage> (<year>2012</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2012.03.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22607801</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clerici</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Role of interleukin-10 in T helper cell dysfunction in asymptomatic individuals infected with the human immunodeficiency virus</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Invest.</source> 
<volume>93</volume>, 
<fpage>768</fpage> (<year>1994</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI117031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8113410</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Landay</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>In vitro restoration of T cell immune function in human immunodeficiency virus-positive persons: effects of interleukin (IL)-12 and anti-IL-10</article-title>. <source>J. Infect. Dis.</source> 
<volume>173</volume>, 
<fpage>1085</fpage> (<year>1996</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/173.5.1085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8627058</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rigopoulou</surname><given-names>E. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>W. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haigh</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naoumov</surname><given-names>N. V.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Blocking of interleukin-10 receptor&#x2014;a novel approach to stimulate T-helper cell type 1 responses to hepatitis C virus</article-title>. <source>Clin. Immunol.</source> 
<volume>117</volume>, 
<fpage>57</fpage> (<year>2005</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clim.2005.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16006191</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brockman</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>IL-10 is up-regulated in multiple cell types during viremic HIV infection and reversibly inhibits virus-specific T cells</article-title>. <source>Blood</source> 
<volume>114</volume>, 
<fpage>346</fpage> (<year>2009</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2008-12-191296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19365081</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><etal /><collab>ATAHC Study Group</collab></person-group>, 
<article-title>Early IL-10 predominant responses are associated with progression to chronic hepatitis C virus infection in injecting drug users</article-title>. <source>J. Viral Hepat.</source> 
<volume>18</volume>, 
<fpage>549</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2893.2010.01335.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20626625</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Nonredundant roles for B cell-derived IL-10 in immune counter-regulation</article-title>. <source>J. Immunol.</source> 
<volume>183</volume>, 
<fpage>2312</fpage> (<year>2009</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.0900185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19620304</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Au</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowther</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juang</surname><given-names>Y. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitha</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Identification of a member of the interferon regulatory factor family that binds to the interferon-stimulated response element and activates expression of interferon-induced genes</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>92</volume>, 
<fpage>11657</fpage> (<year>1995</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.92.25.11657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8524823</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Functional role of type I and type II interferons in antiviral defense</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>264</volume>, 
<fpage>1918</fpage> (<year>1994</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.8009221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8009221</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gough</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnstone</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Constitutive type I interferon modulates homeostatic balance through tonic signaling</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source> 
<volume>36</volume>, 
<fpage>166</fpage> (<year>2012</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2012.01.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22365663</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guarda</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Type I interferon inhibits interleukin-1 production and inflammasome activation</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source> 
<volume>34</volume>, 
<fpage>213</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2011.02.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21349431</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tishon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewicki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rall</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Herrath</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oldstone</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>An essential role for type 1 interferon-gamma in terminating persistent viral infection</article-title>. <source>Virology</source> 
<volume>212</volume>, 
<fpage>244</fpage> (<year>1995</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/viro.1995.1477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7676639</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Von Herrath</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oldstone</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Low-affinity cytotoxic T-lymphocytes require IFN-gamma to clear an acute viral infection</article-title>. <source>Virology</source> 
<volume>229</volume>, 
<fpage>349</fpage> (<year>1997</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/viro.1997.8442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9126248</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tishon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borrow</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oldstone</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Virus-induced immunosuppression. 1. Age at infection relates to a selective or generalized defect</article-title>. <source>Virology</source> 
<volume>195</volume>, 
<fpage>397</fpage> (<year>1993</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/viro.1993.1389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8393233</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Role of an intact splenic microarchitecture in early lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus production</article-title>. <source>J. Virol.</source> 
<volume>76</volume>, 
<fpage>2375</fpage> (<year>2002</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jvi.76.5.2375-2383.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11836415</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moir</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauci</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Pathogenic mechanisms of HIV disease</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Pathol.</source> 
<volume>6</volume>, 
<fpage>223</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-pathol-011110-130254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21034222</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moskophidis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Critical role for alpha/beta and gamma interferons in persistence of lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus by clonal exhaustion of cytotoxic T cells</article-title>. <source>J. Virol.</source> 
<volume>75</volume>, 
<fpage>8407</fpage> (<year>2001</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.75.18.8407-8423.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11507186</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Hepatic gene expression discriminates responders and nonresponders in treatment of chronic hepatitis C viral infection</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> 
<volume>128</volume>, 
<fpage>1437</fpage> (<year>2005</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2005.01.059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15887125</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarasin-Filipowicz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Interferon signaling and treatment outcome in chronic hepatitis C</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>105</volume>, 
<fpage>7034</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0707882105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18467494</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosinger</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Global genomic analysis reveals rapid control of a robust innate response in SIV-infected sooty mangabeys</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Invest.</source> 
<volume>119</volume>, 
<fpage>3556</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19959874</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacquelin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Nonpathogenic SIV infection of African green monkeys induces a strong but rapidly controlled type I IFN response</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Invest.</source> 
<volume>119</volume>, 
<fpage>3544</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19959873</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolen</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>The blood transcriptional signature of chronic hepatitis C virus is consistent with an ongoing interferon-mediated antiviral response</article-title>. <source>J. Interferon Cytokine Res.</source> 
<volume>33</volume>, 
<fpage>15</fpage> (<year>2013</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jir.2012.0037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23067362</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hahm</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trifilo</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuniga</surname><given-names>E. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oldstone</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Viruses evade the immune system through type I interferon-mediated STAT2-dependent, but STAT1-independent, signaling</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source> 
<volume>22</volume>, 
<fpage>247</fpage> (<year>2005</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2005.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15723812</pub-id></citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank S. Bensinger for insightful discussion and critical review of the manuscript, all the members of the Brooks laboratory for discussions and technical assistance, and the UCLA Translational Pathology Core Facility for expert histological tissue processing and analysis. The data presented in the manuscript are tabulated in the main paper and in the supplementary materials. D.G.B. and E.B.W. are named inventors on a provisional patent assigned to The Regents of the University of California relating in part to methods of treating chronic viral infections by administering agents that inhibit IFN. The microarray data set from this study is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link> (accession no. GSE44322). Our work was supported by the NIH (grants AI085043 and AI082975 to D.G.B., AI060567 to E.B.W., and HL108949 to J.D.), an Institutional Clinical and Translational Science Award (NIH/NCATS 8UL1TR000077-04 to B.J.A.), and the UCLA Center for AIDS Research (P30 AI028697).</p>
</ack></back>
</article>