<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Findings</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Findings</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>findings</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Virology</subject><subject>Medicine</subject><subject>Computer-Science</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>MEDICINE</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>On Twitter, #Antivaccination Goes Viral</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>12</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage seq="a">128</fpage>
<lpage>128</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="findings.pdf" />
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>When fear goes viral on the Internet, it can help spread viruses in the real world. Antivaccination tweets, researchers find, spread much faster than those supportive of vaccines.</p>
<p>Biologist and computer scientist Marcel Salath&#x00E9; and colleagues at Pennsylvania State University, University Park, collected almost half a million vaccine-related tweets during the 2009 influenza pandemic and categorized those relevant to flu as positive, negative, or neutral. (Undergrads rated the first 47,143 tweets; then an algorithm took over.) Negative tweets were often retweeted, while positive ones generally weren't, the team reported in a paper published online on 4 April in <italic>EPJ Data Science</italic>. Instead, too much positive sentiment appeared to backfire: Twitter users who received many provaccine tweets sent out more negative messages themselves. Perhaps some held antivaccination views that they didn't express "until they were bombarded with positive messages," Salath&#x00E9; says.</p>
<p>"We are more compelled by fear than by rational thinking," says Paul Offit, director of the Vaccine Education Center at The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia in Pennsylvania. To reach the public, vaccine advocates may have to go negative themselves, he adds&#x2014;for instance, by tapping into people's fear of losing a child.</p>
</body>
</article>