<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Virology</subject><subject>Zoology</subject><subject>Genetics</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ASIA/PACIFIC NEWS</subject><subject>MEDICINE</subject><subject>VIROLOGY</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Influenza</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>New Flu Virus in China Worries and Confuses</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>Jon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn id="FN1">
<label>*</label>
<p>With reporting by Kai Kupferschmidt and Mara Hvistendahl.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>12</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage>129</fpage>
<lpage>130</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Evidence suggests that novel bird flu virus H7N9 isn't spreading between people, but how patients became infected is still unclear.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>A novel bird flu virus, designated H7N9, has infected three humans in China, killing two of them. While the Chinese government has won praise for aggressively pursuing this outbreak and openly discussing its findings, how the confirmed cases became infected is a mystery. Still, many researchers are guardedly optimistic: There is no persuasive evidence that the virus spreads between people, an ability it would need to set off the next flu pandemic. </p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Bird culls.</title>
<p>Health officials killed nearly 100,000 poultry in Shanghai markets after finding H7N9-infected birds there.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_129_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: STR/AFP/GETTY IMAGES</attrib>
</fig>
<p>As many an influenza researcher has observed, the virus that they study is predictably unpredictable. But when a bird flu virus makes the jump to people, it's easy to predict how humans will react: Pandemic jitters will reverberate around the world, media will scrutinize the actions of public officials, and investigators will begin racing to answer questions about the virus's origins, spread, and potential threat.</p>
<p>The scenario unfolded again after China's National Health and Family Planning Commission announced on 31 March that a bird flu virus, designated H7N9, had infected three humans, killing two of them. But so far, researchers are guardedly optimistic: There is no persuasive evidence that the virus spreads between people, an ability it would need to set off the next flu pandemic. On 9 April, as <italic>Science</italic> went to press, a steady trickle of Chinese government reports had confirmed 28 cases and eight deaths.</p>
<p>The Chinese government has won praise for aggressively pursuing this outbreak and openly discussing its findings (see sidebar, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="340" page="130" issue="6129">130</related-article>). Chinese officials have monitored the health of more than 600 close contacts of confirmed cases&#x2014;the earliest of whom became ill in mid-February&#x2014;and have not found infections. "So far, there's no human-to-human transmission&#x2014;that's the good news," says virologist Ab Osterhaus of Erasmus MC in Rotterdam, the Netherlands. "If it would have been there, you would probably have seen it by now."</p>
<p>Part of the bad news is that it remains a mystery how the confirmed cases became infected. H7N9 influenza viruses are not often detected in birds, notes Robert Webster, an influenza researcher at St. Jude Children's Research Hospital in Memphis, Tennessee. "We rarely ever find the damn thing," he says. In 2003, the Netherlands had an outbreak in humans of a related bird flu strain, H7N7; but that virus came to light because it readily killed chickens and then mainly caused mild eye problems, such as conjunctivitis, in humans. China has not reported any H7N9-related disease in commercial poultry. "The most important thing now is the Chinese have to do whatever they can to find the origin," Osterhaus says.</p>
<p>On 5 April, China's Ministry of Agriculture reported that pigeon and chicken samples from two poultry markets in Shanghai, home to about half the confirmed cases, tested positive for H7N9. The National Avian Flu Reference Laboratory sequenced the virus's genome and said it was very similar to the sequences of human isolates. Officials culled some 98,000 poultry and subsequently stopped the sale of live birds at city markets. Nanjing and Hangzhou, large cities a few hundred kilometers away affected by the outbreak, closed poultry markets, too. Some, but not all, of the human cases had known contact with poultry.</p>
<p>In early media reports, pigs had come under suspicion as a potential source. In March, bloggers revealed that thousands of dead pigs were washing up on the shores of the Huangpu River, which flows through Shanghai. Avian influenza viruses readily infect pigs, but the Shanghai Animal Disease Prevention and Control Center has reported that it tested 34 carcasses and none had the virus. J&#x00FC;rgen Richt, a swine flu researcher at Kansas State University, Manhattan, notes that 34 samples isn't very many and that influenza RNA may have become degraded during the trip downriver. "Pigs could be positive even if they test negative," Richt says. Still, he thinks that the pig origin hypothesis is "highly speculative," in part because other flu strains that are lethal in humans cause little disease in swine.</p>
<p>The clearest evidence so far about the origin of H7N9 comes from its genes. Richt's lab and several others began studying the sequences of H7N9 viruses from human cases immediately after China made them available. Type A influenza viruses like this one have a genome made up of eight RNA segments containing 11 genes coding for 11 proteins, including hemagglutinin and neuraminidase, which stick out from the viral surface. (They are the "H" and "N" in the names of influenza subtypes.) Comparisons with known influenza sequences show that all of the genes in the new virus closely resemble ones found in avian flu strains. But this H7N9 is a mashup, or "reassortant," of several such strains.</p>
<p>The genes that code for the proteins inside of the H7N9 virus closely match genes from H9N2 isolates recently found in chickens, pigeons, and bramblings (a type of finch) in China. H9N2 is a "totally benign virus," Webster says, and "is in every big chicken house from China to Israel to Germany." The H7, in contrast, appears similar to an H7N3 found in Chinese ducks 2 years ago, while the N9 has ties to H11N9 viruses found in ducks and wild birds in Europe and Asia.</p>
<p>Adding to the confusing backstory are mutations in H7N9 genes that suggest how the strain enters and sickens humans. Avian influenza typically doesn't affect humans because receptors on our cells do not allow bird viruses to attach to them. But three of the first four human H7N9 isolates had mutations in what's known as H7's receptor binding site, allowing it to infect mammals, says Michael Shaw of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta. Researchers found another mutation in the <italic>PB2</italic> subunit of influenza's polymerase enzyme that's also known to help the virus thrive in mammals. In addition, H7N9 has a deletion in the neuraminidase gene that researchers typically find in domestic chickens and quail. "It looks like this virus has been in multiple hosts, and it's a real detective story to figure out which paths it has gone through to get to this point," Shaw says.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Origin clues.</title>
<p>Sequences of eight RNA segments from human H7N9 isolates show close ties to different bird viruses.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_129_F2"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: ADAPTED FROM CHARLES DAVIS/CDC</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Richard Webby, another influenza researcher at St. Jude in Memphis, says a central mystery is whether humans became infected with H7N9s that had mammalian adaptations&#x2014;which would suggest the virus has been circulating in mammals for some time&#x2014;or whether those variations occurred after the virus replicated in their bodies. "I don't think we've seen quite these many changes upon infection, but it is possible," Webby says. Either way, the changes are "worrying," he says.</p>
<p>The World Health Organization announced plans to work with partner countries to begin development of an H7N9 vaccine for humans, although whether that ever moves into large-scale production may depend on how readily the virus spreads. The few known cases so far may be the tip of an iceberg: Researchers will have to screen for antibodies to H7N9 in large numbers of people, which might reveal that many had mild or no disease.</p>
<p>Richt says that he and his colleagues urgently need isolates of the virus to begin testing its effects in various species, including chickens, pigs, monkeys, and ferrets. Maybe the virus readily infects pigs and spreads between them, making swine an important reservoir. Maybe it reduces egg production in hens or weight in broilers, which would help identify infected flocks and rapidly contain spread. Animal studies can also clarify the likelihood of airborne transmission in mammals; Osterhaus and his colleagues last year caused an international ruckus when they published ferret experiments that showed how easily this could happen with a different bird flu virus that has jumped into humans (<italic>Science</italic>, 22 June 2012, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-publication" vol="336" page="1494" issue="6088">1494</related-article>). "A lot of work needs to be done," Osterhaus says. "We have to take this seriously."</p>
</body>
</article>