<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<!--Produced by Media Entities, Inc., XMLtoolWorks, 10 Aug 2012-->
<article article-type="other" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">STM</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science Translational Medicine</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Sci. Transl. Med.</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1946-6234</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1946-6242</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3004611</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3004611</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>Medicine</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>GLIO-VASCULAR Circulation</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Brain Superhighways</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Begley</surname><given-names>David J.</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff id="aff1">Institute of Pharmaceutical Science, King&#x2019;s College London, London SE1 9NH, UK.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes><corresp id="cor1">E-mail: <email xlink:href="david.begley@kcl.ac.uk">david.begley@kcl.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>147</issue>
<fpage>147fs29</fpage>
<lpage>147fs29</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; , American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>Glio-vascular pathways guide water flow and solute clearance in the brain.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract>
<p>Glio-vascular pathways guide water flow and solute clearance in the brain (Iliff <italic>et al</italic>., this issue).</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>KL</meta-value></custom-meta>
<custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>CF</meta-value></custom-meta>
<custom-meta><meta-name>Number-figs</meta-name><meta-value>1</meta-value></custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>For many years, neuroscientists have naturally focused on neuronal structure and function because these cells undertake the essential integrative and behavioral electrical activity of the brain. But the nervous system comprises other cell types, such as glial cells, that have received relatively less attention. In this issue of <italic>Science Translational Medicine</italic>, Iliff <italic>et al</italic>. describe a glial-vascular pathway that clears solute, including amyloid &#x03B2; protein, from the brain extracellular space (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>As the size of the mammalian brain increases, glial cell functions appear to become more and more critical to proper brain physiology. For example, mouse, cat, human, and fin-whale brains contain glial cell&#x2013;to-neuron ratios of approximately 1:10, 1:5, 1:2, and &gt;1:0.8, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). Clearly, the larger and more complex the brain becomes and the greater the distances over which function must be coordinated, the more important the role of glial cells seems to become. </p>
<p>Glial cells are divided into three broad functional categories: tanycytes [cells that transport hormones from the cerebro-spinal fluid (CSF) to brain tissue], astrocytes [also called astroglia, star-shaped cells that support the blood-brain barrier (BBB), supply nutrients, and engage in healing and scar formation], and microglia (brain macrophages that function in immune defense). Within the mature brain, these three functional categories are further divided into at least 11 different glial subtypes that display a number of different astrocytic morphologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). Tanycytes and astroglial cells have long processes that extend considerable distances within the brain tissue and form cytoplasmic bridges between the internal ependymal surfaces of the CSF-filled ventricles and the pial (outer) surface of the brain and make intimate contact with neurons and endothelial cells that form the BBB (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> for anatomical relationships between tanycytes and astroglial cells and other brain structures).</p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p><bold>Flow</bold>. In the brain microcirculation, both astrocytes and tanycytes have long processes that run through the brain tissue and connect the cells with other structures. The tanycytes and astrocytes form endfeet (a) that are applied closely to the microvasculature that forms the BBB and express AQP4 adjacent to the endothelial basement membrane (basal lamina). The cells also bear processes that connect the cells with other brain structures. These processes may either interdigitate with the ependymal cells (c) that line the brain ventricles and directly contact the CSF (b) or may abut the ependymal cells and extend to the pial surface of the brain, which faces the subarachnoid CSF space (d). Other processes also terminate at neuronal cell bodies (e). The ependymal epithelium that covers the choroid plexuses across which CSF is secreted has tight junctions between the cells (f), as do the endothelial cells that form the BBB. Possible directions for water flow though the cells are indicated by the arrows. Adapted from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="4147fs29-F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: B. STRAUCH/<italic>SCIENCE TRANSLATIONAL MEDICINE</italic></attrib></fig>
<sec sec-type="other1" disp-level="1">
<title>BULK FLOW</title>
<p>Aquaporins belong to a family of proteins that forms pores&#x2014;or water channels&#x2014;in a cell&#x2019;s plasma membrane that regulate the flow of water in and out of the cell. In the astroglia, aquaporin-4 (AQP4) is expressed chiefly in membranes of the outer endfeet and faces the extracellular matrix, which is applied closely to the capillary endothelium that forms the BBB. There is a continous movement of water through the brain extracellular space, a process referred to as bulk flow. This water is partly produced by filtration and secretion across the capillaries and small vessels that form the brain microcirculation and partly produced by metabolic processes in the brain cells themselves. The continuous production of this water powers its movement through the brain extracellular spaces. Solutes in the extracellular space will also move along with the water. However, the extracellular space is not a simple solution, but rather is a complex gel of proteins and glycosaminoglycans. Thus, solutes will be subject to a gel filtration effect as they move in the water flow, and molecular size, shape, and charge will influence their rate of movement.</p>
<p>In the new work, Iliff <italic>et al</italic>. use two-photon imaging techniques with small but differently sized fluorescent and radiolabeled tracers to illustrate the rates and directions of CSF (water and solute) movement through the brains of mice. On the basis of these results, the authors suggest that water that is filtered or secreted by the microcirculation can be rapidly taken up by the astrocytic endfeet via AQP4-containing pores and distributed throughout the astrocyte cytoplasm. The water is then released globally into the brain extracellular fluid and cleared from the brain by bulk-flow processes. Water can leave the brain tissue across the pial and ependymal surfaces of the brain and enter the CSF, which then drains by a variety of routes into the general blood circulation. Iliff <italic>et al</italic>. also found that water flow into the brain occurred partly along the Virchow-Robin spaces of the arterioles entering the brain, powered by pulsations in the vessels, and water flow out of the brain proceeded via the corresponding spaces surrounding the venules when exiting the brain tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
<p>It has been estimated that in the normal human brain, interstitial fluid turns over approximately every 20 hours and the CSF volume every 4.4 hours (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>). In addition to the pathway proposed by Iliff <italic>et al</italic>., the other sources of brain fluid described above could work in parallel to produce the bulk movement of water through the brain tissue. The authors suggest that under normal physiological conditions, these bulk-flow mechanisms may aid in the clearance of solutes, such as amyloid &#x03B2;, from the extracellular fluid. Furthermore, using radiolabeled amyloid &#x03B2; protein injected directly into mouse brains, the authors showed that clearance of the protein from the brain parenchyma was significantly reduced in mice in which AQP4 had been knocked out relative to wild-type controls. Thus, a continued disturbance of a glial extracellular water flow path may be an etiological feature in the development of Alzheimer&#x2019;s disease.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="other2" disp-level="1">
<title>NETWORK SOLUTIONS</title>
<p>In addition to their endfeet connections, astrocytes link to a variety of cell types in the brain via their gap junctions, which specify a complex network of highways that bridge and ultimately connect a wide range of brain regions. However, this aspect of astrocytic influences is often poorly considered when exploring normal brain function and pathological states. An important function of astrocytes might be to rapidly transport various cytoplasmic signals and solutes from one region of the brain to another, and this movement may indeed be faster and more direct than diffusive or bulk flow movement via the extracellular space of the brain, where the tortuousity of the extracellular pathway may become a rate-limiting factor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). </p>
<p>It should also be borne in mind that the extracellular space is not simply a fluid-filled compartment but consists of a complex gel, partly formed by the glycoprotein-polysaccharide covering (glycocalyx) of the cells and the extracellular matrix, which contains a complex mixture of proteins and glycoproteins such as laminins, glycosaminoglycans, chondritin sulfate, and heparan. Thus, a solute propelled by bulk flow through the brain extracellular space is subject to a gel-filtration effect and interactions with the many charged and fixed molecules within this space. Thus, solutes in the extracellular fluid of similar molecular size likely do not all move at similar rates or at the same rate as the bulk fluid flow. Indeed, as shown by using quantum dots and other tracers, the extracellular space of the mammalian brain is estimated to have a width of 38 to 64 nm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>), which limits the size of structures that can traverse the space.</p>
<p>Indeed, many drug delivery vectors such as viruses, liposomes, and other nanoparticles are too large to move freely in the extracellular space (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>). Macromolecules and drug delivery vectors are carried across the BBB in endosomes in a process called transcytosis; once inside the brain, these molecules may follow the speedy cytoplasmic route through the tissue, because biological end points can often be observed within a very short time after intravenous injection of the delivery system. Because they link the BBB with more remote structures, astrocytes might provide such a cytoplasmic route through the brain. For example, recent studies have demonstrated the appearance of apolipoprotein E&#x2013; and A&#x2013;targeted albumin nanoparticles in the cytoplasm of neurons throughout the brain within 30 min of intravenous administration. These albumin particles are 200 nm in diameter and are thus unlikely to have taken an extracellular route to the neuronal cell bodies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref><italic>, </italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="other3" disp-level="1">
<title>REPORTERS WITHOUT BORDERS</title>
<p>Enclosure of the brain capillaries by the supporting astrocytic endfeet probably helps to maintain BBB function in the mature brain. It has long been observed that in vitro coculture with astrocytes or astrocyte-conditioned medium induces many BBB features in brain microvascular endothelial cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). Formation of the principle BBB features during vasculogenesis occurs before gliogenesis begins in the developing embryo and fetus (such as the prerequisite tight junctions between endothelial cells) and is probably induced by interactions with pericytes&#x2014;capillary-hugging accessory cells that sit just inside the vessels&#x2019; basement membrane and the astrocytic endfeet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>). </p>
<p>In adult life, pericytes retain their close association with the brain microvasculature where they secrete and model the extracellular matrix, which is distinct in composition from the matrix in the general brain extracellular space and probably has an additional role in the maintenance of BBB integrity. Pericytes also appear to control blood flow, via contractile fingerlike extensions, at the individual capillary level in the mature brain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>The steady bulk flow and turnover of the brain extracellular fluid influenced by astrocytic endfeet not only clears a number of solutes from the extracellular space but also has the effect of distributing signaling molecules, such as growth factors secreted by neurons and glia, to remote brain regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). This phenomenon of long-distance signaling, often referred to as volume transmission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>), plays an important role in the long-term regulation of central nervous system function. Astroglia and their endfeet aquaporins also even out potential osmotic gradients and quickly relieve osmotic stress in damaged areas of the brain tissue and microcirculation. If the aquaporins in the astrocytic endfeet are druggable to the extent that they can be up-regulated and maintained during brain injury, then fluid flow and interstitial clearance in the brain tissue can be maintained during perilous times. Indeed, antagonists of adenosine 5&#x0374;-triphosphate&#x2013;binding P2XR7 receptors in astrocytes inhibit the down-regulation of AQP4 in rats during anoxic brain injury. Manipulating the expression and activity of aquaporins could have important clinical relevance in the control of cerebral edema and bulk clearance of extracellular solutes. Clearly, neurons are not the only long-distance communicators in the brain.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iliff</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plogg</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gundersen</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benveniste</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vates</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deane</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagelhus</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nedergaard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>A paravascular pathway facilitates CSF flow through the brain parenchyma and the clearance of interstitial solutes, including amyloid &#x03B2;</article-title>. <source>Sci. Transl. Med.</source> <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>147ra111</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tower</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>O. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>The activities of butyrylcholinesterase and carbonic anhydrase, the rate of anaerobic glycolysis, and the question of a constant density of glial cells in cerebral cortices of various mammalian species from mouse to whale</article-title>. <source>J. Neurochem.</source> <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>278</lpage> (<year>1973</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.1973.tb12126.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4633361</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="book">N. J. Abbott, in <italic>Blood-Brain Barrier Interfaces: From Ontology to Artificial Barriers</italic>, R. Dermietzel, D. C. Spray, M. Nedergaard, Eds. (Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH, Weinheim, 2006), pp.189&#x2013;208.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="book">D. J. Begley, E. U. Khan, C. Rollinson, N. J. Abbott, A. Regina, F. Roux, in <italic>The Blood-Brain Barrier and Drug Delivery to the CNS</italic>, D. J. Begley, M. W. Bradbury, J. Kreuter, Eds. (Marcel Dekker, NY and Basel, 2000), pp. 93&#x2013;108.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>In vivo diffusion analysis with quantum dots and dextrans predicts the width of brain extracellular space</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> <volume>103</volume>, <fpage>5567</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5572</lpage> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0509425103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16567637</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zensi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Begley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontikis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Legros</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihoreanu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;chel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>von Briesen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreuter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Albumin nanoparticles targeted with Apo E enter the CNS by transcytosis and are delivered to neurones</article-title>. <source>J. Control. Release</source> <volume>137</volume>, <fpage>78</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>86</lpage> (<year>2009</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jconrel.2009.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19285109</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zensi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Begley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontikis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Legros</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihoreanu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;chel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreuter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Human serum albumin nanoparticles modified with apolipoprotein A-I cross the blood-brain barrier and enter the rodent brain</article-title>. <source>J. Drug Target.</source> <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>842</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>848</lpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/1061186X.2010.513712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20849354</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daneman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kebede</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barres</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Pericytes are required for blood-brain barrier integrity during embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>468</volume>, <fpage>562</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>566</lpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20944625</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peppiatt</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Howarth</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mobbs</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Attwell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Bidirectional control of CNS capillary diameter by pericytes</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>443</volume>, <fpage>700</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>704</lpage> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17036005</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="book">A. Chodobska, G. D. Silverberg, J. Szmydynger-Chodobska, in <italic>The Blood-Cerebrospinal Fluid Barrier</italic>, W. Zheng, A. Chodobska Eds. (Chapman and Hall/CRC, Taylor and Francis Group, Boca Raton, London, New York, Singapore, 2005), pp.241&#x2013;278.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<ack>
<p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author thanks the Engineering and Physical Science Research Council (EPSRC-UK), the UK Society for Mucopolysaccharide Diseases, the Brains for Brain Foundation, and Shire Human Genetic Therapies for support. <bold>Competing interests:</bold> The author declares that he has no competing interests.</p>
</ack>
</back>
</article>
