<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1224876</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1224876</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Books <italic>et al.</italic></subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>books</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>BOTANY</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Plant Science</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Life from a Rooted Perspective</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Eller</surname><given-names>Chelsie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>The reviewer is at the Department of Biochemistry, University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI 53706-1544, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>eller@wisc.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage>295</fpage>
<lpage>296</lpage>
<product product-type="book"><bold>What a Plant Knows: A Field Guide to the Senses.</bold> Daniel Chamovitz. Scientific American/Farrar, Straus and Giroux, New York, 2012. 187 pp. $23. ISBN 9780374288730.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Chamovitz provides an anti-sensationalist perspective on plants' abilities to sense and respond to their surroundings.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Chamovitz provides an anti-sensationalist perspective on plants' abilities to sense and respond to their surroundings.</p></abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sherman J. Suter</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Cynthia Howe</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Think of your fondest memories. How many of those contain some kind of plant? Perhaps you recall a vacation visit to awe-inspiring giant sequoias; the vibrant yellows, oranges, and reds of a New England fall; or receiving roses on a special occasion. Although we often draw emotional ties to plants, it's easy to pass them daily with little regard. However, have you ever stopped and thought about the plants' ability to sense us?</p>
<p>In <italic>What a Plant Knows</italic>, Daniel Chamovitz guides readers through the landscape of plant biology and describes how it is not all that different from our own biological complexity. Chamovitz (a plant biologist at Tel Aviv University) draws on centuries of landmark research on plants' sensory capabilities, including Darwin's observations that canary grass grows toward light sources and growth experiments in the near-weightless conditions of the International Space Station.</p>
<p>Although a plant is rooted in one spot, it is not insensitive to the world. It must be able to detect and respond to environmental changes. Chamovitz discusses several examples, drawing parallels between human senses and those of plants. Plants &#x201C;see&#x201D; using cryptochrome, a blue-light receptor, to determine the time of the day that imparts circadian rhythm. Cryptochromes are now known from every kingdom of life. When a caterpillar nibbles on the leaves of a white poplar, the victim alerts neighboring brethren of the attack by emitting a hormone that surrounding trees can &#x201C;smell.&#x201D; They respond by producing toxic compounds in their leaves to ward off the pest. The classic example of the Venus flytrap highlights that plant's ability to feel the pressure of an unsuspecting lunch and quickly close its jaws, operating via action potentials much like our own nerves.</p>
<p>Whereas plants cannot hear per se, a number of genes involved in hearing impairments in humans have been found in plants. These affect myosin, which is crucial for the function of the hair cells in our inner ear and the root hairs of plants (which allow them to absorb water and nutrients from the soil). Needing to know where the earth is, plants sense gravity. Employing a mechanism similar to that we use for balance, plants contain heavy starchy sacks that sink, thus indicating the down direction. And in order to time their next flowering, many plants remember whether they have experienced a cold season.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Tune deaf.</title>
<p>Music does not affect the growth of marigold (<italic>Tagetes erecta</italic>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_295_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: SANJA565658/WIKIMEDIA COMMONS</attrib>
</fig>
<p>The author never claims that plants are sentient beings with feelings and instead emphasizes their lack of nerves and brains. In fact, he often spotlights the faults of pseudoscience that has advanced alternative claims about plant sentience. (Such reports often lack proper scientific controls and set back the overall progress of plant biology.) Rather, Chamovitz tries to convey the interesting aspects of plants that we may take for granted.</p>
<p>Early on, Chamovitz reminds us that several of the most important discoveries in biology&#x2014;including Robert Hooke's identification of cells (in cork) and Barbara McClintock's recognition of jumping genes (in corn)&#x2014;arose through the study of plants. He gently hints that we should have a greater appreciation of plants' complexity and perceptiveness. Although he doesn't make any controversial arguments, he does suggest that we reconsider what it means to be aware. If plants can see, smell, feel, know where they are, and remember, then perhaps they do possess some kind of intelligence. Maybe that is worth reflecting on the next time you casually stroll past a plant.</p>
</body>
</article>