<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ANTHRO</subject><subject>SOCIOLOGY</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>European Association for South Asian Archaeology and Art Meeting</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Persians Made the Afghan Desert Bloom</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lawler</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage>289</fpage>
<lpage>289</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>A French team surveying a region of north-central Afghanistan has recently discovered large settlements organized around an impressive water system dating back 2500 years.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>North-central Afghanistan is a harsh desert of dunes long thought to have been uninhabited save for the occasional hardy nomad; even today the region is sparsely settled. But a French team surveying the region north and west of Mazar-i-Sharif has recently discovered large settlements organized around an impressive water system dating back 2500 years. No other culture before or since has managed to support large settlements in this desolate region. The find could provide exciting new information on irrigation techniques that made the early central Asian desert bloom, say the archaeologists who work here.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>North-central Afghanistan is a harsh desert of dunes long thought to have been uninhabited save for the occasional hardy nomad; even today the region is sparsely settled. But a French team surveying the region north and west of Mazar-i-Sharif has recently discovered large settlements organized around an impressive water system dating back 2500 years. No other culture before or since has managed to support large settlements in this desolate region. The find could provide exciting new information on irrigation techniques that made the early central Asian desert bloom, say the small cadre of archaeologists who work here.</p>
<p>Roland Besenval, an archaeologist with the French national research agency in Paris; Eric Fouache, a geoarchaeologist at the University of Paris, Sorbonne; and others identified more than 30 large settlements, all dating to the period of the Achaemenid Persian Empire, which flourished from the shores of Greece to western India in the 5th and 4th centuries B.C.E. The empire was overwhelmed by Alexander the Great late in the 4th century B.C.E. The archipelago of northern Afghan settlements appears to have died out at that time or a little earlier, and has been largely uninhabited ever since.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Water lifeline.</title>
<p>The sands of northern Afghanistan (<italic>background</italic>) have covered this ancient canal (<italic>foreground</italic>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_289_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: ROLAND BESENVAL</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Many of these towns or garrisons had massive walls that have been hidden in the sands. One site, Altin Dilyar Tepe, first noted by Russian researchers in the 1970s, sits on a hill that the French team determined was an artificial mound, showing that enormous manpower was used to build it, Besenval says.</p>
<p>Using a tiny, instrument-filled drone called a hexacopter, the team spotted a 2-meter-wide linear feature that led to a 60-by-80-meter basin near Altin Dilyar Tepe. The mud-brick canal stretches for nearly 10 kilometers, pierced periodically with at least two other large basins that coincide with settlements. Besenval says this apparent aqueduct likely carried water for farming from the Balkh River, which flows out of the mountains, across the harsh desert. Achaemenid pottery found nearby dates the structure as early as the 5th century B.C.E. By the 4th century B.C.E., a drying climate may have made this always-marginal land too difficult to farm even with irrigation, Besenval adds.</p>
<p>In Central Asia, where water remains a key and scarce resource, the discovery of a sophisticated water system this ancient excited archaeologists at the meeting. Besenval's interpretation of the feature &#x201C;is very convincing,&#x201D; says archaeologist Pierfrancesco Callieri of the University of Bologna in Italy, who has dug in Central Asia. Besenval also recently found signs of irrigation at a site in Tajikistan that dates back long before the Achaemenids, as early as the 4th millennium B.C.E., suggesting that irrigation has old roots in the area.</p>
<p>Because of security issues, the researchers couldn't stay overnight near the Afghan sites, so they have yet to establish details such as the aqueduct's gradient or whether it stretches another dozen kilometers to reach the Amu Darya river to the north. Besenval is eager to return to gather more data, but security concerns kept him out of the field entirely last season. &#x201C;Our visits have been too short,&#x201D; he says in frustration. &#x201C;And we have so many questions to ask.&#x201D;</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>See abstracts at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.easaa.cnrs.fr/">http://www.easaa.cnrs.fr/</ext-link></p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>