<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI POLICY</subject><subject>GENETICS</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Patents</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>U.S. Appeals Court Hears Gene Patent Arguments</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>Eliot</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage>277</fpage>
<lpage>278</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>James Watson, co-discoverer of DNA's double helix, has signed up as the most celebrated champion of a lawsuit that aims to block patents on human genes.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>James Watson, co-discoverer of DNA's double helix, is championing a lawsuit that aims to block patents on human genes. With a strongly worded amicus brief filed last month, Watson joined a long list of scientists and doctors who have intervened in the test case, scheduled for oral argument on 20 July. A three-judge panel in the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit in Washington, D.C., will consider whether to invalidate patents on breast cancer genes owned by the Utah diagnostic company Myriad Genetics. Biotech leaders claim that if the patent critics win, their industry could suffer; they're campaigning to preserve the status quo.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_277_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: COLD SPRING HARBOR LABORATORY</attrib>
</fig>
<p>James Watson, co-discoverer of DNA&apos;s double helix, has signed up as the most celebrated champion of a lawsuit that aims to block patents on human genes. With a strongly worded amicus brief filed last month, Watson joined a long list of scientists and doctors who have intervened in the test case, scheduled for oral argument on 20 July. A three-judge panel in the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit (CAFC) in Washington, D.C., will consider whether to invalidate patents on breast cancer genes owned by the Utah diagnostic company Myriad Genetics. Biotech leaders claim that if the patent critics win, their industry could suffer; they&apos;re campaigning to preserve the status quo.</p>
<p>At the center of this fight is a challenge to patents on the <italic>BRCA1</italic> and <italic>BRCA2</italic> genes, owned by Myriad since the late 1990s. Myriad&apos;s opponents&#x2014;led by nonprofit attorney Daniel Ravicher and colleagues at two New York City advocacy organizations, the Public Patent Foundation and the American Civil Liberties Union&#x2014;hope to end Myriad&apos;s monopoly on <italic>BRCA</italic> genes and undercut many other DNA patents. They argue that genes are &#x201C;products of nature,&#x201D; not inventions, and for that reason are not patentable. Although U.S. courts have allowed such patents for more than 3 decades, opponents say it&apos;s not too late to reject them. Some judges have agreed.</p>
<p>A U.S. district court in New York sided with Ravicher and his allies in 2010, invalidating many of Myriad&apos;s claims (<italic>Science</italic>, 9 April 2010, p. 
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/328/5975/153.full">153</ext-link>). That decision was partly overturned, however, when it reached the CAFC on appeal in 2011. The case then went to the Supreme Court, which didn&apos;t issue an opinion; instead, it cited its own 9-0 rejection of a different nongene diagnostic patent this spring and ordered the CAFC in March to take a fresh look at the matter in the light of that rejection (<italic>Science</italic>, 30 March , p. 
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/335/6076/1550.2.full#sec-7">1550</ext-link>).</p>
<p>The prolonged fight could well bounce back to the Supreme Court before it&apos;s over, says a longtime follower of the case, attorney Harold Wegner of Foley &amp; Lardner in Washington, D.C. What he finds &#x201C;amazing&#x201D; is the skill with which Ravicher and colleagues have kept the case moving, rallying public opinion to a cause that they portray as good social policy. Other combatants have focused more narrowly on the &#x201C;nuts and bolts&#x201D; of patent law, Wegner says, and the legal tacticians now appear to be on the defensive.</p>
<p>The loudest shot fired at Myriad&apos;s position so far, Wegner says, was from Watson. The brief filed by the 1962 Nobelist argues that courts should recognize that human genes are not ordinary molecules but are &#x201C;fundamentally unique&#x201D; because they &#x201C;transmit the instructions for creating humans.&#x201D; Watson writes: &#x201C;Life&apos;s instructions ought not be controlled by legal monopolies created at the whim of Congress or the courts.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Watson gives a first-person account of the discovery of the double helix, explains how DNA encodes proteins, and notes that even great legal minds can falter when they offer an opinion on genetics&#x2014;citing a comment by Supreme Court Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes Jr. in 1927 on the beneficial use of genetics to eliminate &#x201C;imbeciles&#x201D; from the population. Watson writes that he has long opposed human gene patents, saying that he was &#x201C;forced to resign&#x201D; as the head of the Human Genome Project at the National Institutes of Health in 1992 because his views conflicted with those of the agency. He cites another Nobel winner, University of Manchester geneticist John Sulston, who wrote that gene patents will &#x201C;get in the way of [genetics-based] treatment unless you have a lot of money.&#x201D; Watson argues that biotech companies don&apos;t need human gene patents to make a profit and warns that multigene testing methods could be &#x201C;unnecessarily delayed&#x201D; or halted by a thicket of patent claims.</p>
<p>Myriad disagrees. In its brief, it argues that the Supreme Court&apos;s 9&#x2013;0 decision in March rejecting a diagnostic patent held by Prometheus Laboratories is not relevant to this case. And the company reiterates an argument made before, that patents on <italic>BRCA1</italic> and <italic>BRCA2</italic> do not run afoul of the ban on patenting natural products because they are based on sequences taken from &#x201C;isolated BRCA molecules&#x201D; created in a lab.</p>
<p>More than a dozen groups have filed amicus briefs, some for and some against gene patents. Some support gene patents in principle without specifically backing Myriad&apos;s claims. The Biotechnology Industry Association (BIO), in a brief with the Association of University Technology Managers (AUTM) and others, argues that gene patents should not be restricted and warns of &#x201C;far reaching negative consequences&#x201D; if this advice is ignored. The BIO-AUTM brief says that &#x201C;innumerable other patents claiming medically and industrially useful compounds that are isolated or derived from natural sources&#x201D; would be endangered, such as the antianemia agent erythropoietin, the antibacterial product rapamycin, and a monoclonal antibody (muromonab-CD3) derived from the mouse and used in transplant therapy.</p>
<p>The threat to biotech patents may not be as great as BIO suggests, says Robert Cook-Deegan, an expert on genetics and patents at Duke University&apos;s Institute for Genome Sciences and Policy in Durham, North Carolina. But he thinks that a sweeping ban on patenting natural DNA sequences would affect key industrial and agricultural products. He likes an amicus brief filed by the U.S. Justice Department, a view significantly not endorsed by the Patent and Trademark Office. It proposes a distinction between naturally occurring DNA and DNA that has been &#x201C;markedly&#x201D; or &#x201C;significantly&#x201D; altered to create a new invention during discovery. In this reading, the latter type of DNA is patentable but the former is not. Cook-Deegan thinks this fine-grained logic may be persuasive to judges at CAFC and the Supreme Court. If this rule were applied, Myriad might keep certain patent claims and lose others.</p>
</body>
</article>