<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1225342</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1225342</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Books <italic>et al.</italic></subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>books</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ECOLOGY</subject><subject>OCEANS</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Natural History</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>From the Belly of a Whale</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>DeRuiter</surname><given-names>Stacy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>The reviewer is at the Centre for Research into Ecological and Environmental Modeling, University of St. Andrews, St. Andrews, Fife KY16 9LZ, Scotland, UK.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>sldr@st-andrews.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage seq="b">296</fpage>
<lpage>297</lpage>
<product product-type="book"><bold>Floating Gold: A Natural (and Unnatural) History of Ambergris.</bold> Christopher Kemp. University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 2012. 209 pp. $22.50, &#x00A3;14.50. ISBN 9780226430362.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Blending science, history, and travelogue, Kemp carries readers into the world of the people who seek this coveted essence of sperm whales.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Blending science, history, and travelogue, Kemp carries readers into the world of the people who seek this coveted essence of sperm whales.</p></abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sherman J. Suter</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Cynthia Howe</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Carefully and thoughtfully written, Christopher Kemp's <italic>Floating Gold</italic> can take a place on the bookshelf among my favorite natural histories. Those peer at their subject from many angles, combining facts with observations of the places and people that have become part of its history. Kemp (a molecular biologist) tells stories about ambergris: fragrant stuff, produced in the gut of the sperm whale, that for centuries has been both a prized commodity and a compellingly mysterious substance.</p>
<p>Ambergris begins to form when the sharp, undigested beaks of ingested squid cause irritation in a sperm whale's intestines. In response, the whale produces a secretion that surrounds the beaks, forming proto-ambergris. A lucky whale might pass the growing mass like feces, or the concretion might eventually cause an intestinal blockage so complete as to be fatal. Either way, the black, sticky, fecal-smelling mess of fresh ambergris may end up floating in the ocean. There it matures by degrees over a period of months to years, lightening in color to gray and then white and changing in odor until it achieves a scent that is, by all accounts, distinctive and hard to describe yet not unpleasant. Eventually, the ambergris might be washed up on a beach almost anywhere, found, and collected. Prized, at various times, as a perfume ingredient, a medicine, or a spice in gourmet recipes, its value can rival that of gold.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Fine white ambergris.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_296b_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: CHRISTOPHER KEMP</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Given that convoluted process, it may not be surprising that the exact origin of ambergris was contentious well into the 20th century. The recent, somewhat tentative resolution of an old mystery sets the tone of the book, which manages to be both historical and immediate. Kemp intersperses historical notes related to ambergris, scientific findings on its production and its properties, accounts of correspondence and meetings with ambergris experts, and finally journal-like accounts of his compulsion to search local beaches for his own piece of treasure.</p>
<p>The author presents tantalizing descriptions of his research to discover everything there is to know about ambergris and enticing reports of his conversations with the often guarded, sometimes eccentric people who make a living as ambergris hunters or dealers. He manages to convey the ambiguities and peculiarities that arise when building a livelihood on a rare, practically impossible-to-synthesize natural substance whose existence depends on the misfortunes of a sick whale and the vagaries of a long aging process.</p>
<p>One recurring theme is wonder at the mystery and improbability of ambergris production and consumption&#x2014;from the belly of a deep-diving whale, via ocean winds and currents, to the hands of an elite and secretive buyer. I understand that it's in such a spirit that Kemp often emphasizes how little is known about what sperm whales do during their deep dives. Even so, I felt some disappointment at the relatively little attention he gives to recent findings on the natural history of sperm whales.</p>
<p>That aside, I admit that I now find it hard to walk a beach without keeping an eye out for objects with strong, strange-but-not-unpleasant scents. I'm definitely waiting for a chance to smell the singular scent of ambergris (assuming that the stuff a Moroccan tour guide wanted to sell me was phony), although reading Kemp's fantastic description of his own attempts to eat ambergris was much more satisfying that trying the experiment myself. In other words, <italic>Floating Gold</italic> offers an enticing initiation into the shadowy and intriguing history of ambergris.</p>
</body>
</article>