<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="other" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>New Products</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Products &amp; Materials</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>products</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>New Products</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>20</day><month>07</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage seq="a">365</fpage>
<lpage>365</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>A weekly roundup of information on newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of potential interest to researchers.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary">
<p>A weekly roundup of information on newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of potential interest to researchers.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>RNA QUANTITATION </title>
<fig id="F1" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="337_365a_F1"><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text></graphic></fig>
<p>The One-Step RT-ddPCR kit for probes provides researchers with the ability to measure target RNA molecules with precision and sensitivity for applications such as gene expression analysis, miRNA analysis, and viral load quantitation. The One-Step RT-ddPCR kit creates a new paradigm for the precise quantitation of RNA by combining reverse transcription with Droplet Digital PCR (ddPCR). Researchers can use the One-Step RT-ddPCR Kit for probes with Bio-Rad's QX100 Droplet Digital PCR system to determine small differences in copy number of target RNA that they were previously unable to measure using real-time polymerase chain reaction (qPCR). In combination with the QX100 ddPCR system, the One-Step RT-ddPCR Kit for probes allows scientists to enrich for rare target RNA sequences, detect small differences in gene expression levels, and determine copies of an RNA molecule without a standard curve. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Bio-Rad</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-424-6723   </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bio-rad.com">www.bio-rad.com   </ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>CHROMATIN IMMUNOPRECIPITATION KIT</title>
<p>The Magna ChIP HT96 kit is designed for high throughput chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP). Using the kit, ChIP can be performed on up to 96 samples in a single experiment using as few as 10,000 cells per well. The optimized protocol uses a single, proprietary buffer for sonication, immunoprecipitation, and washing, which yields excellent sensitivity and lower backgrounds than conventional ChIP methods. The Magna ChIP HT96 protocol has been designed and optimized for efficient immunoprecipitation and recovery of DNA. Consequently, in many cases, a separate DNA purification step is not required for downstream analysis. The Magna ChIP HT96 kits utilize a magnetic protein A/G bead blend that provides multiple advantages over single-bead approaches. In contrast to kits with either protein A or protein G, the Magna ChIP A/G beads allow affinity capture of a broader range of antibody isotypes. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>EMD Millipore</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-645-5476      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.millipore.com/epigenetics">www.millipore.com/epigenetics</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>NUCLEIC ACID STAIN</title>
<p>The LabSafe<sup> </sup>Nucleic Acid Stain is a new and safe nucleic acid stain for the visualization of double-stranded DNA, single-stranded DNA, and RNA in agarose gels. The dyes are developed to replace toxic ethidium bromide (a potent mutagen), commonly used in gel electrophoresis for visualization of nucleic acids in agarose gels. LabSafe<sup> </sup>Nucleic Acid Stain is noncarcinogenic by the Ames test. The results are negative in both the mouse marrow chromophilous erythrocyte micronucleus and mouse primary spermatocyte chromosomal aberration tests. LabSafe<sup> </sup>Nucleic Acid Stain emits green fluorescence when bound to dsDNA and red fluorescence when bound to ssDNA or RNA. It has two excitation wavelength peaks when bound to nucleic acid, at 290 nm and 490 nm.</p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>G-Biosciences</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 314-991-6034      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbiosciences.com">www.gbiosciences.com</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>WHOLE GENOME AMPLIFICATION KIT</title>
<p>The Ampli1 Whole Genome Amplification Kit has been uniquely designed to optimize whole gene amplification of the DNA from a single cell. This new method combines all the amplification steps into single-tube protocol to avoid template loss. DNA released from the single cell is amplified with a single primer generating a library of highly concentrated DNA fragments which represent the complete genome. The DNA fragments can be employed for further targeted genetic research analysis including sequencing, microsatellite analysis, SNPs detection, or copy number variation analysis. The Ampli1 WGA Kit also supports the DNA amplification of samples containing higher numbers of cells. Although the best results are obtained with DNA from live cells, good results have also been obtained with single fixed or fixed and permeabilized cell samples such as paraformaldehyde fixed or cells stained with fluorophore conjugated antibodies.</p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Silicon Biosystems</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: +39-051-4071300    </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.siliconbiosystems.com/ampli.page">www.siliconbiosystems.com/ampli.page</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>MULTIPLEX GENE EXPRESSION ANALYSIS</title>
<p>TRAC (Transcript Analysis with the aid of Affinity Capture) is a new approach for measuring gene expression offering several benefits over real-time polymerase chain reaction (qPCR), including higher sample throughput, increased assay speed, and reduced technical variation. The method can reliably analyze the expression of up to 30 transcripts per sample using 96 well plates and avoids the need for RNA extraction, cDNA conversion, and amplification&#x2014;making it fast, simple, accurate, and cost-effective. While the technology can be used to measure any known gene sequence, several predesigned detection panels are offered, including the recently updated Human ADME-Tox library. This includes validated probes for members of the Cytochrome P450 family of genes, used to investigate in vitro drug interactions during preclinical studies. TRAC also has a wide range of research and process optimization applications and can be easily set up in a user's laboratory, or utilized via the FAST TRAC outsourced service.</p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Plexpress</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: +358-50-313-9427      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plexpress.com">www.plexpress.com</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="product-submission-instructions"><p>Electronically submit your new product description or product literature information! Go to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/products/newproducts.dtl">www.sciencemag.org/products/newproducts.dtl</ext-link> for more information.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="disclaimer"><p><italic>Newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of interest to researchers in all disciplines in academic, industrial, and governmental organizations are featured in this space. Emphasis is given to purpose, chief characteristics, and availabilty of products and materials. Endorsement by </italic>Science<italic> or AAAS of any products or materials mentioned is not implied. Additional information may be obtained from the manufacturer or supplier.</italic></p></fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
