<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="reply" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1221690</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1221690</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Technical Response</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Technical Comments</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>t-comment</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ECOLOGY</subject><subject>TECH COMMENT</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Response to Comment on &#x201C;Illusions Promote Mating Success in Great Bowerbirds&#x201D;</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Endler</surname><given-names>John A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mielke</surname><given-names>Paul W.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>Laura A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Centre for Integrative Ecology, School of Life and Environmental Sciences, Deakin University, 75 Pigdons Road, Geelong VIC 3216, Australia.</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Statistics, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, CO 80523&#x2013;1877, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:href="john.endler@deakin.edu.au">john.endler@deakin.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>20</day><month>07</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage seq="c">292</fpage>
<lpage>292</lpage>
<history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>03</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>06</month><year>2012</year></date></history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Borgia <italic>et al</italic>. raise some questions about our recent study showing that great bowerbirds create visual illusions that are used in mate choice. We address them by providing further details about our methods and results. We also provide detailed descriptions of our geometric calculations to address their measurement and analysis questions.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sacha Vignieri</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Cynthia Howe</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Borgia <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>) questioned the validity of our recent study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>) showing that great bowerbirds&#x2019; geometric illusions promote mating success. Here, we answer all their criticisms and further substantiate our results.</p>
<p>Our predictions were about the entire pattern (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>), not width or depth independently. Borgia <italic>et al</italic>.&#x2019;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>) suggestion of separate analysis of visible width and depth (<italic>w</italic> and <italic>d</italic>) and the associated visual angles (&#x00F8;<italic><sub>w</sub></italic> and &#x00F8;<italic><sub>d</sub></italic>) is statistically invalid, and there is no contradiction in the fact that the partial regression coefficients have opposite signs. This arises because <italic>w</italic> and <italic>d</italic> are different aspects of the same object. For any object other than a sphere, as the object orientation changes, if <italic>w</italic> increases, <italic>d</italic> must decrease and vice versa (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> and supplementary materials). Because bower objects are nonspherical, and often elongated, it is very difficult for a bowerbird to make good gradients in both <italic>w</italic> and <italic>d</italic> at the same time, making it very difficult to minimize both <italic>s</italic><sub>&#x00F8;</sub><italic><sub>w</sub></italic> and <italic>s</italic><sub>&#x00F8;</sub><italic><sub>d</sub></italic>. Univariate measures simply ignore this tight relationship and also ignore the fact that there are a large number of equally good layouts with different combinations of s<sub>&#x00F8;</sub><italic><sub>w</sub></italic> and s<sub>&#x00F8;d</sub> [figure 3 in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>)]. The prediction planes are tilted, yielding partial regression coefficients of opposite signs because on average the birds attend more to the effects of <italic>d</italic> than <italic>w</italic> and the two effects are strongly negatively related.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption>
<p>Relationship between visual angles &#x00F8;<italic><sub>w</sub></italic> and &#x00F8;<italic><sub>d</sub></italic> (degrees) of circular (dot) or elliptical (lines) court objects with various aspect ratios (length/width, numbers along bottom), rotated from parallel to perpendicular to the avenue-object axis, and seen from typical natural height and distance. For reference, the Sun subtends about 0.5 degrees. See the supplementary materials for details and effects of other sizes and distances.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_292c_F1"></graphic></fig>
<p>Distinguishing the noncolored (gesso) and colored objects is fully justified. Color and luminance are processed separately by the retina and brain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). In several thousand hours of video recordings in several localities, about 3.5% of the objects picked up by males and waved at female were gesso. Including all objects in the analysis had no effect on any results.</p>
<p>Vertical photographs are excellent for reconstructing visual angles (&#x00F8;). Females view the court from a height of ~30 cm and a distance of 30 to 80 cm, and this was included in our analysis. At this natural viewing height and distance, the hiding effects are very small. The size gradients reduce the effect even more because larger objects are behind smaller objects. Hiding does not affect the rank differences among bowers, and there is no significant effect of recalculating for all objects, even unrealistically assuming that all are spherical. (See the supplementary materials for details.)</p>
<p>Our mating assessment is accurate because direct measurement of mating success (number of matings) is always more accurate than related measures such as the proportion of successful courtships. The recording time used in our analysis was the time that cameras were primed to record, not the time that the cameras were triggered and actually recording. Our cameras were constantly primed to record during daylight hours, and we adjusted camera triggering by setting the region of interest, the minimum pixel change per frame, and frame changes for that region. Only movement within the avenue triggered recording, and false triggers were very rare. Our cameras did not &#x201C;malfunction&#x201D; as Borgia <italic>et al</italic>. suggested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Each bower had periods where cameras were not recording due to battery discharge, but these interruptions were randomly distributed over the whole 2.5-month mating period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). We calculated mating rate as the number of matings observed during the time a camera was ready to record, and found no relationship between this measure and the number of matings (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.10, df = 18, <italic>P</italic> = 0.68). We disagree that male courtship success is a more reliable measure of male attractiveness compared with direct mating measures, and it does not take into account the duration of courtships. We found that courtship duration and mating success were correlated, whether courtship duration included the entire time a female was near the avenue (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.61, df = 18, <italic>P</italic> = 0.004) or whether it only included the time that a female was within the avenue (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.59, df = 18, <italic>P</italic> = 0.006). We found no relationship between the number of matings per minute of courtship and recording time (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.06, df = 18, <italic>P</italic> = 0.27).</p>
<p>Exclusion of bowers had nothing to do with the time females gazed at the court. We restricted our analysis to males that obtained one or more matings. This excluded earlier choice criteria and ensured that females were recorded (sexual dimorphism is negligible in this species, and young males frequently spend time in bower avenues). Mating refusals can result from many courtship and bower traits that are assessed before forced perspective comes into play. It is invalid to assume that criteria used early in a courtship sequence are necessarily correlated with criteria used later (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). We explored the conditional probability of mating given that a proven female was in the bower. There are many failures before that, but they are irrelevant to this question (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>We tested the hypothesis that gradients might result if males put larger objects away from where they stand during the displays to avoid uneven footing. If true, then the objects would show steps, jumping to larger sizes where the male does not stand. For each court, we fitted a linear, quadratic, cubic, and sigmoid regression (generalized linear) model to the data and asked which model fit the data with the least error. The quadratic indicates whether object size increases in a faster-than-linear relationship as distance increases; some bowers have very large bones near the outer court edge. The cubic is sensitive to steps, but past the steps it turns toward the mean, so would be sensitive to very large objects in the outer court with smaller ones beyond and vice versa. The sigmoid fits simulated data with steps much better than the cubic. We tested both courts of 44 bowers in 2 years [typical data in figure S4 of (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>)]. In 2009, all fit the linear model. In 2010, 96% fit the linear and 4% the cubic. The 4% fit to the cubic is either type I error or arises from a few large bones toward the end of the court, with smaller objects behind them. Therefore, stable footing is unlikely to explain the presence of object gradients in this population.</p>
<p>We considered courtship traits that are important to great bowerbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>), not traits that are important in all other species. Different bowerbird species are known to produce different sexual displays; for example, Borgia <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>) cite vocal mimicry, which is not part of the sexual display in great bowerbirds. Furthermore, different bowerbird species use different mate choice criteria. For example, object count predicts male mating success in some species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref><italic>&#x2013;</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>) but not in others, including ours (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13"><italic>13</italic></xref>), and we also found no effect of decoration count on mating success (<italic>P</italic> &gt;&gt; 0.05). Moreover, female preferences even differ among populations of spotted bowerbirds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>), so factors that are important in mate choice are highly variable within and among bowerbird species. It is invalid to assume that all populations or species assess mates in the same way.</p>
</body>
<back><app-group><app>
<title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/337/6092/292-c/DC1">www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/337/6092/292-c/DC1</ext-link></p>
<p>Supplementary Text</p>
<p>Figs. S1 to S5</p>
<p>References (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17"><italic>17</italic></xref>)</p></supplementary-material></app></app-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borgia</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyle</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keagy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Comment on &#x201C;Illusions promote mating success in great bowerbirds&#x201D;</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>337</volume>, 
<fpage>292</fpage> (<year>2012</year>); <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/337/6092/292-b">www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/337/6092/292-b</ext-link></citation></ref>
<ref id="R2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Endler</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Illusions promote mating success in great bowerbirds</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>335</volume>, 
<fpage>335</fpage> (<year>2012</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1212443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22267812</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endler</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mielke</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Comparing entire colour patterns as birds see them</article-title>. <source>Biol. J. Linn. Soc. Lond.</source> 
<volume>86</volume>, 
<fpage>405</fpage> (<year>2005</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1095-8312.2005.00540.x</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endler</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Natural and sexual selection on color patterns in poeciliid fishes</article-title>. <source>Environ. Biol. Fishes</source> 
<volume>9</volume>, 
<fpage>173</fpage> (<year>1983</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00690861</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Genner</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haesler</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Sequential female assessment drives complex sexual selection on bower shape in a cichlid fish</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> 
<volume>64</volume>, 
<fpage>2246</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20199564</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levav</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Partition-edit-count: Naive extensional reasoning in judgment of conditional probability</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Psychol. Gen.</source> 
<volume>133</volume>, 
<fpage>626</fpage> (<year>2004</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0096-3445.133.4.626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15584810</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endler</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Endler</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doerr</surname><given-names>N. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Great bowerbirds create theaters with forced perspective when seen by their audience</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source> 
<volume>20</volume>, 
<fpage>1679</fpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2010.08.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20832314</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="book">C. B. Frith, D. W. Frith, <italic>The Bowerbirds</italic> (Oxford Univ. Press, Oxford, 2004).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borgia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Complex male display and female choice in the spotted bowerbird: Specialized functions for different bower decorations</article-title>. <source>Anim. Behav.</source> 
<volume>49</volume>, 
<fpage>1291</fpage> (<year>1995</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/anbe.1995.0161</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uy</surname><given-names>J. A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borgia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Sexual selection drives rapid divergence in bowerbird display traits</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> 
<volume>54</volume>, 
<fpage>273</fpage> (<year>2000</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10937203</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Behav. Ecol. Sociobiol.</source> 
<volume>53</volume>, 
<fpage>269</fpage> (<year>2003</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenz</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Mating-behavior and sexual competition in the regent bowerbird <italic>Sericulus chrysocephalus</italic></article-title>. <source>Emu</source> 
<volume>94</volume>, 
<fpage>263</fpage> (<year>1994</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/MU9940263</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katsuno</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okida</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>J. Yamashina Inst. Ornithol.</source> 
<volume>42</volume>, 
<fpage>19</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Interpopulation differences exhibited by spotted bowerbirds <italic>Chlamydera</italic> <italic>maculata</italic> across a suite of male traits and female preferences</article-title>. <source>Ibis</source> 
<volume>148</volume>, 
<fpage>425</fpage> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1474-919X.2006.00540.x</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiltie</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Scaling of visual acuity with body size in mammals and birds</article-title>. <source>Funct. Ecol.</source> 
<volume>14</volume>, 
<fpage>226</fpage> (<year>2000</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2435.2000.00404.x</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaffney</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodos</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The visual acuity and refractive state of the American kestrel (<italic>Falco sparverius</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Vision Res.</source> 
<volume>43</volume>, 
<fpage>2053</fpage> (<year>2003</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0042-6989(03)00304-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12842158</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curcio</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalina</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendrickson</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Human photoreceptor topography</article-title>. <source>J. Comp. Neurol.</source> 
<volume>292</volume>, 
<fpage>497</fpage> (<year>1990</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.902920402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2324310</pub-id></citation></ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>