<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI POLICY</subject><subject>SCI COMMUN</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Random Sample</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>20</day>
<month>07</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6092</issue>
<fpage seq="a">275</fpage>
<lpage>276</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>On 21 July, Les Horribles Cernettes&#x2014;CERN's favorite 1960s-style girl group, which has been serenading Geneva-based physicists with songs such as &#x22;Strong Interaction,&#x22; &#x22;Antiworld,&#x22; &#x22;Mr. Higgs,&#x22; and &#x22;Collider&#x22; for 22 years&#x2014;will give their last performance at the CERN Hadronic Festival. And this week's numbers quantify lemur species that are listed as critically endangered, endangered, or vulnerable and plankton taxa.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>On 21 July, Les Horribles Cernettes&#x2014;CERN's favorite 1960s-style girl group, which has been serenading Geneva-based physicists with songs such as &#x22;Strong Interaction,&#x22; &#x22;Antiworld,&#x22; &#x22;Mr. Higgs,&#x22; and &#x22;Collider&#x22; for 22 years&#x2014;will give their last performance at the CERN Hadronic Festival. And this week's numbers quantify lemur species that are listed as critically endangered, endangered, or vulnerable and plankton taxa.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec>
<title>They Said It</title>
<p>&#x201C;I can&apos;t find anyone in my peer group who believes in BioWatch. &#x2026; The only times it goes off, it&apos;s wrong. I just think it&apos;s a colossal waste of money. It&apos;s a stupid program.&#x201D;</p>
<p>&#x2014;Ned Calonge, former chief medical officer for the Colorado Department of Public Health and Environment, to <italic>The Los Angeles Times</italic> on 7 July about the Department of Homeland Security&apos;s efforts to equip cities with devices to detect a biological terrorist attack.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Swan Song for the Cernettes</title>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_275a_F2"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: SILVANO DE GENNARO (2)</attrib>
</fig>
<p>A woman in a puffy pink prom dress croons plaintively; three backup singers with beehive hairstyles sway and sing. Behind them all, a familiar giant particle accelerator curves away into the distance.</p>
<p>&#x201C;You never spend your nights with me. &#x2026; You only love your collider.&#x201D;</p>
<p><italic>&#x201C;Ooooh &#x2026; wop wop.&#x201D;</italic></p>
<p>For 22 years, Les Horribles Cernettes&#x2014;CERN&apos;s favorite 1960s-style girl group&#x2014;have been serenading Geneva-based physicists with songs such as &#x201C;Strong Interaction,&#x201D; &#x201C;Antiworld,&#x201D; &#x201C;Mr. Higgs,&#x201D; and the aforementioned &#x201C;Collider,&#x201D; all written by the band&apos;s creator, manager, composer, and keyboardist/bassist, Silvano de Gennaro. But on 21 July, the Cernettes&apos; era will come to an end, with one last performance at the CERN Hadronic Festival. (The show will be available on YouTube, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/user/cernettes">http://www.youtube.com/user/cernettes</ext-link>).</p>
<p>It all started in 1990, when a CERN secretary&#x2014;tired of feeling neglected by her always-on-shift physicist boyfriend&#x2014;asked de Gennaro (then a CERN computer scientist and former musician) to turn her tale of woe into a song. De Gennaro says he opted for doo-wop &#x201C;because the average age at CERN was mid-50s.&#x201D; He assembled singers and a band to perform the song, and the Cernettes were born.</p>
<p>Over the years, about a dozen different singers have been in the group&#x2014;CERN secretaries and interns, and outside talent from Geneva&apos;s operatic society. &#x201C;We never played for money,&#x201D; de Gennaro says. &#x201C;We played to get the physicists to smile and dance.&#x201D;</p>
<p>But now de Gennaro is retiring, so the act must disband. Ironically, the Cernettes went briefly viral last week, when news outlets reported that a 1992 still of the group was the first photo ever uploaded to the World Wide Web. De Gennaro demurs: When the photo was posted to CERN&apos;s Web site, &#x201C;they told me that this was the first photo <italic>of a band</italic> that appeared on the Web,&#x201D; he says. &#x201C;Somehow, this got twisted.&#x201D;</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>By The Numbers</title>
<p><bold>1.5 million</bold> &#x2014; Number of different plankton taxa in the oceans according to a preliminary analysis of 27,000 samples collected by Tara Oceans, a scientific sailing expedition, from the Mediterranean Sea and the Red Sea to the Pacific Ocean and the Antarctic region.</p>
<p><bold>91</bold> &#x2014; Percentage of the world&apos;s 103 lemur species that are listed as critically endangered, endangered, or vulnerable by the International Union for Conservation of Nature.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title><italic>Science</italic>LIVE</title>
<p>Join us on Thursday, 26 July, at 3 p.m. EDT for a live chat with leading experts on a hot topic in science. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scim.ag/science-live"><bold>http://scim.ag/science-live</bold></ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>