<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">sigtrans</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science Signaling</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Sci. Signal.</abbrev-journal-title>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1937-9145</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">1945-0877</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2002720</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scisignal.2002720</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>STKE Research Articles</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>BIOCHEM</subject><subject>NEUROSCIENCE</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Biochemistry</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Sequential Inter- and Intrasubunit Rearrangements During Activation of Dimeric Metabotropic Glutamate Receptor 1</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hlavackova</surname><given-names>Veronika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zabel</surname><given-names>Ulrike</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Frankova</surname><given-names>Daniela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x00E4;tz</surname><given-names>Julia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>Carsten</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prezeau</surname><given-names>Laurent</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>Jean-Philippe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1">*</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x2020;</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Blahos</surname><given-names>Jaroslav</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1">*</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x2020;</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>Martin J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1">*</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x2020;</sup></xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, University of W&#x00FC;rzburg, 97078 W&#x00FC;rzburg, Germany.</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Rudolf Virchow Center, University of W&#x00FC;rzburg, 97078 W&#x00FC;rzburg, Germany.</aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Pharmacology, Institute of Molecular Genetics, Czech Academy of Science, 142 20 Prague 4, Czech Republic.</aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>University of Montpellier 1 &amp; 2, CNRS UMR5203, Institut de G&#x00E9;nomique Fonctionnelle, Montpellier F-34094, France.</aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>INSERM U661, Montpellier F-34094, France.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn id="afn1"><label>*</label>
<p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x2020;</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:href="lohse@toxi.uni-wuerzburg.de">lohse@toxi.uni-wuerzburg.de</email> (M.J.L.); <email xlink:href="blahos@img.cas.cz">blahos@img.cas.cz</email> (J.B.); <email xlink:href="Jean-Philippe.Pin@igf.cnrs.fr">Jean-Philippe.Pin@igf.cnrs.fr</email> (J.-P.P.)</corresp></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>14</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>237</issue>
<fpage>ra59</fpage>
<lpage>ra59</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>07</month><year>2012</year></date></history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>Both subunits in the metabotropic glutamate receptor 1 dimer move relative to each other before one adopts an active conformation.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="editor">
<title>Visualizing Activation of a GPCR</title>
<p>Activation and signaling by G protein&#x2013;coupled receptors (GPCRs), which can function as monomers or dimers, occur through conformational changes. Hlavackova <italic>et al</italic>. introduced fluorescent proteins and epitope tags into and engineered the C terminus of metabotropic glutamate receptor 1 (mGluR1) to produce chimeric proteins useful for the analysis of the inter- and intrasubunit conformational changes associated with activation of this dimeric GPCR. Intrasubunit rearrangements triggered a decrease in fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET) between fluorophores within the same subunit, and intersubunit rearrangements triggered an increase in FRET between fluorophores on different subunits. Kinetic analysis showed that intersubunit rearrangements occurred faster than did intrasubunit rearrangements. Furthermore, only one subunit in each dimer adopted an active conformation. Thus, for a dimeric GPCR, ligand binding first causes intersubunit movements, which are followed by an intrasubunit conformational change that puts one subunit in an active state.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract>
<p>The metabotropic glutamate receptor 1 (mGluR1), a class C member of the heterotrimeric guanine nucleotide&#x2013;binding protein (G protein)&#x2013;coupled receptor family, is a constitutive dimer that regulates excitatory neurotransmission. We investigated the role of homodimer formation in mGluR1 activation by examining activation-dependent inter- and intrasubunit conformational changes by fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET). We inserted yellow and cyan fluorescent proteins in the second intracellular loop and at the carboxyl terminus of mGluR1 to act as FRET sensors and expressed these proteins in human embryonic kidney 293 cells. Agonist-dependent activation of these mGluR1 chimeras rapidly increased the intersubunit FRET, suggesting rapid movement of the subunits relative to each other. After intersubunit movement, the intrasubunit FRET decreased, reflecting conformational changes within a subunit. Cotransfection of chimeric receptor subunits that were capable or incapable of G protein coupling revealed that only a single subunit assumes an active state in an mGluR1 receptor dimer.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Ernesto Andrianantoandro</meta-value></custom-meta>
<custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>SPI</meta-value></custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Heterotrimeric guanine nucleotide&#x2013;binding protein (G protein)&#x2013;coupled receptors (GPCRs) are major players in cellular communication and comprise receptors for various stimuli, such as light, taste, and many small molecule neurotransmitters, as well as small peptide and large protein hormones. Whereas most other classes of cell surface receptors function as dimers, many GPCRs act as monomers. Monomeric GPCRs, notably the light receptor rhodopsin, as well as the &#x03B2;<sub>2</sub>-adrenergic and &#x03BC;-opiate receptors, can fully activate their effector G proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>). However, many GPCRs can also exist and function as dimers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>). Evidence for multimeric GPCRs is based on findings of physical association in recombinant, as well as native, systems and on functional data indicating interactions between two (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>) or more (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18"><italic>18</italic></xref>) GPCRs.</p>
<p>Some class C GPCRs, such as &#x03B3;-aminobutyric acid type B (GABA<sub>B</sub>) and metabotropic glutamate receptors (mGluRs), form constitutive dimers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19"><italic>19</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21"><italic>21</italic></xref>) and represent opportune models to decipher conformational changes in a GPCR dimer. Each subunit of a class C GPCR dimer is composed of a large N-terminal Venus flytrap domain (VFT) containing the agonist binding site, followed by a cysteine-rich domain, and then a heptahelical domain (HD). For mGluRs, mutational analyses, as well as structural and modeling data, suggested that agonist binding to the VFT induces a relative movement between the two subunits, which may be accompanied by a conformational change in the HD, leading to G protein activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22"><italic>22</italic></xref>). In the case of the GABA<sub>B</sub> receptor, one subunit (GABA<sub>B1</sub>) mediates ligand binding, and the other subunit (GABA<sub>B2</sub>) couples to G proteins. Only the heterodimer comprising both GABA<sub>B1</sub> and GABA<sub>B2</sub> (GABA<sub>B1/B2</sub>) triggers full transmembrane signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23"><italic>23</italic></xref>). The distinct functional deficits of each of the two subunits may explain why some class C GPCRs form obligatory dimers, but they also raise a number of important issues concerning their mechanisms of activation.</p>
<p>It is unclear whether activation involves a conformational change in the HDs or whether G protein activation results only from the movement of the subunits relative to each other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24"><italic>24</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25"><italic>25</italic></xref>). If a conformational change in the HD is relevant for receptor activation, it is unknown whether this conformational change occurs on the same time scale (~50 ms) as in the case of class A GPCRs, for which agonists bind directly to the HD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26"><italic>26</italic></xref>). It is also unclear whether conformational changes occur in the HDs in both subunits of the dimer and, if so, whether both conformational changes are necessary for G protein activation. In earlier studies, we provided evidence for G protein coupling after conformational change in a single HD in the mGluR dimer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>). Here, we directly examined the conformational changes in the HD and investigated how the kinetics of such conformational changes relates to the kinetics of other processes involved in class C GPCR activation.</p>
<p>Fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET) technologies are useful in studying conformational changes of proteins and protein-protein interactions in living cells. Fusion of fluorophores, such as cyan fluorescent protein (CFP) and yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29"><italic>29</italic></xref>), or the small yellow label fluorescein arsenical hairpin binder (FlAsH) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30"><italic>30</italic></xref>) at different positions in the intracellular loops and C-terminal tail of a receptor allowed for measurement of FRET between different regions of the protein (intramolecular conformational changes). FRET measurements enabled the determination of the kinetic parameters of activation for the receptors studied. Activation time constants ranged from ~40 to 100 ms for the &#x03B1;<sub>2A</sub>-, &#x03B2;<sub>1</sub>-, and &#x03B2;<sub>2</sub>-adrenergic receptors; adenosine A<sub>2A</sub> receptor; and various muscarinic receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31"><italic>31</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36"><italic>36</italic></xref>) to ~1 s for the class B parathyroid hormone receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35"><italic>35</italic></xref>). Tagging GPCRs and downstream signaling proteins with fluorescent proteins allowed the temporal and spatial resolution of signaling patterns of several GPCRs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37"><italic>37</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41"><italic>41</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>FRET techniques have been used to study intermolecular events in dimeric GPCRs by placing a single fluorophore in each subunit of a GPCR dimer. For mGluR1&#x03B1; receptors, Tateyama <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25"><italic>25</italic></xref>) showed an agonist-dependent increase in FRET between the second intracellular (i2) loops of the HDs and a decrease between the first intracellular loops of the HDs within several seconds after adding agonists. A similar study on mGluR1&#x03B2; receptors (a C-terminally shortened splice variant of mGluR1) reported only small increases in FRET between the i2 loops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42"><italic>42</italic></xref>). However, no intramolecular conformational changes were observed in either of these FRET studies. These studies suggested that, unlike the class A GPCRs in which intramolecular conformational changes in the HD represent the activation mechanism, the dimeric class C GPCRs might be primarily activated by intermolecular movements of the two subunits relative to each other.</p>
<p>These findings led us to investigate and compare inter- versus intramolecular activation-dependent changes in fluorescently labeled mGluR1 receptors. We created sensors for each process by placing CFP and YFP at suitable positions within the mGluR1 receptor subunit and used these to analyze the sequence of events during dimer activation and the crosstalk between the two subunits.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="results" disp-level="1">
<title>Results</title>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Tools for studying activation of the mGlu1 receptor</title>
<p>To study the intermolecular activation kinetics of mGlu1 receptors, we generated a number of sensors by fusing the CFP or the YFP to one of two sites in the receptor: either inserted into the i2 loop, between Ile<sup>685</sup> and Leu<sup>686</sup>, or added at the C terminus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> and table S1). To generate sensors for studying intramolecular activation kinetics, we fused both YFP and CFP to the receptor, one at each site. We also added N-terminal hemagglutinin (HA) or myc epitope tags to the receptors. To control the subunit composition of mGluR1 dimers, we used the C-terminal &#x201C;quality control system&#x201D; of the GABA<sub>B</sub> receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43"><italic>43</italic></xref>). We replaced the C termini of the mGluR1 subunits with either the last 87 C-terminal amino acids of GABA<sub>B1</sub> (c1) or the first 62 amino acids of the C-terminal tail of GABA<sub>B1</sub> (c1sh), or the last 181 C-terminal amino acids of GABA<sub>B2</sub> (c2) or the first 61 amino acids of the C-terminal tail of GABA<sub>B2</sub> (c2sh), such that only heterodimers containing two different longer C-terminal tails (a c1 version and a c2 version) reached the cell surface (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43"><italic>43</italic></xref>). The A-sensor and A-sensor-C/E, which have the short C-terminal tails, reached the cell surface. All receptor constructs used in this study and their key properties are summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption>
<p>Schematic representation and overview of the mGluR1 constructs used in this study. HA (or myc) epitopes for antibody recognition were inserted at the beginning of the VFT domain. The C terminus was replaced with that of the GABA<sub>B1</sub> receptor, resulting in an 87&#x2013; or 62&#x2013;amino acid C terminus derived from the GABA<sub>B1</sub> receptor (c1 and c1sh); the corresponding C termini derived from the GABA<sub>B2</sub> receptor comprised 181 amino acid (c2) or 61 amino acid (c2sh), respectively. Fluorescent proteins&#x2014;enhanced CFP (eCFP) and enhanced YFP (eYFP)&#x2014;were fused to the receptor subunits either at the altered C terminus or by insertion into the i2 loop, or both. See table S1 for the fusion sites. Color codes denote the parent sequences: black, mGlu1 receptor; dark red, GABA<sub>B1</sub> receptor; cyan, eCFP; yellow, eYFP; and white, HA epitope tag. ER, endoplasmic reticulum.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="5_ra59_F1"></graphic></fig>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Intersubunit sensors of the mGlu1 receptor</title>
<p>To study FRET between the two subunits in an mGluR1 dimer, we generated constructs bearing a single fluorescent protein either within the i2 loop or at the C terminus. All of these constructs, cotransfected into human embryonic kidney (HEK) 293 cells such that one was labeled with CFP and the other with YFP, reached the cell surface, as revealed by confocal microscopy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>) and by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) using antibodies recognizing the HA or the myc tags (fig. S1). In agreement with earlier observations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25"><italic>25</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30"><italic>30</italic></xref>), compared to cells expressing the unlabeled dimers, the dimers with CFP (or YFP) in the i2 loop were nonfunctional: Ca<sup>2+</sup> responses to the mGluR1 agonist quisqualate were absent for dimers containing subunits with CFP (or YFP) in the i2 loop (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). All other constructs and combinations retained some functionality. Compared to the unlabeled dimers, the recombinant receptor complexes were almost fully functional when full-length C-terminally tagged subunits were present and had about 50% functionality when one of the two subunits was tagged within the i2 loop (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption>
<p>Characterization of mGluR1 constructs for intersubunit FRET. (<bold>A</bold>) Left panels: schematic representation of the mGluR1 constructs with color codes and symbols as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>; magenta denotes GABA<sub>B2</sub> sequence. The antibody epitopes are denoted as white (HA) or gray (myc) squares. Middle and right panels: confocal images of cells expressing the indicated heterodimers. HEK cells were transfected with the indicated constructs and imaged in the CFP channel (middle panels) and the YFP channel (right panels). Scale bars in confocal images are equal to 10 &#x03BC;m. (<bold>B</bold>) Responses to 10 &#x03BC;M quisqualate of the R1c1:R1c2 heterodimer and the mGluR1 homodimer labeled with CFP in the i2 loop (R1i2CFP). Values are normalized to the ELISA signal (a measure of relative abundance) and are means &#x00B1; SEM of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> signal divided by the ELISA signal of <italic>n</italic> = 3 independent experiments performed in triplicate. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 versus unlabeled, paired-sample <italic>t</italic> test. (<bold>C</bold>) Increase in Ca<sup>2+</sup> release induced by quisqualate in HEK cells expressing the indicated receptor subunits. Values are normalized to the quisqualate-induced maximal response obtained with heterodimeric unlabeled receptors and to the relative amount of the HA-tagged receptors based on the ELISA signal in the same transfections. Values are normalized to the ELISA signal and are means &#x00B1; SEM of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> signal divided by the ELISA signals of <italic>n</italic> = 3 to 9 independent experiments performed in triplicate. The maximal calcium response was significantly lower for R1ctCFP homodimers (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and slightly lower for R1ctYFP (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.07) compared to the unlabeled R1c1:R1c2 heterodimer (two-sample <italic>t</italic> test). For heterodimers, where one subunit carried a CFP or YFP in the i2 loop, the maximal calcium response was significantly lower (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) compared to the heterodimer where both subunits carried the label at the C terminus. The values for the Hill coefficient (<italic>h</italic>) were for all curves close to 1 (for <italic>h</italic> and 95% confidence interval values, see table S2).</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="5_ra59_F2"></graphic></fig>
<p>Basal FRET between the fluorophores in these dimeric constructs was determined by acceptor photobleaching and the resultant donor dequenching (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). From the increase in CFP (donor) emission after bleaching YFP with prolonged excitation at 500 nm, we calculated the following FRET efficiencies for sensors containing subunits in the indicated combinations: 4.0 &#x00B1; 0.7% for R1i2CFP:R1ctYFP, 10.0 &#x00B1; 2.4% for R1ctCFP:R1i2YFP, and 16.0 &#x00B1; 2.0% for R1ctCFP:R1ctYFP.</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption>
<p>Intersubunit FRET measured with mGluR1 constructs carrying single CFP or YFP labels. (<bold>A</bold>) Determination of basal FRET between two different mGluR1 constructs labeled either at the C terminus or within the i2 loop. FRET was determined by donor dequenching after acceptor photobleaching. Shown is a representative trace from a cell expressing R1ctCFP and R1i2YFP, transfected at a ratio of 1:3. CFP and YFP fluorescence were initially measured using excitation (exc.) at 436 nm. This was followed by acceptor bleaching (pb.) at 500 nm for ~70 s, then another measurement of CFP and YFP fluorescence using excitation at 436 nm. (<bold>B</bold>) Agonist-induced changes in FRET between singly labeled mGluR1 constructs. Shown are changes in FRET (%) induced by 100 &#x03BC;M quisqualate in HEK cells expressing the various combinations of subunits as indicated. The color code in the schematic representation corresponds to that used in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. Data are means &#x00B1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 21 to 81 independent experiments; *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 versus E-sensor, two-sample <italic>t</italic> test). (<bold>C</bold>) Representative trace of agonist-induced change in CFP (cyan) and YFP (yellow) emission (top) and normalized FRET ratio (bottom) in HEK cells transiently expressing the E-sensor. Application of 100 &#x03BC;M quisqualate (Quis) is indicated. (<bold>D</bold>) Dose-response curve of quisqualate activation measured in cells transiently expressing the E-sensor. The FRET changes were measured 24 hours after transfection. The concentration-response curve was derived from individual traces, where the change in FRET for each concentration was normalized to the FRET change caused by 100 &#x03BC;M quisqualate. Data are means &#x00B1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 18 independent experiments; SEM not shown when smaller than symbol size; Hill coefficient, <italic>h</italic> = 0.82 &#x00B1; 0.06; for 95% confidence interval values, see table S2).</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="5_ra59_F3"></graphic></fig>
<p>The addition of agonists to dimers of the various subunit combinations produced major changes in FRET only when two constructs labeled in the i2 loop were co-expressed, such as R1i2CFP:R1i2YFP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). The FRET ratio increased by an average of 8.1 &#x00B1; 0.4% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), with dimers of this combination, and some cells showed an increase of greater than 20%. This increase in FRET occurred rapidly, was characterized by symmetrical changes in the donor and acceptor emissions, and was fully reversible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). The concentration-response curve for the agonist quisqualate gave an EC<sub>50</sub> (median effective concentration) value of 1.05 &#x03BC;M (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>), which is compatible with mGluR1 pharmacology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44"><italic>44</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45"><italic>45</italic></xref>). The increase in FRET between fluorescent proteins placed in the intracellular loops of the subunits is compatible with the assumed activation mechanism of class C receptors that involves a rearrangement of the two subunits within the receptor dimer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46"><italic>46</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48"><italic>48</italic></xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<p>Dynamic FRET changes in response to agonist (100 &#x03BC;M quisqualate; %).</p>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides">
<col width="%"/>
<col width="%"/>
<col width="%"/>
<col width="%"/>
<thead>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="col"><bold>Receptor composition</bold></td>
<td valign="top" align="center" scope="col"><bold><italic>A</italic> (%)</bold></td>
<td valign="top" align="center" scope="col"><bold>SEM</bold></td>
<td valign="top" align="center" scope="col"><bold><italic>n</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">Transient expression</td>
<td valign="top"></td>
<td valign="top"></td>
<td valign="top"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">E-sensor</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">+8.1</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.4</td>
<td valign="top" align="center">88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">R1ctCFP:R1ctYFP</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.0</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.0</td>
<td valign="top" align="center">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">R1ctCFP:R1i2YFP</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.0</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.0</td>
<td valign="top" align="center">30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">R1i2CFP:R1ctYFP</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.4</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.1</td>
<td valign="top" align="center">33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">A-sensor</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">&#x2212;6.2</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.2</td>
<td valign="top" align="center">66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">A-sensor-C/E</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.0</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.0</td>
<td valign="top" align="center">26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">A-sensor:R1i2YFP</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">&#x2212;6.2</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.3</td>
<td valign="top" align="center">43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">A-sensor:R1ctYFP</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">&#x2212;0.4</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.1</td>
<td valign="top" align="center">29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">A-sensor:R1ctYFP-C/E</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.6</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.2</td>
<td valign="top" align="center">52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">Stable expression (Flp-In)</td>
<td valign="top" align="center"></td>
<td valign="top" align="center"></td>
<td valign="top" align="center"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">A-sensor</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">&#x2212;7.4</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.4</td>
<td valign="top" align="center">33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left" scope="row">A-sensor:R1c2sh</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">&#x2212;0.4</td>
<td valign="top" align="char" char=".">0.1</td>
<td valign="top" align="center">66</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table></table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Intrasubunit sensor of mGluR1</title>
<p>To investigate potential HD conformational changes, we generated several constructs analogous to previously reported class A GPCR sensors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40"><italic>40</italic></xref>) by placing fluorophores both at the C terminus and within the intracellular loops of a single mGluR1 dimer subunit. An optimized mGluR1 subunit construct, termed the &#x201C;A-sensor,&#x201D; which was tagged with YFP in the i2 loop and with CFP 10 amino acids downstream of the C-terminal retention RSRR motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> and table S1), showed robust agonist-induced changes in FRET (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). This A-sensor homodimer was present at the cell surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>) and produced agonist-induced reductions in FRET, ranging from 6 to 15%, depending on abundance of chimeric receptor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="F4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption>
<p>Intrasubunit FRET measured with an mGluR1 construct carrying two labels on the same subunit (A-sensor). (<bold>A</bold>) Top: schematic representation of the mGluR1 construct with color codes as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>. Middle and bottom: confocal images of the A-sensor transiently expressed in HEK cells viewed in the CFP channel (middle) and the YFP channel (right). Scale bar, 10 &#x03BC;m. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative traces of agonist-induced change in CFP (cyan) or YFP (yellow) emission (above) and normalized FRET ratio (below) in cells transiently expressing the A-sensor. Application of the various agonists is indicated. Glu, glutamate. (<bold>C</bold>) Dose-response curves of agonist-induced changes in FRET of the A-sensor. Quisqualate- or glutamate-induced changes in FRET were recorded in response to various agonist concentrations. The dose-response curves were derived from individual traces for which FRET change at every concentration was normalized to FRET change at 100 &#x03BC;M quisqualate. Data are means &#x00B1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 9 to 16 independent experiments; SEM not shown when smaller than symbol size; <italic>h</italic><sub>Quis</sub> = 0.77 &#x00B1; 0.08, <italic>h</italic><sub>Glu</sub> = 0.74 &#x00B1; 0.11; for the 95% confidence interval values, see table S2). (<bold>D</bold>) Pharmacological modulation of the quisqualate-induced FRET ratio change in the A-sensor. Compounds were applied first alone [AIDA, 100 &#x03BC;M; 4C3HPG (4C3), 1 mM] or in addition to 100 &#x03BC;M quisqualate. Buffer indicates buffer used for AIDA (buffer plus 10 &#x03BC;M NaOH coming from AIDA stock solution).</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="5_ra59_F4"></graphic></fig>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Pharmacological characterization of the intrasubunit mGluR1 sensor (A-sensor)</title>
<p>Various mGluR1 agonists&#x2014;quisqualate, glutamate, and (<italic>S</italic>)-3,5-dihydroxyphenylglycine (DHPG)&#x2014;caused similar decreases in FRET of the A-sensor homodimer when transiently expressed in HEK cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). In agreement with earlier observations on the &#x03B1;<sub>2</sub>-adrenergic receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49"><italic>49</italic></xref>), the response to the partial agonist DHPG was slower than those of the full agonists glutamate and quisqualate. Concentration-response curves for these FRET signals yielded EC<sub>50</sub> values of 1.3 &#x03BC;M for quisqualate and 22.6 &#x03BC;M for glutamate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>), which parallels in vitro functional assays of the mGluR1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45"><italic>45</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>We demonstrated the specificity of the agonist-induced FRET ratio change using the mGluR1-specific competitive ligands AIDA [(<italic>RS</italic>)-1-aminoindan-1,5-dicarboxylic acid] and 4C3HPG [(<italic>S</italic>)-4-carboxy-3-hydroxyphenylglycine] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). There was no change in FRET when the antagonist AIDA (or its buffer) was applied alone. However, AIDA fully inhibited the quisqualate-induced decrease in FRET, thus behaving as an antagonist. 4C3HPG had a weak agonistic effect of its own and only partially inhibited the quisqualate-evoked FRET signal, indicating that 4C3HPG acts as a partial agonist for mGluR1, as already known for the mGluR5 receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44"><italic>44</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50"><italic>50</italic></xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Disruption of agonist-induced FRET signals by a C258E mutation in the A-sensor</title>
<p>To demonstrate that the FRET signals of the A-sensor homodimer depended on the transmission of signal from the VFT to the HD, we constructed a C258E mutant of the A-sensor (A-sensor-C/E) (fig. S2A). The corresponding mutation in the mGluR5 (C240E) functionally uncouples the VFT domain from the HD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51"><italic>51</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52"><italic>52</italic></xref>). This C258E mutant homodimer displayed no agonist-induced FRET decrease, unlike the A-sensor homodimer (fig. S2B), even though this mutant was present at the cell surface and its basal FRET efficiency (based on donor dequenching after acceptor photobleaching) reached 26.2 &#x00B1; 1.1% in comparison to 31.7 &#x00B1; 1.1% for the A-sensor (fig. S2, C and D). Thus, the C258E point mutation, which uncouples the VFT domain from the HD and prevents agonist-dependent receptor signaling, was sufficient to prevent the agonist-induced conformational change within the HD of the A-sensor.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Kinetics of intra- versus intersubunit conformational changes</title>
<p>The ability to record both intrasubunit (A-sensor) and intersubunit (E-sensor) changes in FRET allowed us to compare the kinetics of these two steps. This comparison was facilitated by the fact that FRET in response to the agonist increased with the E-sensor but decreased with the A-sensor homodimer, which excludes interference between the two processes in the A-sensor. We stimulated cells transfected with either the A-sensor homodimer or the E-sensor with various concentrations of quisqualate (0.001 to 3 mM) and analyzed the observed changes in FRET. Mono-exponential curves were fitted to the data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, A and B) to determine the time constants of activation.</p>
<fig id="F5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption>
<p>Kinetics of the agonist-induced changes in inter- and intramolecular mGluR1 FRET sensors. (<bold>A</bold>) Activation kinetics of the intermolecular E-sensor. Shown is a representative trace obtained with HEK cells transiently expressing the constructs R1i2CFP and R1i2YFP in response to quisqualate (3 mM), with data points obtained every 20 ms. The curve represents the best fit to the mono-exponential equation as described in Materials and Methods and yields a time constant of 27 &#x00B1; 2 ms. (<bold>B</bold>) Activation kinetics of the intramolecular A-sensor. Shown is a representative trace obtained with HEK cells transiently expressing the A-sensor construct in response to quisqualate (3 mM), with data points obtained every 20 ms. The curve represents the best fit to the mono-exponential equation as described in Materials and Methods and yields a time constant of 39 &#x00B1; 4 ms (SEM coming from the uncertainty of the curve fit). (<bold>C</bold>) Comparison of the activation kinetics of the inter- and intramolecular mGluR1 sensors. The activation rate constants for different concentrations of quisqualate (1, 10, 100, 1000, and 3000 &#x03BC;M) were determined from mono-exponential curve fits as shown in (A) and (B) for either the intramolecular A-sensor (black) or the intermolecular E-sensor (blue). Data are means &#x00B1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 10 independent experiments, measured side by side for A- and E-sensor; *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, two-sample <italic>t</italic> test). (<bold>D</bold>) Maximal activation kinetics of the inter- and intramolecular mGluR1 sensors. Data are from the same experiments as in (C), showing only stimulation by quisqualate (3 mM) at <italic>t</italic> = 0. Shown is the change in FRET ratio (&#x0394;<italic>R</italic>/<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>, % of maximum) for the A-sensor (black) or the inverse of the change in FRET ratio (&#x2212;&#x0394;<italic>R</italic>/<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>, % of maximum) for the E-sensor (blue) versus time. Data are means &#x00B1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 10 independent experiments; *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, two-sample <italic>t</italic> test).</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="5_ra59_F5"></graphic></fig>
<p>For both sensors, the rate of activation increased with increasing concentrations of quisqualate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>). At low concentrations of quisqualate, the activation rates of both sensors were similar (and presumably controlled by diffusion-limited binding of the agonist), but at high concentrations, the activation rates differed. At 3 mM quisqualate, the time constant for activation was 34.8 &#x00B1; 1.2 ms for the intersubunit E-sensor and 51.7 &#x00B1; 2.8 ms for the intrasubunit A-sensor homodimer. The corresponding rate constants (1/&#x03C4;) indicated a significant difference in the maximal activation rates for the inter- versus intrasubunit sensor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>).</p>
<p>When the FRET changes of the two sensors in response to quisqualate (3 mM) were plotted as a function of time (with values for the A-sensor inverted so that both curves can be compared), it was visible that the E-sensor responded to agonist stimulation faster than the A-sensor homodimer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5D</xref>). Thus, the conformational change between the two subunits in an mGluR1 dimer (intersubunit) precedes the conformational change in the HD of an individual subunit (intrasubunit).</p>
<p>The deactivation rates of the A-sensor homodimer and the E-sensor were determined on agonist washout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>, A and B). Washout after stimulation with 100 &#x03BC;M quisqualate caused a reversal of the change in FRET signal in the E-sensor that was slower than the activation time. Curve fitting was optimal with a major rapid component of about 300 ms and a minor slow component of about 6 s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>, A and C). The faster time is still substantially slower than the deactivation time of ~50 ms reported by Marcaggi <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42"><italic>42</italic></xref>). Similar experiments with the intrasubunit A-sensor homodimer also revealed deactivation times of ~300 ms, with mono-exponential time courses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>, B and C). Washout experiments with two additional concentrations of quisqualate (1 or 10 &#x03BC;M) revealed no obvious differences. Within the accuracy of these experiments, the A-sensor homodimer and the E-sensor had similar deactivation time courses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="F6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption>
<p>Deactivation kinetics of the inter- and intramolecular mGluR1 FRET sensors. (<bold>A</bold>) Deactivation kinetics of the intermolecular E-sensor transiently expressed in HEK cells. Data shown are a representative trace in response to washout after stimulation with 100 &#x03BC;M quisqualate, with data points obtained every 20 ms. Curve represents the best fit to a bi-exponential equation as described in Materials and Methods to yield the respective time constants. The time constant for the fast component was 380 &#x00B1; 10 ms. A minor slow component had a time constant of 6.0 &#x00B1; 0.4 s. (<bold>B</bold>) Deactivation kinetics of the intramolecular A-sensor transiently expressed in HEK cells. Data shown are a representative trace in response to washout after stimulation with 100 &#x03BC;M quisqualate, with data points obtained every 20 ms. The curve represents the best fit to the mono-exponential equation as described in Materials and Methods and yields a time constant of 390 &#x00B1; 44 ms. (<bold>C</bold>) Analysis of the deactivation kinetics for the A- and the E-sensor (major, rapid phase) upon washout of 1 or 10 &#x03BC;M quisqualate as indicated. Data are means &#x00B1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 9 to 37, independent experiments). The means are not significantly different [based on <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA), as indicating significance].</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="5_ra59_F6"></graphic></fig>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Heterodimer formation between the A-sensor and other mGluR1 subunits</title>
<p>To study how the two subunits of mGluR1 may affect each other through intersubunit crosstalk, we used a heterodimer composed of the A-sensor and a second subunit modified with the C-terminal quality control system of the GABA<sub>B</sub> receptor. The second subunit (termed R1c2sh) carried a myc tag for ELISA analysis and a shortened version of the C terminus from the GABA<sub>B2</sub> receptor (c2 short) with an additional C-terminal endoplasmic reticulum retention signal KKTN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The latter modification prevented the mGluR1 subunit from reaching the cell surface when transfected alone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52"><italic>52</italic></xref>), as confirmed by ELISA. Cotransfection of the R1c2sh subunit with the A-sensor, on the other hand, resulted in the presence of both subunits at the cell surface (fig. S3A). Because other chimeric receptors with i2-loop insertion fail to signal when expressed alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>) and because chimeras similar to the A-sensor failed to signal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25"><italic>25</italic></xref>), we assumed that the A-sensor subunit alone, which has an i2-loop insertion, would not functionally couple to G proteins and produce a Ca<sup>2+</sup>signal. The R1c2sh alone, because it did not reach the cell surface (fig. S3A), also did not functionally couple to G proteins and cause a Ca<sup>2+</sup> signal (fig. S3B). However, cotransfection of the A-sensor subunit with R1c2sh elicited a Ca<sup>2+</sup> signal, and the maximum amplitude was half that of a heterodimer formed by two functional receptor subunits, such as the C-terminally tagged mGluR1 with R1c2sh (fig. S3B). This was similar to other combinations in which one of the two subunits carried an i2 loop insertion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>) and agrees with conclusions of our earlier studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>).</p> 
<p>Heterodimer formation was further verified with FRET experiments using antibodies recognizing the HA and myc tags, which were labeled with either Eu-cryptate (donor) or the Cisbio D2 (acceptor) (fig. S3, C and D). Time-resolved FRET (TR-FRET) occurred between two HA epitopes, when only the A-sensor was present (indicating homodimer formation), and between HA and myc epitopes, when both the A-sensor and the myc-tagged R1c2 were transfected in a 1:1 ratio, indicating heterodimer formation (fig. S3C). The small signal in the HA-myc FRET seen with the A-sensor alone indicates a background signal. Heterodimerization of the A-sensor with R1c2sh occurred over a wide range of abundance of the A-sensor on the cell surface and was preferred over A-sensor homodimerization (fig. S3D). These data demonstrate that the A-sensor subunit forms heterodimers with the R1c2sh subunit at the cell surface.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Crosstalk in mGluR1 heterodimers with the A-sensor</title>
<p>Heterodimer formation between the A-sensor and the other mGluR1 subunit variants allowed us to study the effects of these latter variants on the activation of the A-sensor. This was initially done using Flp-In HEK cells that stably expressed a tetracycline-inducible (Tet-on) R1c2sh subunit and were cotransfected with the A-sensor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>). This system provides a precise means for producing A-sensor:R1c2sh heterodimers (induced by tetracycline for 24 hours) or A-sensor homodimers (no tetracycline). The ELISA of the HA and myc tags confirmed that there were comparable amounts of the two types of subunits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="F7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption>
<p>Inhibition of agonist-induced FRET signals in the A-sensor by a second mGluR1 subunit. (<bold>A</bold>) Schematic representation of the receptor heterodimer with color codes and symbols as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Demonstration of presence of indicated mGluR1 subunits at the cell surface by ELISA. Expression of the R1c2sh subunit (myc tag) was induced by tetracycline for 24 hours in HEK R1c2sh Flp-In cells or in the same line transiently transfected with the A-sensor. Presence of the A-sensor (HA tag) and the R1c2sh subunit (myc tag) at the cell surface was determined by ELISA with antibodies recognizing the HA or the myc tag, respectively. Data are means &#x00B1; range from <italic>n</italic> = 2 independent experiments performed in triplicates. (<bold>C</bold>) Inhibition of agonist-induced FRET signals in the A-sensor subunit by an R1c2sh subunit. Shown is the FRET change in HEK R1c2sh Flp-In cells transfected with the A-sensor subunit as in (B). Twenty-four&#x2013;hour induction with tetracycline is indicated. Data are means &#x00B1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 33 and 66, respectively, independent experiments; *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, two-sample <italic>t</italic> test). (<bold>D</bold>) Determination of basal FRET in the A-sensor in HEK R1c2sh Flp-In cells, where formation of A-sensor:R1c2sh heterodimers was induced for 24 hours with tetracycline. FRET was determined by donor dequenching after acceptor photobleaching. Shown is one representative trace from nine independent experiments. (<bold>E</bold>) Effects of different YFP-labeled mGluR1 subunits on agonist-induced FRET signals in the A-sensor. HEK cells were transiently transfected with complementary DNAs (cDNAs) for the indicated subunits, and the change in FRET induced by 100 &#x03BC;M quisqualate was measured. Data are means &#x00B1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 29 to 43 independent experiments). *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 versus the A-sensor, two-sample <italic>t</italic> test.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="5_ra59_F7"></graphic></fig>
<p>Whereas cells expressing the A-sensor alone showed a ~7% decrease of the FRET ratio signal in response to quisqualate, the presence of the R1c2sh subunit essentially abolished this FRET signal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7C</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). This suppression of the FRET signal occurred even though the A-sensor was detectable at the cell surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>). Moreover, photobleaching experiments demonstrated that there was basal FRET when both subunits were present (19.1 &#x00B1; 1.9%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7D</xref>).</p>
<p>We also observed suppression of the A-sensor FRET signal when the co-expressed R1c2sh subunit carried the C258E mutation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), which functionally uncouples the VFT domain from its HD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51"><italic>51</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52"><italic>52</italic></xref>). This is compatible with the hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51"><italic>51</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52"><italic>52</italic></xref>) that the HD of R1c2sh may be activated either in cis (through its own VFT) or in trans (through the VFT of the A-sensor subunit) mode. To further test this hypothesis, we examined different heterodimer compositions in dynamic FRET measurements. As partners of the A-sensor subunit, we chose YFP-labeled mGluR1 variants that were either capable of coupling to G proteins (YFP at the C terminus) or not (YFP in the i2 loop). These heterodimers with the A-sensor subunit were generated by transient cotransfection. The A-sensor homodimers showed a ~6% decrease in FRET in response to agonist, as did A-sensor heterodimers with R1i2YFP, a subunit incapable of interacting with G proteins. However, A-sensor heterodimers with R1ctYFP, a subunit capable of interacting with G proteins, abolished the agonist-induced FRET signal of the A-sensor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7E</xref>). Thus, both inducible expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7C</xref>) and transient co-expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7E</xref>) experiments show that the FRET signal of the A-sensor is suppressed by dimer formation with a second subunit that is capable of coupling to G proteins.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The present study elucidates the dynamics of inter- and intramolecular conformational changes in the mGluR1 dimer using FRET measurements between fluorescent protein labels inserted into the receptor. We showed that with suitably placed fluorescent labels, FRET can be used to study both inter- and intramolecular changes in these receptors. In addition, we showed that in response to agonist stimulation, the intermolecular changes preceded the intramolecular changes, and we observed that in an mGluR1 dimer, the presence of an mGluR1 subunit capable of coupling to G proteins prevented the agonist-induced changes in FRET that report intramolecular changes in the adjacent mGluR1 subunit.</p>
<p>The ability to record both inter- and intramolecular changes in mGluR1 contrasts with the experimental methods of Tateyama <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25"><italic>25</italic></xref>) and Marcaggi <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42"><italic>42</italic></xref>). These authors observed only intermolecular changes in FRET, and their sensors for intramolecular FRET did not detect any agonist-induced changes. To create sensors capable of responding to agonist stimulation with a change in their FRET signals, thus identifying intramolecular changes, we generated a large number of constructs with different placements of the fluorescent proteins. Furthermore, the detection of intramolecular changes may have been facilitated by the use of the quality control system derived from the GABA<sub>B</sub> receptor. The resultant stabilization of the receptors&#x2019; C termini by this coiled-coil structure may help to uncover subtle movements of the labels placed in the loops relative to the C terminus. As with other GPCR sensor constructs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35"><italic>35</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40"><italic>40</italic></xref>), the shortening of the C terminus resulted in a six- to eightfold improvement in agonist-induced FRET changes, presumably by placing the two fluorescent labels in an optimal relative position. These differences in the placement of the fluorescent labels may explain the divergence of our observations regarding intramolecular subunit conformational changes in this study from those in the previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25"><italic>25</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42"><italic>42</italic></xref>). We believe that it is unlikely that intermolecular FRET contributed to the agonist-induced signals seen with the intramolecular A-sensor because intermolecular FRET between various constructs was either agonist-independent or increased in response to agonists (E-sensor), whereas the FRET signal decreased with the A-sensor homodimer.</p>
<p>The A-sensor homodimer, used to detect intramolecular changes, retained the ligand-binding and activation properties of wild-type mGluR1: It exhibited differential responses to an agonist, a partial agonist (4C3HPG), and an antagonist (AIDA) and exhibited properties consistent with a key role in the importance of the VFT for transmission of agonist binding to the HD as shown by the effects of the C258E mutation. The distinct amplitudes of agonist- and partial agonist&#x2013;induced signals are compatible with the view that GPCRs can adopt multiple active conformations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33"><italic>33</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53"><italic>53</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57"><italic>57</italic></xref>). Similarly, the fact that the effects of the partial agonist DHPG were slower than those of full agonists is compatible with this view because the kinetics may be different for distinct intramolecular movements. Similarly, in a study with the &#x03B1;<sub>2</sub>-adrenergic receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49"><italic>49</italic></xref>), a class A GPCR reported slower activation by inverse and partial agonists compared to full agonists.</p>
<p>The observation that the co-expressed R1c2sh subunit prevented the intrasubunit conformational change in the A-sensor is consistent with our earlier results indicating that only one HD within the mGluR dimer is activated after agonist addition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>). The R1c2sh subunit might be preferentially in the active state because it can bind to G proteins and thereby be stabilized in its active state, whereas the A-sensor cannot couple to G proteins. These results indicate that a G protein&#x2013;coupling subunit, which is stabilized in its active state by this G protein interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58"><italic>58</italic></xref>), essentially prevents the activation of the A-sensor as recorded by FRET. This is compatible with only one subunit in the mGluR1 dimer reaching active conformation during agonist-mediated signaling.</p>
<p>The availability of both inter- and intramolecular sensors for the mGluR1 dimer allowed us to establish the sequence of events in the activation of this receptor. After the binding of an agonist to the VFT domain of one subunit, the two subunits appear to move closer to each other before there is a change within the HD. The rate of each step increased with the concentration of the agonist but saturated at high agonist concentrations, suggesting that the maximal kinetics approached the actual rates of the relevant steps. The intersubunit step occurred first with a time constant of ~35 ms, whereas the time constant for the intrasubunit step was ~52 ms. The rate of the intersubunit step was much faster than the rate determined by Tateyama <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25"><italic>25</italic></xref>), who did not use a fast superfusion device, but it was slower than the rate determined by Marcaggi <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42"><italic>42</italic></xref>). The latter authors have designed their experiments specifically to be able to monitor rapid effects and observed a rate constant of ~10 ms, but their signal amplitude was only 1%, which in our hands makes it difficult to obtain reliable signals. The rates of the intrasubunit changes are in the same range as those measured for many class A GPCRs, including the &#x03B1;<sub>2A</sub>-, &#x03B2;<sub>1</sub>-, and &#x03B2;<sub>2</sub>-adrenergic receptors; the A<sub>2A</sub>-adenosine receptor; and various muscarinic receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30"><italic>30</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32"><italic>32</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34"><italic>34</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36"><italic>36</italic></xref>). Thus, the overall principle of GPCR activation may be similar across different classes of GPCRs.</p>
<p>The rates of deactivation were similar for the inter- and the intrasubunit sensors and were in the range of 300 ms. This suggests that either the two deactivation processes occurred in a closely linked manner or, under our conditions, the two processes were limited by agonist dissociation and any potential kinetic differences were too small to be detected.</p>
<p>Several studies indicate that in many GPCR dimers, only one of the two subunits becomes activated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58"><italic>58</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59"><italic>59</italic></xref>). We have also reported that in the dimeric mGluR1, only one subunit activates G proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>). In line with these data, the agonist-induced signal of the A-sensor was suppressed by the presence of various mGluR1 constructs. However, only mGluR1 constructs that were capable of coupling to G proteins suppressed the A-sensor activation signal, whereas those that were not capable of coupling to G proteins did not.</p>
<p>Our data suggest that the agonist-induced activation of mGluR1 dimers occurs in a sequential coordinated manner, and this may be true of other class C GPCRs. After agonist binding to the VFT domain of one subunit, the two subunits move relative to each other within ~30 ms. This intermolecular conformational change is followed by a conformational change in the HD of one of the two subunits within ~50 ms, which results in G protein activation. The latter time constant is similar to those reported for class A GPCRs. Because class A and class C receptors exhibit similar kinetics of receptor conformational changes, this suggests that differences in their rates of signaling are likely related to differences in the kinetics of the downstream events of recruiting, interacting with, and activating G proteins.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" disp-level="1">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Chemicals</title>
<p><sc>l</sc>-Quisqualic acid (quisqualate), DHPG, and AIDA were obtained from BIOTREND Chemicals; <sc>l</sc>-glutamic acid (glutamate), Sigma-Aldrich; 4C3HPG and GABA, Tocris Cookson; and carbachol, Alfa Aesar. All compounds except AIDA were dissolved in Hanks&#x2019; balanced salt solution (HBSS) buffer. AIDA was dissolved in NaOH (1 M). Glutamate pyruvate transaminase (GPT) was purchased from Roche Diagnostics and used at a concentration of 1 U/ml.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Construction of mutated mGlu1a receptors</title>
<p>For the construction of the intramolecular mGluR1-based FRET sensor and intermolecular mGluR1-based FRET sensor constructs, we used mGlu1 receptors tagged N-terminally with either HA or C-myc (myc), as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>). To control dimer formation, we replaced the receptors&#x2019; C termini with the C termini of either GABA<sub>B1</sub> (c1) or GABA<sub>B2</sub> (c2) subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>). The enhanced YFP and CFP were inserted between the amino acids Ile<sup>685</sup> and Leu<sup>686</sup> in the i2 loop or attached to the extreme C terminus of the receptors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> and table S1). All constructs were subcloned into the pRK5 expression vector and verified by DNA sequencing. In the intramolecular sensor, the terminal 27 amino acids of the c1 terminus were deleted, thus positioning the CFP 10 amino acids downstream of the RSRR retention signal. All constructs bearing CFP at the GABA<sub>B1</sub> C terminus had a similarly shortened C terminus.</p>
<p>The C258E mutation, which uncoupled the HD from the VFT domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51"><italic>51</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52"><italic>52</italic></xref>), was introduced into the FRET sensor with polymerase chain reaction (PCR). The PCR fragment was amplified with the following primers: 5&#x2032;-AAAAAAGGATCCATGGTCCTTCTGTTGATC-3&#x2032;, 3&#x2032;-TTCCGGAGCTCTAGCGTGTGAGCCTG-5&#x2032;, 5&#x2032;-AAGGCCTCGAGATCGCACACTCGGAC-3&#x2032;, and 3&#x2032;-CCCTGGACCGTACTTCCT-5&#x2032; and was subcloned into Mlu I&#x2013;Pml I digested vector DNA, the pRK5-HA-R1-YFP-c1sh-CFP.</p>
<p>The construction of R1c2sh (pRK5-myc-R1-c2sh), a gift from C. Brock, has been described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52"><italic>52</italic></xref>). For inducible expression in Flp-In HEK293 cells, the cDNA for this construct was subcloned into the vector pcDNA5-FRT/TO (Invitrogen).</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Cell culture and transfection</title>
<p>HEK293 and COS-7 cells were cultured in Dulbecco&#x2019;s modified Eagle&#x2019;s medium (PAN Biotech), without sodium pyruvate, supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, <sc>l</sc>-glutamine, and penicillin/streptomycin cocktail. Cells were transiently transfected by electroporation as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60"><italic>60</italic></xref>). To prevent potential effects of glutamate in the medium, we cotransfected the high-affinity glutamate transporter EAAC1. Flp-In HEK cells bearing the inducible R1c2sh subunit were prepared as described in the manual (Invitrogen) with clonal selection.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Confocal microscopy</title>
<p>Confocal images were taken with a Leica TCS SP5 system. Images were taken with a 63&#x00D7; objective (numerical aperture, 1.4). CFP was excited with a 458-nm laser line, and fluorescence intensities were recorded from 465 to 530 nm. YFP was excited with a 514-nm laser line, and fluorescence intensities were recorded from 525 to 600 nm.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Single-cell FRET measurements with intact cells</title>
<p>HEK cells were electroporated and seeded onto poly-<sc>d</sc>-lysine&#x2013;coated glass coverslips with a medium (GlutaMAX-I medium, Invitrogen) change 3 hours after transfection. FRET experiments were performed with intact cells 24 hours after transfection and after a 1-hour treatment with GPT/pyruvate (1 U/ml; 2 mM) in 0.1% HBSS/bovine serum albumin (BSA) buffer. Fluorescence microscopy was done with an inverted microscope (Axiovert 200, Zeiss) with a 63&#x00D7; oil immersion objective (numerical aperture, 1.4), a dual-emission photometric system, and a polychrome V light source (TILL Photonics). Signals were converted with a Digidata1440A (Axon Instruments) and stored with a Clampex 10.2 software (Axon Instruments).</p>
<p>The fluorescence signal was recorded from entire cells with a frequency of 20 or 50 Hz. The excitation wavelength was 436 &#x00B1; 10 nm (beam splitter dichroic long pass, 460 nm), and emission was recorded at 535 &#x00B1; 15 nm (FRET between CFP and YFP) and 480 &#x00B1; 20 nm (beam splitter dichroic long pass, 505 nm). FRET was monitored as the emission ratio of YFP to CFP. The CFP bleed-through (33 to 50% of <italic>F</italic><sub>CFP</sub>) was recorded separately and subtracted from the YFP fluorescence. The adjusted FRET ratio was further corrected for the direct YFP excitation (YFP emission at 436 nm excitation divided by YFP emission at 500 nm excitation was 0.023 to 0.033). For the measurements of the changes in FRET amplitude (&#x0394;FRET), photobleaching was subtracted from the data, yielding the normalized FRET ratio <italic>R</italic>/<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>. CFP and YFP fluorescence were shown as raw data, whereas all FRET ratios represent corrected data.</p>
<p>Basal FRET was determined with donor dequenching after acceptor photobleaching (2 to 3 min of illumination at 500 nm) as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37"><italic>37</italic></xref>). From the increase and decrease of the CFP (<italic>F</italic><sub>CFP</sub>) and YFP (<italic>F</italic><sub>YFP</sub>) fluorescence, respectively, the FRET efficiency was calculated as follows: <italic>E</italic> = (&#x0394;<italic>F</italic><sub>CFP</sub>/&#x0394;<italic>F</italic><sub>YFP</sub>) &#x00D7; 100.</p>
<p>To determine dynamic changes in FRET, we continuously superfused cells with buffer as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30"><italic>30</italic></xref>). Agonists and antagonists were freshly prepared and applied with a rapid superfusion system (OctaFlow, ALA Scientific Instruments). The change in normalized FRET ratio (&#x0394;<italic>R</italic>/<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>) was fit to the mono-exponential equation &#x0394;<italic>R</italic>/<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>A</italic>e<sup>&#x2013;<italic>t</italic>/</sup><sup>&#x03C4;</sup>, where &#x03C4; is the time constant and <italic>A</italic> is the amplitude of the signal. In the case of the biphasic deactivation, the double-exponential equation &#x0394;<italic>R</italic>/<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub>e<sup>&#x2013;<italic>t</italic>/</sup><sup>&#x03C4;</sup><sup>1</sup> + <italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub>e<sup>&#x2212;<italic>t</italic>/</sup><sup>&#x03C4;</sup><sup>2</sup> was used, where &#x03C4;1 and &#x03C4;2, and <italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>A</italic><sub>2</sub> are the time constants and amplitudes for the faster and slower components, respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Determination of the receptors at the cell surface</title>
<p>The presence of the HA- and myc-tagged receptors at the cell surface was determined by ELISA as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>). Briefly, 24 hours after transfection, the HEK cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde, blocked with 10% fetal calf serum (blocking solution), and incubated for 1 hour with the primary antibody. The cells were washed with the blocking solution and incubated for 1 hour with the secondary antibody coupled to horseradish peroxidase (HRP). The cells were again washed several times with the blocking solution and phosphate-buffered saline. The primary antibodies used were the polyclonal rabbit antibody recognizing HA and the monoclonal mouse antibody recognizing myc (clone 9B11; Cell Signaling, New England Biolabs) at a dilution of 1:1000. As secondary antibodies, we used the antibodies coupled to HRP that recognized rabbit or mouse antibody (Dianova) at a dilution of 1:1000. HRP signal was quantified by chemiluminescence with SuperSignal ELISA Femto Maximum Sensitivity Substrate (Pierce) and a Mithras LB 940 microplate reader (Berthold Technologies). The signals obtained from mock-transfected cells were used to define background labeling and were subtracted from each value.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>TR-FRET analysis</title>
<p>These experiments were performed with COS-7 cells transiently expressing HA- or HA- and myc-tagged receptor subunits and were conducted as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>). Briefly, 1 day after transfection, the cells were washed with 1% glucose in HBSS and incubated with tag-specific antibodies. The antibodies recognizing HA (12CA5) and the antibodies recognizing myc (9E10) were labeled with either Eu<sup>3+</sup>-cryptate TATA box&#x2013;binding protein as a donor or D2 as an acceptor fluorophore (Cisbio Bioassays). To avoid quenching of the donor antibody label, we added potassium fluoride to cells to a final concentration of 0.2 M. The TR-FRET signal was measured 50 &#x03BC;s after excitation at 320 nm, and emission was measured at 620 and 665 nm, respectively, with the microplate reader EnVision (Perkin Elmer). The TR-FRET signal was calculated as follows: &#x0394;<italic>R</italic> &#x00D7; 100/<italic>R</italic><sub>neg</sub>. &#x0394;<italic>R</italic> indicates (<italic>R</italic><sub>pos</sub> &#x2212; <italic>R</italic><sub>neg</sub>), where <italic>R</italic><sub>pos</sub> is the ratio of the 665 signal over the 620 signal measured in the presence of both antibodies, and <italic>R</italic><sub>neg</sub> is the same ratio measured in the absence of the acceptor-labeled antibody.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Intracellular calcium mobilization assay</title>
<p>Measurements of intracellular calcium release were performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>). Briefly, HEK cells were washed with 0.1% BSA HBSS and loaded with calcium-sensitive dye Fluo-4 AM (1 &#x03BC;M; Molecular Probes). After 1 hour of incubation at 37&#x00B0;C, the cells were washed and 50 &#x03BC;l of 0.1% BSA HBSS was added into each well. An application plate was prepared with different concentrations of quisqualate, and twice-concentrated quisqualate solution (50 &#x03BC;l) was added into each well 20 s after the start of the recording. Both excitation at 485 nm and emission at 525 nm were measured with a FlexStation (Molecular Devices) every 1.5 s for 1 min.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>All data are presented as means &#x00B1; SEM (or as the range) of <italic>n</italic> independent experiments. SEM given for curve fits represent the uncertainty of the fit. Statistical analyses were performed with the OriginLab software.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back><app-group><app>
<title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencesignaling.org/cgi/content/full/5/237/ra59/DC1">www.sciencesignaling.org/cgi/content/full/5/237/ra59/DC1</ext-link></p>
<p>Fig. S1. mGluR1 constructs for intersubunit FRET are present on the cell surface.</p>
<p>Fig. S2. Uncoupling of the VFT domain of the A-sensor subunit abolishes agonist-induced changes in FRET.</p>
<p>Fig. S3. Formation of heterodimers with the A-sensor.</p>
<p>Table S1. Positioning of the fluorophores within the mGlu1-based receptor FRET sensors.</p>
<p>Table S2. Values for the Hill coefficient (<italic>h</italic>) and 95% confidence interval for concentration-response curves.</p></supplementary-material></app></app-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arcemisb&#x00E9;h&#x00E8;re</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boudier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balestre</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaibelet</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Detouillon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orcel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendre</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahmeh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Granier</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Viv&#x00E8;s</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fieschi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Damian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durroux</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ban&#x00E8;res</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mouillac</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Leukotriene BLT2 receptor monomers activate the G<sub>i2</sub> GTP-binding protein more efficiently than dimers.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>285</volume>, 
<fpage>6337</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6347</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>O. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gramse</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolbe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Monomeric G protein-coupled receptor rhodopsin in solution activates its G protein transducin at the diffusion limit.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>104</volume>, 
<fpage>10859</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10864</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jastrzebska</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fotiadis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipek</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenkamp</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palczewski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Functional characterization of rhodopsin monomers and dimers in detergents.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>279</volume>, 
<fpage>54663</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>54675</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuszak</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitchiaya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosberg</surname><given-names>H. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>N. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunahara</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Purification and functional reconstitution of monomeric &#x03BC;-opioid receptors: Allosteric modulation of agonist binding by G<sub>i2</sub>.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>284</volume>, 
<fpage>26732</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>26741</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeVree</surname><given-names>B. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>K. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobilka</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thian</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calinski</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathiesen</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caffrey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gellman</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steyaert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skiniotis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>W. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunahara</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobilka</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Crystal structure of the &#x03B2;<sub>2</sub> adrenergic receptor&#x2013;Gs protein complex.</article-title> <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>477</volume>, 
<fpage>549</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>555</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whorton</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokoch</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zare</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobilka</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunahara</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A monomeric G protein-coupled receptor isolated in a high-density lipoprotein particle efficiently activates its G protein.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>104</volume>, 
<fpage>7682</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7687</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whorton</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jastrzebska</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fotiadis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palczewski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunahara</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Efficient coupling of transducin to monomeric rhodopsin in a phospholipid bilayer.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>283</volume>, 
<fpage>4387</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4394</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferr&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aymerich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lluis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Calcium-mediated modulation of the quaternary structure and function of adenosine A<sub>2A</sub>&#x2013;dopamine D<sub>2</sub> receptor heteromers.</article-title> <source>Curr. Opin. Pharmacol.</source> 
<volume>10</volume>, 
<fpage>67</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>72</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Dimerization in GPCR mobility and signaling.</article-title> <source>Curr. Opin. Pharmacol.</source> 
<volume>10</volume>, 
<fpage>53</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>58</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neubig</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Devi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Filizola</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Javitch</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milligan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palczewski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmentier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spedding</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>International Union of Basic and Clinical Pharmacology. LXVII. Recommendations for the recognition and nomenclature of G protein-coupled receptor heteromultimers.</article-title> <source>Pharmacol. Rev.</source> 
<volume>59</volume>, 
<fpage>5</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>13</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varghese</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x2019;Dowd</surname><given-names>B. F.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Oligomerization of &#x03BC;- and &#x03B4;-opioid receptors. Generation of novel functional properties.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>275</volume>, 
<fpage>26128</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>26135</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapaidze</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Devi</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Heterodimerization of &#x03BC; and &#x03B4; opioid receptors: A role in opiate synergy.</article-title> <source>J. Neurosci.</source> 
<volume>20</volume>, 
<fpage>RC110</fpage> (<year>2000</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eid</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocheville</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazlett</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gratton</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Ligand binding to somatostatin receptors induces receptor-specific oligomer formation in live cells.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>99</volume>, 
<fpage>3294</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3299</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x00ED;guez-Frade</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vila-Coro</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Ana</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albar</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;nez</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellado</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The chemokine monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 induces functional responses through dimerization of its receptor CCR2.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>96</volume>, 
<fpage>3628</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3633</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salahpour</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Dimerization: An emerging concept for G protein-coupled receptor ontogeny and function.</article-title> <source>Annu. Rev. Pharmacol. Toxicol.</source> 
<volume>42</volume>, 
<fpage>409</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>435</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorsch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klotz</surname><given-names>K. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;nemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Analysis of receptor oligomerization by FRAP microscopy.</article-title> <source>Nat. Methods</source> 
<volume>6</volume>, 
<fpage>225</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>230</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maurel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Comps-Agrar</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rives</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourrier</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayoub</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durroux</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pr&#x00E9;zeau</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trinquet</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Cell-surface protein-protein interaction analysis with time-resolved FRET and snap-tag technologies: Application to GPCR oligomerization.</article-title> <source>Nat. Methods</source> 
<volume>5</volume>, 
<fpage>561</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>567</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salahpour</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Angers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Functional significance of oligomerization of G-protein-coupled receptors.</article-title> <source>Trends Endocrinol. Metab.</source> 
<volume>11</volume>, 
<fpage>163</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>168</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciruela</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McIlhinney</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Characterization of the dimerization of metabotropic glutamate receptors using an N-terminal truncation of mGluR1&#x03B1;.</article-title> <source>J. Neurochem.</source> 
<volume>72</volume>, 
<fpage>2539</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2547</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x2019;Malley</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Metabotropic glutamate receptor 5 is a disulfide-linked dimer.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>271</volume>, 
<fpage>28612</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>28616</lpage> (<year>1996</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Main</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Disney</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Foord</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Heterodimerization is required for the formation of a functional GABA<sub>B</sub> receptor.</article-title> <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>396</volume>, 
<fpage>679</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>682</lpage> (<year>1998</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bessis</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rondard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaven</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brabet</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Triballeau</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pr&#x00E9;zeau</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acher</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Closure of the Venus flytrap module of mGlu8 receptor and the activation process: Insights from mutations converting antagonists into agonists.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>99</volume>, 
<fpage>11097</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11102</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaupmann</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malitschek</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuler</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heid</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Froestl</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosbacher</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bischoff</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigemoto</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karschin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettler</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>GABA<sub>B</sub>-receptor subtypes assemble into functional heteromeric complexes.</article-title> <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>396</volume>, 
<fpage>683</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>687</lpage> (<year>1998</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parnot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobilka</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Toward understanding GPCR dimers.</article-title> <source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source> 
<volume>11</volume>, 
<fpage>691</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>692</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tateyama</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Ligand-induced rearrangement of the dimeric metabotropic glutamate receptor 1&#x03B1;.</article-title> <source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source> 
<volume>11</volume>, 
<fpage>637</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>642</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolaev</surname><given-names>V. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilardaga</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;nemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Kinetics of G-protein-coupled receptor signals in intact cells.</article-title> <source>Br. J. Pharmacol.</source> 
<volume>153</volume> (<supplement>Suppl. 1</supplement>), 
<fpage>S125</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>S132</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goudet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kniazeff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hlavackova</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malhaire</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acher</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blahos</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pr&#x00E9;zeau</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Asymmetric functioning of dimeric metabotropic glutamate receptors disclosed by positive allosteric modulators.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>280</volume>, 
<fpage>24380</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24385</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hlavackova</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goudet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kniazeff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zikova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vol</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanova</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pr&#x00E9;zeau</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blahos</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Evidence for a single heptahelical domain being turned on upon activation of a dimeric GPCR.</article-title> <source>EMBO J.</source> 
<volume>24</volume>, 
<fpage>499</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>509</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>F. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacharias</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swofford</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>R. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenardo</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Fluorescence resonance energy transfer analysis of cell surface receptor interactions and signaling using spectral variants of the green fluorescent protein.</article-title> <source>Cytometry</source> 
<volume>44</volume>, 
<fpage>361</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>368</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaietta</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;nemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oberdorff-Maass</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Behr</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilardaga</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>R. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellisman</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A FlAsH-based FRET approach to determine G protein&#x2013;coupled receptor activation in living cells.</article-title> <source>Nat. Methods</source> 
<volume>2</volume>, 
<fpage>171</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>176</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyssand</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hague</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hille</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Fluorescence changes reveal kinetic steps of muscarinic receptor&#x2013;mediated modulation of phosphoinositides and Kv7.2/7.3 K<sup>+</sup> channels.</article-title> <source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source> 
<volume>133</volume>, 
<fpage>347</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>359</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maier-Peuschel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fr&#x00F6;lich</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dees</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hommers</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolaev</surname><given-names>V. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A fluorescence resonance energy transfer-based M<sub>2</sub> muscarinic receptor sensor reveals rapid kinetics of allosteric modulation.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>285</volume>, 
<fpage>8793</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8800</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambrosio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Differential signaling of the endogenous agonists at the &#x03B2;<sub>2</sub>-adrenergic receptor.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>285</volume>, 
<fpage>36188</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>36198</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rochais</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilardaga</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolaev</surname><given-names>V. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;nemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Real-time optical recording of &#x03B2;<sub>1</sub>-adrenergic receptor activation reveals supersensitivity of the Arg389 variant to carvedilol.</article-title> <source>J. Clin. Invest.</source> 
<volume>117</volume>, 
<fpage>229</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>235</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vilardaga</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;nemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Measurement of the millisecond activation switch of G protein&#x2013;coupled receptors in living cells.</article-title> <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source> 
<volume>21</volume>, 
<fpage>807</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>812</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00E4;tz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabel</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>FRET-based sensors for the human M<sub>1</sub>-, M<sub>3</sub>-, and M<sub>5</sub>-acetylcholine receptors.</article-title> <source>Bioorg. Med. Chem.</source> 
<volume>19</volume>, 
<fpage>1048</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1054</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x00FC;nemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Gi protein activation in intact cells involves subunit rearrangement rather than dissociation.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>100</volume>, 
<fpage>16077</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>16082</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;nemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Dynamics of receptor/G protein coupling in living cells.</article-title> <source>EMBO J.</source> 
<volume>24</volume>, 
<fpage>4106</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4114</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rochais</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorsch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolaev</surname><given-names>V. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berlot</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;nemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>G<sub>s</sub> activation is time-limiting in initiating receptor-mediated signaling.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>281</volume>, 
<fpage>33345</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>33351</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R40"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolaev</surname><given-names>V. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilardaga</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;nemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Optical techniques to analyze real-time activation and signaling of G-protein-coupled receptors.</article-title> <source>Trends Pharmacol. Sci.</source> 
<volume>29</volume>, 
<fpage>159</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>165</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R41"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nikolaev</surname><given-names>V. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;nemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannawacker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Novel single chain cAMP sensors for receptor-induced signal propagation.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>279</volume>, 
<fpage>37215</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>37218</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R42"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcaggi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutoh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kn&#x00F6;pfel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Optical measurement of mGluR1 conformational changes reveals fast activation, slow deactivation, and sensitization.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>106</volume>, 
<fpage>11388</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11393</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R43"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kniazeff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bessis</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ansanay</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pr&#x00E9;zeau</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Closed state of both binding domains of homodimeric mGlu receptors is required for full activity.</article-title> <source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source> 
<volume>11</volume>, 
<fpage>706</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>713</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R44"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joly</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomeza</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brabet</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bockaert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Molecular, functional, and pharmacological characterization of the metabotropic glutamate receptor type 5 splice variants: Comparison with mGluR1.</article-title> <source>J. Neurosci.</source> 
<volume>15</volume>, 
<fpage>3970</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3981</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R45"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mutel</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaboz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilly</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleuel</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Metzler</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malherbe</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlaeger</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roughley</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faull</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Characterization of [<sup>3</sup>H]quisqualate binding to recombinant rat metabotropic glutamate 1a and 5a receptors and to rat and human brain sections.</article-title> <source>J. Neurochem.</source> 
<volume>75</volume>, 
<fpage>2590</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2601</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R46"><label>46</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunishima</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumasaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jingami</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Structural basis of glutamate recognition by a dimeric metabotropic glutamate receptor.</article-title> <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>407</volume>, 
<fpage>971</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>977</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R47"><label>47</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jingami</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Structures of the extracellular regions of the group II/III metabotropic glutamate receptors.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>104</volume>, 
<fpage>3759</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3764</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R48"><label>48</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kniazeff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goudet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bessis</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galvez</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acher</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rondard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pr&#x00E9;zeau</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The activation mechanism of class-C G-protein coupled receptors.</article-title> <source>Biol. Cell</source> 
<volume>96</volume>, 
<fpage>335</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>342</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R49"><label>49</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nikolaev</surname><given-names>V. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;nemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilardaga</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Molecular basis of partial agonism at the neurotransmitter &#x03B1;<sub>2A</sub>-adrenergic receptor and G<sub>i</sub>-protein heterotrimer.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>281</volume>, 
<fpage>24506</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24511</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R50"><label>50</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brabet</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mary</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bockaert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Phenylglycine derivatives discriminate between mGluR1- and mGluR5-mediated responses.</article-title> <source>Neuropharmacology</source> 
<volume>34</volume>, 
<fpage>895</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>903</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R51"><label>51</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rondard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malhaire</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vol</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinault</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Labesse</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Coupling of agonist binding to effector domain activation in metabotropic glutamate-like receptors.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>281</volume>, 
<fpage>24653</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24661</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R52"><label>52</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oueslati</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boudier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rondard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Activation of a dimeric metabotropic glutamate receptor by intersubunit rearrangement.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>282</volume>, 
<fpage>33000</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>33008</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R53"><label>53</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghanouni</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gryczynski</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenhuis</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrens</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakowicz</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobilka</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Functionally different agonists induce distinct conformations in the G protein coupling domain of the &#x03B2;<sub>2</sub> adrenergic receptor.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>276</volume>, 
<fpage>24433</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24436</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R54"><label>54</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Agonist-selective, receptor-specific interaction of human P<sub>2Y</sub> receptors with &#x03B2;-arrestin-1 and -2.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>283</volume>, 
<fpage>30933</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>30941</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R55"><label>55</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobilka</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Structural insights into adrenergic receptor function and pharmacology.</article-title> <source>Trends Pharmacol. Sci.</source> 
<volume>32</volume>, 
<fpage>213</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>218</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R56"><label>56</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parnot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deupi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratnala</surname><given-names>V. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaminath</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrens</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobilka</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Coupling ligand structure to specific conformational switches in the &#x03B2;<sub>2</sub>-adrenoceptor.</article-title> <source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source> 
<volume>2</volume>, 
<fpage>417</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>422</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R57"><label>57</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Z&#x00FC;rn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabel</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilardaga</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schindelin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Fluorescence resonance energy transfer analysis of &#x03B1;<sub>2A</sub>-adrenergic receptor activation reveals distinct agonist-specific conformational changes.</article-title> <source>Mol. Pharmacol.</source> 
<volume>75</volume>, 
<fpage>534</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>541</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R58"><label>58</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Damian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesnier</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ban&#x00E8;res</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Asymmetric conformational changes in a GPCR dimer controlled by G-proteins.</article-title> <source>EMBO J.</source> 
<volume>25</volume>, 
<fpage>5693</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5702</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R59"><label>59</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vilardaga</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolaev</surname><given-names>V. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrandon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Conformational cross-talk between &#x03B1;<sub>2A</sub>-adrenergic and &#x03BC;-opioid receptors controls cell signaling.</article-title> <source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source> 
<volume>4</volume>, 
<fpage>126</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>131</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R60"><label>60</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brabet</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmentier</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Colle</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bockaert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acher</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Comparative effect of <sc>l</sc>-CCG-I, DCG-IV and &#x03B3;-carboxy-<sc>l</sc>-glutamate on all cloned metabotropic glutamate receptor subtypes.</article-title> <source>Neuropharmacology</source> 
<volume>37</volume>, 
<fpage>1043</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1051</lpage> (<year>1998</year>).</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank C. Vol, H. Jurova, M. Hoffmann, and C. Dees for the technical help. We also thank M. Hlavacek for the IT support and help. The intracellular calcium release, the inositol phosphate assays, and the HTRF experiments have been performed using the ARPEGE (Pharmacology Screening Interactome) platform facility at the Institut de G&#x00E9;nomique Fonctionnelle (Montpellier, France). The polyclonal rabbit antibody recognizing HA was a gift from S. Schulz, W&#x00FC;rzburg/Jena, Germany. <bold>Funding:</bold> This work was supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (SFB487 TPA1); the European Research Council (advanced grant TOPAS); the Grant Agency of the Czech Republic (GACR 303/08/1591, GACR P303/12/2408); the Czech Science Foundation and the Ministry of Education of the Czech Republic (LC 06063); the CNRS, INSERM, and the Agence Nationale de la Recherche (grants ANR-06-BLAN-0087 and ANR-09-PIRI-0014); and the European Molecular Biology Organization (long-term fellowship to V.H.). <bold>Author contributions:</bold> V.H. and J. B&#x00E4;tz performed the experiments and analyzed the data. V.H., U.Z., and D.F. prepared expression constructs. V.H., J. Blahos, J.-P.P., and M.J.L. designed the experiments and wrote the paper. C.H. and L.P. were technical consultants and revised the manuscript. <bold>Competing interests:</bold> The University of W&#x00FC;rzburg holds a patent on GPCR FRET sensors.</p>
</ack></back>
</article>
