<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Anthropology</subject><subject>Environment</subject><subject>Medicine</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ANTHRO</subject><subject>PALEO</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Paleoanthropology Society | 2&#x2013;3 April | Honolulu</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Following the Males' Trail, 1.5 Million Years Later</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balter</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>26</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6131</issue>
<fpage seq="b">426</fpage>
<lpage>427</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
    <abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>A team described 1.5-million-year-old footprints of at least six individuals walking together across the sand at Ileret, Kenya. Coupled with experiments with living people, the researchers concluded that the size and direction of the prints suggest a party of males out hunting or on patrol, an example of male coalitionary behavior also seen in chimpanzees.</p></abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>A team described 1.5-million-year-old footprints of at least six individuals walking together across the sand at Ileret, Kenya. Coupled with experiments with living people, the researchers concluded that the size and direction of the prints suggest a party of males out hunting or on patrol, an example of male coalitionary behavior also seen in chimpanzees.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><bold>HONOLULU</bold>&#x2014;Fossils can say a lot about what human ancestors looked like, but their evidence is indirect when it comes to how hominins behaved. That's why rare finds of hominin footprints generate such excitement: They capture ancient human activity at a moment in time. But only a handful of such tracks are known.</p>
<p>At the Paleoanthropology Society meeting here this month, a team described 1.5-million-year-old footprints of at least six individuals walking together across the sand at Ileret, Kenya. Coupled with experiments with living people, the researchers concluded that the size and direction of the prints suggest a party of males out hunting or on patrol, an example of male coalitionary behavior also seen in chimpanzees, says team leader Brian Richmond of George Washington University (GWU) in Washington, D.C.</p>
    <p>The team had earlier reported other footprints at Ileret, (<italic>Science</italic>, 27 February 2009, p. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/323/5918/1197.full">1197</ext-link>), which showed that by 1.5 million years ago hominins had evolved a nearly modern foot. Richmond reported here on two new footprint trails: one headed east and the other west. The prints, made in mud near a river, were well preserved by later mud flows that quickly covered them and then hardened. The eastbound prints were made by six to eight individuals; the westbound prints were made by at least five. Some of the westbound prints were partly superimposed on the first set and could have been the same individuals coming back, Richmond said.</p>
<p>Unlike TV detectives, who can tell exactly which shoe a culprit was wearing from their prints, the traces of barefoot hominins have to be interpreted cautiously, Richmond said. A footprint in sand is not a mirror image of the foot that made it, because it also reflects the type of sediment and how fast the maker was traveling.</p>
<p>So in a companion talk, GWU Ph.D. student Kevin Hatala detailed experiments with the local Daasanach people, who traditionally walk shoeless. The researchers asked 20 Daasanach men and 20 women to walk and run barefoot across a strip of sand, moistened to various degrees, next to the Ileret site. The length of their footprints correlated well with the length of their feet, but print width was a poor predictor of actual foot width. The footprint dimensions were good predictors of height and reasonably good predictors of body weight, Hatala found.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Footsteps on the sands of time.</title>
<p>Comparing ancient and modern footprints at Ileret, Kenya (<italic>above</italic>), gives insights into early human behavior.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_426b_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: BRIAN RICHMOND; KEVIN HATALA</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Three hominins lived near Ileret around that time: <italic>Homo erectus, H. habilis</italic>, and the australopithecine <italic>Paranthropus boisei</italic>. The prints were all too large to have been made by the smaller <italic>H. habilis</italic> or by females, the team concluded, and must have been made by males of either <italic>H. erectus</italic> or <italic>P. boisei</italic>.</p>
<p>Such gatherings of males are seen "in humans that are hunting or tracking, or groups of male chimps out on patrol," Richmond says. "This male coalitionary behavior was probably represented in the common ancestor of humans and chimps."</p>
<p>Others at the meeting expressed cautious enthusiasm. "Footprints are cool," says Ariane Burke, an anthropologist at the University of Montreal in Canada. But "interpreting social behavior based on footprints begs for extreme caution," says Zeray Alemseged, an anthropologist at the California Academy of Sciences in San Francisco. Anthropologist Susan Larson of the Stony Brook University School of Medicine in New York agrees, but adds that "at least this speculation has some basis in fact."</p>
</body>
</article>