<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1234493</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1234493</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Report</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Reports</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>reports</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ANTHRO</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Sociology</subject><subject>Earth-Science</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Early Ceremonial Constructions at Ceibal, Guatemala, and the Origins of Lowland Maya Civilization</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Inomata</surname><given-names>Takeshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Triadan</surname><given-names>Daniela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aoyama</surname><given-names>Kazuo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>Victor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yonenobu</surname><given-names>Hitoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>School of Anthropology, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ 85721&#x2013;0030, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Faculty of Humanities, University of Ibaraki, Mito 310-8512, Japan.</aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Graduate School of Education, Naruto University of Education, Tokushima 772-8502, Japan.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. E-mail: <email xlink:href="inomata@email.arizona.edu">inomata@email.arizona.edu</email></corresp></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>26</day><month>04</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6131</issue>
<fpage>467</fpage>
<lpage>471</lpage>
<history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>02</month><year>2013</year></date></history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="editor"><title>Early Mayan Architects</title><p>Lowland Mayan civilizations began to construct dramatic pyramids beginning about 900 BCE. The cultural origins of these civilizations have been uncertain, particularly the connection to earlier Olmec cultures along the Gulf of Mexico. <bold>Inomata <italic>et al.</italic></bold> (p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="340" issue="6131" page="467">467</related-article>; see the cover; see the News story by <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="340" page="417" issue="6131">Pringle</related-article>) describe excavations and extensive radiocarbon dating at the early Mayan city of Ceibal in Guatamala. The site shows incipient plaza and pyramid construction beginning before those seen in the lowlands or Olmec areas, suggesting a broader cultural exchange through to the Pacific Coast as Mayan cultures evolved.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Excavations at the Mayan city of Ceibal, Guatemala, reveal early examples of plazas and pyramids.</p></abstract>
<abstract>
<p>The spread of plaza-pyramid complexes across southern Mesoamerica during the early Middle Preclassic period (1000 to 700 BCE) provides critical information regarding the origins of lowland Maya civilization and the role of the Gulf Coast Olmec. Recent excavations at the Maya site of Ceibal, Guatemala, documented the growth of a formal ceremonial space into a plaza-pyramid complex that predated comparable buildings at other lowland Maya sites and major occupations at the Olmec center of La Venta. The development of lowland Maya civilization did not result from one-directional influence from La Venta, but from interregional interactions, involving groups in the southwestern Maya lowlands, Chiapas, the Pacific Coast, and the southern Gulf Coast.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Brooks Hanson</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Cara Tate</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>During the early Middle Preclassic period (1000 to 700 BCE), sedentary communities using ceramics began to appear in the Maya lowlands (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Many of their neighbors were already leading sedentary ways of life and were using ceramics during the Early Preclassic period (before 1000 BCE) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). In particular, the inhabitants of southern Veracruz and western Tabasco, generally called the Gulf Coast Olmec, were building a large center at San Lorenzo and were producing elaborate stone sculptures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). Scholars have long debated the influence that the Gulf Coast Olmec had on the development of lowland Maya society. Some view the Gulf Coast Olmec as the mother culture: the source of cultural innovations from which characteristic art styles and centralized political organization spread to the Maya and other Mesoamerican groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). Others contend that the lowland Maya received only limited Olmec influence or interacted with them as competing peers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>). A critical issue is the development of formal architectural complexes consisting of plazas and pyramids, which eventually became the hallmarks of Mesoamerican civilizations. San Lorenzo did not have substantial mounds or pyramids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>). The subsequent Gulf Coast center of La Venta, in contrast, exhibited a highly formalized arrangement of a pyramid, platforms, and plazas, and it has been suggested that this architectural template developed there spread to the Maya lowlands and other parts of southern Mesoamerica (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>). Here we describe excavations at the Maya center of Ceibal that provide evidence of earlier architecture and thus imply a more complex process.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Map of southern Mesoamerica with the locations of Ceibal and the sites discussed in the text.</bold></p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="340_467_F1"></graphic></fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Chronology of southern Mesoamerica.</bold></p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="340_467_F2"></graphic></fig>
<p>Ceibal (also spelled Seibal) is located in the southwestern part of the Maya lowlands and was explored extensively in the 1960s by a team from Harvard University (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>). These studies showed that its occupation began during the early Middle Preclassic period characterized by Real ceramics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13"><italic>13</italic></xref>). We targeted group A, where the Harvard team found concentrations of Real ceramics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Our excavations revealed early Middle Preclassic buildings in four areas: the core of structure A-20 and the plaza in front of structure A-20, as well as in the lower levels of the A-24 platform and the East Court. Structure A-20 appears to have at least 11 construction stages, of which 5 or more date to the Real phase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). The excavation results and radiocarbon dates indicate that around 1000 BCE, the early residents of Ceibal made the first version of structure A-20 (Ajaw) by carving a high point of the limestone bedrock and placing black soil with high clay content on top (fig. S1). This building measured 2.0 m in height and 4.0 m in the east-west dimension of its summit. Thus, the first version of A-20 was a low flat platform rather than a pyramid. On the eastern side of the building, a ramp carved out of natural marl (decaying limestone bedrock) provided access to the summit. A major renovation took place during the Real 2 phase (850 to 800 BCE), and the expanded building (B&#x2019;ehom) appears to have reached a height of 3 to 5 m and had a pyramidal shape. We estimate that the building measured roughly 6 to 8 m in height by the end of the Real phase around 700 BCE. Fifty meters to the east of structure Ajaw, we uncovered a long platform (Xa&#x2019;an) buried under later plaza fills. Structure Xa&#x2019;an was also carved out of natural marl around 1000 BCE, and it measured 1.0 m in height and probably 42 to 55 m in length. Structures Ajaw and Xa&#x2019;an represent the earliest known example of the so-called &#x201C;E-Group assemblage,&#x201D; a ceremonial compound consisting of a western square structure and an eastern long platform that became ritual foci of many lowland Maya centers during later periods. At the same time, the residents scraped off the surface soil in the area between structures Ajaw and Xa&#x2019;an to create a leveled plaza and used the exposed whitish marl as the first plaza floor. Numerous offerings, including greenstone axes, were deposited in this plaza, indicating that this space served as the primary stage of communal ritual throughout the Middle Preclassic period. During the Real 3 phase (800 to 700 BCE), the Ceibal residents expanded this plaza by burying structure Xa&#x2019;an in a plaza fill and constructing a new version of the eastern long platform (Saqpusin) farther to the east.</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Map of Ceibal group A with the locations of excavation units and Real-phase structures.</bold></p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="340_467_F3"></graphic></fig>
<fig id="F4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption>
<p><bold>East-west section of the central plaza and structures A-10 and A-20.</bold></p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="340_467_F4"></graphic></fig>
<p>The earliest version of the A-24 platform (Sulul), revealed in operation (Op.) 200B, was also built around 1000 BCE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> and fig. S2). It consisted of sticky dark clay that appears to have been taken from the wetlands and was placed directly over the irregular natural ground surface. This fill measured 1.3 m in thickness, but the platform&#x2019;s horizontal dimensions are unknown. Platform Sulul was soon expanded horizontally to reach an east-west dimension of more than 34 m, as indicated by the find of the same wetland-soil fill in Op. 200A. The total thickness of platform Sulul&#x2019;s fill in Op. 200A measured more than 2.5 m because of the sloping natural terrain, suggesting that the construction of this platform involved a substantial investment of labor. During the latter part of the Real 1 phase, the Ceibal residents expanded this platform vertically using clay mixed with silt and sand. Through at least 17 episodes of construction by the end of the Real 2 phase, the renovated version of the platform (Ch&#x2019;och&#x2019;) reached total fill thicknesses of 3.5 m in Op. 200B and roughly 6 m in Op. 200A. During the Real 3 phase, the A-24 platform received little renovation, and the focus of construction activity shifted to the northeastern platform, the East Court. This platform started with one or two episodes of substantial construction with earthen fills (K&#x2019;at), possibly during the Real 2 phase, which measured 1.4 to 1.7 m in total thickness. By the end of the Real phase, platform K&#x2019;at had received at least 15 episodes of reflooring and rebuilding, reaching a fill thickness of 2.0 to 2.3 m. In contrast to structures Ajaw, Xa&#x2019;an, and Saqpusin of a public and ceremonial nature, platforms Sulul/Ch&#x2019;och&#x2019; and K&#x2019;at appear to have supported multiple residential structures, which consisted of low clay or clay-and-stone foundations and perishable walls and roofs. Excavations of the East Court revealed parts of three structures dating to the late Middle Preclassic Escoba phase, which appear to have surrounded a square patio. We suspect that a residential complex in a similar configuration existed during the Real phase.</p>
<fig id="F5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption>
<p><bold>East-west section of the A-24 platform.</bold></p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="340_467_F5"></graphic></fig>
<p>We obtained 54 radiocarbon dates, to which we applied Bayesian modeling to develop a site chronology (figs. S3 and S4 and table S1). Multiple dates associated with the earliest versions of structures Ajaw and Xa&#x2019;an and platform Sulul concentrate around 1000 BCE, marking the beginning of the Real 1 phase. The following Real 2 phase is dated to 850 to 800 BCE with 13 overlapping radiocarbon dates. This facet is more precisely dated because the radiocarbon calibration curve of this span is steep, and the radiocarbon dates obtained from a sequence of numerous floors in platform Ch&#x2019;och&#x2019; made Bayesian modeling effective. The date of the Real 3 phase is less precise because of the flattening of the calibration curve, but we estimate that it spanned from 800 to 700 BCE.</p>
<p>The beginning date of 1000 BCE for Ceibal corresponds roughly with the onset of sedentary settlements with ceramics in other parts of the Maya lowlands, including Cuello, Cahal Pech, Blackman Eddy, and Tikal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17"><italic>17</italic></xref>). Although some of these sites have yielded earlier calibrated dates, acceptable dates from secure contexts tend to fall around 1000 BCE or later (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18"><italic>18</italic></xref>). Furthermore, these sites share ceramics with post-slip incisions characteristic of the early Middle Preclassic period. However, formal ceremonial complexes dating to 1000 to 800 BCE have not been found at these other sites; excavations have revealed only humble residences, consisting of postholes dug in the natural ground or small platforms less than half a meter in height. The Ceibal E-Group assemblage consisting of structures Ajaw and Xa&#x2019;an thus predates other known examples from the Maya lowlands by two centuries or more. Komchen may have substantial platforms dating to the early Middle Preclassic period, but their initial configuration is not clear, and their dates remain imprecise. During the Real 2 phase, the Ceibal E-Group assemblage grew to be the earliest known plaza-pyramid complex in the Maya lowlands, and structure B&#x2019;ehom and platform Ch&#x2019;och&#x2019; represented the earliest monumental constructions. The next oldest E-Group assemblages in the Maya lowlands have been found at Tikal and Cival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17"><italic>17</italic></xref>). They are associated with ceramics contemporaneous with the Real 3 and Escoba 1 phases (800 to 600 BCE). During the late Middle Preclassic period (700 to 400 BCE), E-Group assemblages with pyramids spread to numerous lowland Maya centers, including Nakbe.</p>
<p>Outside the Maya lowlands, interpretations hinge on a comparison with La Venta. Much of our knowledge of this Olmec center comes from excavations in the 1940s and 1950s, and a large part of the site is unexplored. Its chronology has been a vexing problem. New radiocarbon dates and the cross-dating of ceramics and figurines, however, suggest to some that the rise of La Venta as a major center occurred after 800 BCE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19"><italic>19</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21"><italic>21</italic></xref>). We applied Bayesian statistics to these radiocarbon dates, using the improved regional ceramic sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22"><italic>22</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23"><italic>23</italic></xref>). Out of 10 significant cultural features excavated in complexes E and G near the La Venta ceremonial core, 9 belong to the Franco ceramic phase (800 to 400 BCE), characterized by composite-silhouette bowls and plates (round bases and walls that are straight or curve out), black serving vessels, and hatched triangles and other incised or grooved motifs (figs. S5 and S6 and table S2). These results support the interpretation that the population of La Venta grew rapidly after 800 BCE. The construction of La Venta&#x2019;s ceremonial core may have started earlier (fig. S7 and table S3), but before 800 BCE La Venta was probably a smaller, less influential center and may have had mutually stimulating interactions with Ceibal and other contemporaneous communities. These dates also indicate that there was a substantial gap between the decline of San Lorenzo and the growth of its successor. The interpretation of San Lorenzo&#x2019;s fall has been equally uncertain, although the date of 1000 BCE has traditionally been used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). However, a Bayesian model of available dates suggests that San Lorenzo&#x2019;s heyday more likely ended around 1150 BCE (figs. S8 and S9 and table S4). Moreover, archaeological data from central Chiapas and the Chiapas Pacific Coast, as well as the Bayesian statistics of radiocarbon dates from there (figs. S10 and S11 and table S5), indicate that the influence of San Lorenzo diminished around this date (the end of the Cuadros phase on the Pacific Coast and that of the Cacahuan&#x00F3; phase in the western Grijalva River basin) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19"><italic>19</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24"><italic>24</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25"><italic>25</italic></xref>). The establishment of formal ceremonial spaces and their growth into plaza-pyramid complexes probably occurred during this transitional period between the two Gulf Coast powers.</p>
<p>An important area for the development of ceremonial complexes was probably central Chiapas along the Grijalva River. Clark, following McDonald and Lowe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26"><italic>26</italic></xref>), noted that Middle Preclassic centers in this region, including Mirador, San Isidro, Ocozocoautla, Chiapa de Corzo, Finca Acapulco, and La Libertad, as well as Tzutzuculi on the Pacific Coast, shared highly standardized spatial plans, each consisting of an E-Group assemblage and large platforms placed along the north-south axis of the settlements. This configuration, which Clark called the Middle Formative Chiapas (MFC) pattern, closely resembles that of Ceibal. Many of the MFC-pattern complexes, including those at Tzutzuculi, Mirador, San Isidro, and La Libertad, were not constructed until 800 or 700 BCE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26"><italic>26</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29"><italic>29</italic></xref>). The E-Group assemblage at Chiapa de Corzo may be slightly earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30"><italic>30</italic></xref>). Excavations also suggest that, at the beginning of the Middle Preclassic, the central part of Chiapa de Corzo was leveled off, and scraped surface soils along with remains of the Early Preclassic period were dumped to the slope near the ceremonial core (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31"><italic>31</italic></xref>). This means that the early residents of Chiapa de Corzo and Ceibal shared similar manners of preparing the areas at the onset of ceremonial constructions, apparently emphasizing a break from the previous era. The excavation results of Finca Acapulco have not been fully described, but it is possible that this site with significant Early Preclassic occupations had ceremonial constructions contemporaneous with those of Ceibal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25"><italic>25</italic></xref>). An even earlier plaza-pyramid complex may have existed on the Chiapas Pacific Coast. During the Jocotal phase (1200 to 1000 BCE), when the influence of San Lorenzo weakened, a series of extensive mounds were constructed near estuaries, but the most impressive was Ojo de Agua in an inland area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32"><italic>32</italic></xref>). Its pyramids, substantial platforms, and plazas exhibit a vague resemblance to the MFC pattern. The southern Pacific Coast had a tradition of building residences on raised platforms associated with plazas dating back at least to the Locona phase (1600 to 1500 BCE) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33"><italic>33</italic></xref>). However, during the Cuadros phase (1350 to 1200 BCE), when influence from San Lorenzo was notable, the largest community of the area, Cant&#x00F3;n Corralito, adopted San Lorenzo&#x2013;like constructions lacking tall mounds but consisting of an extensive low terrace that supported residential buildings with low foundations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24"><italic>24</italic></xref>). This sequence suggests that the plaza-pyramid complex of Ojo de Agua did not derive from the Gulf Coast. During the following Conchas phase (1000 to 600 BCE), the center of La Blanca across the Guatemalan border grew, with a large pyramid, mound 1, eventually reaching a height of 25 m. The date of La Blanca mound 1 remains problematic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34"><italic>34</italic></xref>). Its monumental construction may predate those at Ceibal and La Venta or may be contemporaneous with them.</p>
<p>It is well documented in North and South America that monumental architecture could be built long before the emergence of centralized polities and marked social inequality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35"><italic>35</italic></xref>). Critical issues in this study then are not only the sizes of buildings but also the social roles that buildings and spaces played in specific historical contexts. The data from Ceibal make it clear that the original emphasis was on the ceremonial complex as a stage for communal ritual performances. Pyramids resulted from a sequence of architectural renovations applied to original platforms and possibly provided spatial settings for more marked segregations among community members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36"><italic>36</italic></xref>). The emergence of standardized ceremonial complexes exemplified by the E-Group assemblage and the MFC pattern were possibly associated with increasingly prescribed forms of interactions and shared notions of new social order (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37"><italic>37</italic></xref>). The sequential architectural development at Ceibal implies that this center was not a passive recipient of an idea established elsewhere, but it most likely participated actively in the process of this innovation. This development appears to have occurred through interregional interactions, primarily involving groups in the southwestern Maya lowlands, Chiapas, the Pacific Coast, and the southern Gulf Coast. Then around 800 to 400 BCE, plaza-pyramid complexes spread to other parts of southern Mesoamerica, including the central Maya lowlands, the Guatemalan highlands, El Salvador, and Honduras. The residents of highland Mexico, including the Basin of Mexico, Morelos, and Oaxaca, built substantial platforms during the Early Preclassic period, but they were slow to adopt pyramidal architecture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38"><italic>38</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40"><italic>40</italic></xref>). These observations indicate that the origins of lowland Maya civilization can be explained neither in terms of Gulf Coast Olmec influence nor independent development. One-directional influence from La Venta was probably not significant at the beginning of the Middle Preclassic period, but interactions with and inspirations from the area to the west were still critical for social changes in the Maya lowlands.</p>
</body>
<back><app-group><app>
<title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/340/6131/467/DC1">www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/340/6131/467/DC1</ext-link></p>
<p>Materials and Methods</p>
<p>Figs. S1 to S11</p>
<p>Tables S1 to S5</p>
<p>References (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41"><italic>41</italic></xref><italic>&#x2013;</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67"><italic>67</italic></xref>)</p></supplementary-material></app></app-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="book">J. E. Clark, D. Cheetham, in <italic>Archaeology of Tribal Societies</italic>, W. A. Parkinson, Ed. (International Monographs in Prehistory, Ann Arbor, MI, 2002), pp. 278&#x2013;339.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="book">M. D. Coe, R. A. Diehl, <italic>The Land of the Olmec</italic> (Univ. of Texas Press, Austin, TX, 1980).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="book">A. Cyphers, A. Di Castro, in <italic>Art of Urbanism: How Mesoamerican Kingdoms Represented Themselves in Architecture and Imagery</italic>, W. L. Fash, L. L&#x00F3;pez Luj&#x00E1;n, Eds. (Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection, Washington, DC, 2009), pp. 21&#x2013;52.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="book">M. D. Coe, in <italic>Origins of Maya Civilization</italic>, R. E. W. Adams, Ed. (Univ. of New Mexico Press, Albuquerque, NM, 1977), pp. 183&#x2013;195.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="book">J. E. Clark, R. D. Hansen, in <italic>Royal Courts of the Ancient Maya, Volume 2: Data and Case Studies</italic>, T. Inomata, S. D. Houston, Eds. (Westview Press, Boulder, CO, 2001), pp. 1&#x2013;45.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blomster</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neff</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glascock</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Olmec pottery production and export in ancient Mexico determined through elemental analysis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>307</volume>, 
<fpage>1068</fpage> (<year>2005</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1107599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15718462</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="book">F. Estrada Belli, <italic>The First Maya Civilization: Ritual and Power Before the Classic Period</italic> (Routledge, London, 2011).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Cultura hermana: Reappraising the Olmec</article-title>. <source>Quart. Rev. Archaeol.</source> 
<volume>9</volume>, 
<fpage>1</fpage> (<year>1989</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="book">R. D. Hansen, in <italic>New Perspectives on Formative Mesoamerican Cultures</italic>, T. G. Powis, Ed., vol. 1377 of <italic>BAR International Series</italic> (Archaeopress, Oxford, 2005), pp. 51&#x2013;72.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="book">A. Cyphers, in <italic>Olmec to Aztec: Settlement Patterns in the Ancient Gulf Lowlands</italic>, B. L. Stark, P. J. Arnold III, Eds. (Univ. of Arizona Press, Tucson, AZ, 1997), pp. 96&#x2013;114.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="book">G. W. Lowe, in <italic>The Origins of Maya Civilization</italic>, R. E. W. Adams, Ed. (Univ. of New Mexico Press, Albuquerque, NM, 1977), pp. 197&#x2013;248.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="book">G. R. Willey, A. L. Smith, G. Tourtellot III, I. Graham, <italic>Excavations at Seibal, Department of Peten, Guatemala: Introduction: The Site and Its Setting</italic> (Harvard Univ., Cambridge, MA, 1975).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="book">J. A. Sabloff, <italic>Excavations at Seibal, Department of Peten, Guatemala: Ceramics</italic> (Harvard Univ., Cambridge, MA, 1975).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="book">N. Hammond, Ed., <italic>Cuello: An Early Maya Community in Belize</italic> (Cambridge Univ. Press, Cambridge, 1991).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="book">J. F. Garber, M. K. Brown, J. Awe, C. J. Hartman, in <italic>The Ancient Maya of the Belize Valley: Half a Century of Archaeological Research</italic>, J. F. Garber, Ed. (Univ. Press of Florida, Gainesville, FL, 2004), pp. 25&#x2013;47.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="book">P. F. Healy, J. J. Awe, Eds., <italic>Belize Valley Preclassic Maya Project: Report on the 1994 Field Season</italic> (Department of Anthropology, Trent Univ., Peterborough, Ontario, Canada, 1995).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laporte</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fialko</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Reencuentro con Mundo Perdido, Tikal, Guatemala</article-title>. <source>Ancient Mesoamerica.</source> 
<volume>6</volume>, 
<fpage>41</fpage> (<year>1995</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0956536100002108</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Archaic origins of the lowland Maya</article-title>. <source>Latin Am. Antiquity.</source> 
<volume>21</volume>, 
<fpage>312</fpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7183/1045-6635.21.3.312</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="book">J. E. Clark, M. E. Pye, in <italic>Olmec Art and Archaeology in Mesoamerica</italic>, J. E. Clark, M. E. Pye, Eds. (National Gallery of Art, Washington, DC, 2000), pp. 217&#x2013;251.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="book">R. M. Rosenswig, <italic>The Beginnings of Mesoamerican Civilization: Inter-Regional Interaction and the Olmec</italic> (Cambridge Univ. Press, Cambridge, 2010).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="thesis">W. F. Rust, thesis, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA (2008).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="thesis">C. L. von Nagy, thesis, Tulane University, New Orleans, LA (2003).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="book">R. Gonz&#x00E1;lez Lauck, in <italic>Olmec Art of Ancient Mexico</italic>, E. P. Benson, B. de la Fuente, Eds. (National Gallery of Art, Washington, DC, 1996), pp. 73&#x2013;82.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="thesis">D. Cheetham, thesis, Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ (2010).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="book">G. Lowe, in <italic>Archaeology, Art, and Ethnogenesis in Mesoamerican Prehistory: Papers in Honor of Gareth W. Lowe</italic>, L. S. Lowe, M. E. Pye, Eds. (Brigham Young Univ., Provo, UT, 2007), pp. 63&#x2013;108.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="book">A. J. McDonald, <italic>Tzutzuculi: A Middle-Preclassic Site on the Pacific Coast of Chiapas, Mexico</italic> (New World Archaeological Foundation, Brigham Young Univ., Provo, Utah, 1983).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="book">P. Agrinier, <italic>Mound 27 and the Middle Preclassic Period at Mirador, Chiapas, Mexico</italic> (Brigham Young Univ., Provo, UT, 2000).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="book">D. B. Bryant, J. E. Clark, D. Cheetham, <italic>Ceramic Sequence of the Upper Grijalva Region, Chiapas, Mexico</italic> (Brigham Young Univ., Provo, UT, 2005).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="book">G. W. Lowe, in <italic>The Olmec and Their Neighbors</italic>, M. D. Coe, D. Grove, Eds. (Dumbarton Oaks, Washington, DC, 1981), pp. 231&#x2013;256.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="book">L. Lowe, in <italic>XXV Simposio de Investigaciones Arqueol&#x00F3;gicas en Guatemala, 2011,</italic> B. Arroyo, L. Paiz, H. Mej&#x00ED;a, Eds. (Ministerio de Cultura y Deportes, Instituto de Antropolog&#x00ED;a e Historia, and Asociaci&#x00F3;n Tikal, Guatemala, 2012), pp. 285&#x2013;292.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="book">G. W. Lowe, P. Agrinier, <italic>Mound 1, Chiapa de Corzo, Chiapas, Mexico</italic> (Brigham Young Univ., Provo, UT, 1960).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallaga Murrieta</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Ojo de Agua Monument 3: A new Olmec-style sculpture from Ojo de Agua, Chiapas, Mexico</article-title>. <source>Mexicon</source> 
<volume>32</volume>, 
<fpage>139</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="book">J. E. Clark, in <italic>Mesoamerican Archaeology: Theory and Practice</italic>, R. A. Joyce, J. A. Hendon, Eds. (Blackwell, Malden, MA, 2004), pp. 43&#x2013;72.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="book">M. Love, <italic>Early Complex Society in Pacific Guatemala: Settlements and Chronology of the R&#x00ED;o Naranjo, Guatemala</italic> (Brigham Young Univ., Provo, UT, 2002).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="book">R. L. Burger, R. M. Rosenswig, Eds., <italic>Early New World Monumentality</italic> (Univ. Press of Florida, Gainsville, FL, 2012).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Unintended consequences?: Monumentality as a novel experience in Formative Mesoamerica</article-title>. <source>J. Archaeol. Method Theory.</source> 
<volume>11</volume>, 
<fpage>5</fpage> (<year>2004</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:JARM.0000014346.87569.4a</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="book">M. W. Love, in <italic>Social Patterns in Pre-Classic Meosamerica</italic>, D. C. Grove, R. A. Joyce, Eds. (Dumbarton Oaks, Washington, DC, 1999), pp. 127&#x2013;153.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="book">B. Barba de Pi&#x00F1;a Chan, <italic>Tlapacoya: Los Principios de la Teocracia en la Cuenca de M&#x00E9;xico</italic> (Biblioteca Enciclop&#x00E9;dica del Estado de M&#x00E9;xico, M&#x00E9;xico, D.F., M&#x00E9;xico, 1980).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="book">D. C. Grove, <italic>Ancient Chalcatzingo</italic> (Univ. of Texas Press, Austin, TX, 1987).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R40"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="book">J. Marcus, K. V. Flannery, <italic>Zapotec Civilization: How Urban Society Evolved in Mexico's Oaxaca Valley</italic> (Thames and Hudson, New York, 1996).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R41"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="web">C. Bronk Ramsey, OxCal. <bold>4.1.7</bold> (2011); available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://c14.arch.ox.ac.uk/embed.php?File=oxcal.html">http://c14.arch.ox.ac.uk/embed.php?File=oxcal.html</ext-link>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R42"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>IntCal09 and Marine09 radiocarbon age calibration curves, 0&#x2013;50,000 years cal BP</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> 
<volume>51</volume>, 
<fpage>1111</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R43"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Atley</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Protsch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willey</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Radiocarbon chronology for Seibal, Guatemala</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>252</volume>, 
<fpage>472</fpage> (<year>1974</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/252472a0</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R44"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>A multi-proxy study of Holocene environmental change in the Maya lowlands of Peten, Guatemala</article-title>. <source>J. Paleolimnol.</source> 
<volume>19</volume>, 
<fpage>139</fpage> (<year>1998</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1007968508262</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R45"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodell</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Possible role of climate in the collapse of Classic Maya civilization</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>375</volume>, 
<fpage>391</fpage> (<year>1995</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/375391a0</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R46"><label>46</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islebe</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooghiemstra</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodell</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A Holocene vegetation history from lowland Guatemala</article-title>. <source>Holocene</source> 
<volume>6</volume>, 
<fpage>265</fpage> (<year>1996</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/095968369600600302</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R47"><label>47</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodell</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Climate variability on the Yucatan Peninsula (Mexico) during the past 3500 years, and implications for Maya cultural evolution</article-title>. <source>Quat. Res.</source> 
<volume>46</volume>, 
<fpage>37</fpage> (<year>1996</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/qres.1996.0042</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R48"><label>48</label><citation citation-type="book">L. E. Wright, <italic>Diet, Health, and Status among the Pasi&#x00F3;n Maya: A Reappraisal of the Collapse</italic> (Vanderbilt Univ. Press, Nashville, TN, 2006).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R49"><label>49</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>K. O.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Origin and environmental setting of ancient agriculture in the lowlands of Mesoamerica</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>292</volume>, 
<fpage>1370</fpage> (<year>2001</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.292.5520.1370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11359011</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R50"><label>50</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raab</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boxt</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x00E1;lez Lauck</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Testing at Isla Alor in the La Venta Olmec hinterland</article-title>. <source>J. Field Archaeol.</source> 
<volume>27</volume>, 
<fpage>257</fpage> (<year>2000</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/530442</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R51"><label>51</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raab</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boxt</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x00E1;lez Lauck</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Investigaciones arqueol&#x00F3;gicas en &#x201C;Isla&#x201D; Alor: Un sitio en el &#x00E1;rea de sostenimiento de La Venta, Tabasco</article-title>. <source>Arqueolog&#x00ED;a</source> 
<volume>26</volume>, 
<fpage>3</fpage> (<year>2001</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R52"><label>52</label><citation citation-type="thesis">E. B. Sisson, thesis, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA (1976).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R53"><label>53</label><citation citation-type="thesis">R. Gonz&#x00E1;lez Lauck, thesis, Univ. of California, Berkeley, CA (1990).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R54"><label>54</label><citation citation-type="book">P. Drucker, R. F. Heizer, R. H. Squier, <italic>Excavations at La Venta, Tabasco</italic> (Smithsonian Institution, Washington, DC, 1959).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R55"><label>55</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drucker</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heizer</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Squier</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Radiocarbon dates from La Venta, Tabasco</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>126</volume>, 
<fpage>72</fpage> (<year>1957</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.126.3263.72</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17792925</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R56"><label>56</label><citation citation-type="book">R. Berger, J. A. Graham, R. F. Heizer, in <italic>Studies in Olmec Archaeology</italic> (Univ. of California, Berkeley, CA, 1967), pp. 1&#x2013;24.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R57"><label>57</label><citation citation-type="book">R. F. Heizer, P. Drucker, J. A. Graham, in <italic>Papers on Mesoamerican Archaeology</italic> (Univ. of California, Berkeley, CA, 1968), pp. 1&#x2013;34.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R58"><label>58</label><citation citation-type="book">R. F. Heizer, J. A. Graham, L. K. Napton, in <italic>Papers on Mesoamerican Archaeology</italic> (Univ. of California, Berkeley, CA, 1968), pp. 127&#x2013;203.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R59"><label>59</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stuiver</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Yale natural radiocarbon measurements IX</article-title>. <source>Radiocarbon</source> 
<volume>11</volume>, 
<fpage>545</fpage> (<year>1969</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R60"><label>60</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Radiocarbon chronology for the Late Archaic and Formative periods on the Pacific Coast of southeastern Mesoamerica</article-title>. <source>Ancient Mesoamerica.</source> 
<volume>6</volume>, 
<fpage>161</fpage> (<year>1995</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0956536100002169</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R61"><label>61</label><citation citation-type="book">M. Love, in <italic>Incidents of Archaeology in Central America and Yucat&#x00E1;n: Essays in Honor of Edwin M. Shook</italic>, M. Love, M. Popenoe de Hatch, H. L. Escobedo, Eds. (Univ. Press of America, Lanham, MD, 2002), pp. 51&#x2013;74.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R62"><label>62</label><citation citation-type="book">M. Blake, R. G. Lesure, in <italic>Settlement and Subsistence in Early Formative Soconusco: El Varal and the Problem of Inter-site Assemblage Variation</italic>, R. G. Lesure, Ed. (Cotsen Institute of Archaeology, Univ. of California, Los Angeles, CA, 2009), pp. 171&#x2013;172.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R63"><label>63</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Excavations at El Remolino: Household archaeology in the San Lorenzo Olmec region</article-title>. <source>J. Field Archaeol.</source> 
<volume>30</volume>, 
<fpage>163</fpage> (<year>2005</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1179/009346905791072378</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R64"><label>64</label><citation citation-type="thesis">M. Aguilar Rojas, thesis, Universidad las Americas, Cholula, Puebla, Mexico (1992).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R65"><label>65</label><citation citation-type="thesis">L. Gregor L&#x00F3;pez, thesis, Escuela Nacional de Antropolog&#x00ED;a e Historia, M&#x00E9;xico, D.F., Mexico (1999).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R66"><label>66</label><citation citation-type="thesis">M. I. Pajonares Gonz&#x00E1;lez, thesis, Universidad Veracruzana, Xalapa, Veracruz, Mexico (1999).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R67"><label>67</label><citation citation-type="book">M. E. Pye, A. A. Demarest, B. Arroyo, in <italic>Prehistory: The Evolution of Archaic and Formative Cultures</italic>, M. Blake, Ed. (Washington State Univ. Press, Pullman, WA, 1999), pp. 75&#x2013;88.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Investigations at Ceibal were carried out with permits generously issued by the Instituto de Antropolog&#x00ED;a e Historia de Guatemala. We thank its directors, el Maestro Erick Ponciano and la Licenciada Ivon Putzey. Investigations at Ceibal were supported by the National Geographic Society; NSF (grant BCS-0750808); the National Endowment for the Humanities (grant RZ-51209-10); Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology&#x2013;Japan KAKENHI (grants 21101003 and 21101002); Japan Society for the Promotion of Science KAKENHI (grant 21402008); and the Alphawood Foundation. We thank B. Bachand, J. Hodgson, M. Love, M. Pye, and R. Rosenswig for information on their radiocarbon dates and excavations and W. Andrews and J. Clark for comments.</p>
</ack></back>
</article>