<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Anatomy</subject><subject>Anthropology</subject><subject>Paleontology</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ANTHRO</subject><subject>PALEO</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>American Association of Physical Anthropologists | 9&#x2013;13 April | Knoxville, Tennessee</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>When Early Hominins Got a Grip</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>Ann</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>26</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6131</issue>
<fpage seq="a">426</fpage>
<lpage>427</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Paleoanthropologists announced a modern feature in a rare, 1.4-million-year-old hand bone from Kenya, filling a 1-million-year gap in the fossil record and showing when key adaptations to toolmaking arose. </p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Paleoanthropologists announced a modern feature in a rare, 1.4-million-year-old hand bone from Kenya, filling a 1-million-year gap in the fossil record and showing when key adaptations to toolmaking arose. </p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Old hand.</title>
<p>The point at the bottom tip of this bone suggests its owner could grip tools precisely.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_426a_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: MATT TOCHERI AND CAROL WARD</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Human ancestors were handy, crafting stone tools as early as 2.7 million years ago. But back then their hands lacked the crucial adaptations for tool use seen in living people. About 1.7 million years ago, hominins found a way to make a better tool, and anthropologists have long suspected that they needed a different kind of hand to match. But the fragile bones of the hand are rarely preserved in the fossil record. At the meetings, paleoanthropologist Carol Ward of the University of Missouri, Columbia, announced a modern feature in a rare 1.4-million-year-old hand bone from Kenya, filling a 1-million-year gap in the fossil record and showing when key adaptations to toolmaking arose. "The changes in the hand seem to be occurring much earlier in time [than fossils showed before] and are associated with the evolution of <italic>Homo erectus</italic>," Ward said in her talk.</p>

<p>About 1.7 million years ago, <italic>H. erectus</italic> began to make tear-shaped hand axes in the so-called Acheulean style, in which the blade is flaked symmetrically on both sides. This was a vast improvement over the simple choppers and flakes of the earlier Oldowan style and suggested that hominins were getting more dexterous with tools. But changes in the hand bones have been more obscure. No one has known just when our ancestors developed a complex of changes in the bones at the bases of the thumb, index, and third finger that allow a forceful precision grip. That grip, in which the fingertips and thumb press against an object in the grasp, such as a hand axe, is anatomically demanding: The hand has to curve to grip the tool, but it also has to stiffen at the base of the thumb and in the midhand, to stabilize the hand and dissipate force.</p>
<p>Modern humans and Neandertals have this complex of traits, as does the 800,000-year-old <italic>H. antecessor</italic> from Atapuerca, Spain. But members of <italic>Australopithecus</italic>, which lived about 1.9 million to 4 million years ago, do not. Thus, this refined precision grip arose sometime between 1.9 million years ago and 800,000 years ago. But when? No one knew, because no fragile hand bones had been discovered during this time. "There's a huge gap of 1 million years in the fossil record for hands," Ward says.</p>
<p>Then, in 2010, paleoanthropologist Fredrick Kyalo Manthi of the National Museums of Kenya in Nairobi found a bone at the newly discovered site of Kaitio on the edge of Lake Turkana in Kenya. The bone, the third metacarpal, sits in the middle in the hand, extending from the knuckle of the third finger to the wrist. Although it is just a single bone, it has a key feature&#x2014;a bony point or styloid process&#x2014;at the bottom. This point is "associated with making and using tools," Ward says, because it buttresses other bones to stabilize them and so allows a forceful precision grip.</p>
<p>Ward's team can't say for sure which <italic>Homo</italic> species the bone represents, but they suspect that it was large-bodied <italic>H. erectus</italic>, our direct ancestor, who lived near Lake Turkana during this time and is thought to have left the Acheulean tools. The bone was larger than the same bone in the hand of co-author J. Michael Plavcan of the University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, "who has really big hands," Ward notes, implying a big individual.</p>
<p>The fossil shows that by the time the Acheulean was well established, the precision grip was, too. "The discovery is significant because it corroborates evidence from other parts of the hand that the hominin hand may have become adapted to stone toolmaking with the appearance of the Acheulean," says paleoanthropologist Mary Marzke of Arizona State University, Tempe, who was not a co-author.</p>
</body>
</article>