<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="other" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>New Products</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Products &amp; Materials</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>products</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subject>Immunology</subject><subject>Virology</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>New Products</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>26</day><month>04</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6131</issue>
<fpage seq="a">499</fpage>
<lpage>499</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>A weekly roundup of information on newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of potential interest to researchers.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary">
<p>A weekly roundup of information on newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of potential interest to researchers.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>GEL DOCUMENTATION SYSTEM </title>
<fig id="F1" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="340_499a_F1"><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text></graphic></fig>
<p>A new lightweight, portable gel documentation system enables visualization of real-time size fractionation of nucleic acids. The runDOC gel documentation system is designed exclusively for use with the innovative runVIEW system and comprises a darkroom hood and a 10 megapixel digital camera to capture images of nucleic acids gels stained with EtBr, SYBR, and runSAFE. RunDOC is designed to be placed directly over the RVMSCHOICE gel tank located on the runVIEW base unit, which includes an integrated power supply and blue LED gel illuminator. The blue LED gel illuminator provides the excitation source for the DNA gel located within the tank and following excitation the light emitted is then visualized using either one of the bluVIEW lid options supplied with runVIEW, or the runDOC filter slide. In addition to being lightweight, runDOC has a small footprint and so requires only minimal space within the laboratory. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Cleaver Scientific </bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: +44-(0)-1788-565300      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cleaverscientific.com">www.cleaverscientific.com</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>AUTOMATED BIOLOGICAL SAMPLE CARD PUNCHING </title>
<p>The easyPunch STARlet workstation is the first fully automated system integrating sample card punching and liquid handling into one easy workflow. The easyPunch STARlet system seamlessly integrates punching of GE Healthcare Whatman FTATM and DMPK sample collection cards with automated sample extraction, eliminating common bottlenecks in laboratory processes. The system minimizes human error and enables high throughput sample preparation for a variety of applications, such as forensic reference databasing as well as preclinical and clinical drug metabolism and pharmacokinetics (DMPK) and toxicology studies. The easyPunch workstation is based on the Hamilton Robotics Microlab STARlet platform and features two special modules and robotic arms for transporting and punching paper cards. The samples are monitored by powerful tracking software to eliminate any chance of sample identification errors. The entire process is tracked using imaging recognition. Hamilton's proprietary software, based on industrial machine vision technology, provides complete control and monitoring of the punching process. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Hamilton Robotics</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-648-5950      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hamiltonrobotics.com">www.hamiltonrobotics.com</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<p>The new Eppendorf &#x3BC;Cuvette G1.0 is designed for the accurate and reliable measurement of small volumes of highly concentrated biomolecules, such as proteins and nucleic acids. Users can work easily with samples as small as 1.5 &#x3BC;L without the need for a time-consuming dilution step. The &#x3BC;Cuvette G1.0 expands the measuring range of the Eppendorf BioPhotometer and the Eppendorf BioSpectrometer. Synchronized apertures mean that a closed system is created when used alongside Eppendorf detection instruments, for optimum results and reliable operation. Higher sample concentrations require a shorter optical path length for measurement. The optical path length of the &#x3BC;Cuvette G1.0 is just 1 mm, 10 times shorter than the light path length of standard cuvettes. This provides a better system for measurements at high concentrations.</p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Eppendorf</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-645-3050      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eppendorf.com">www.eppendorf.com</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>CELL-BASED ASSAY SYSTEM</title>
<p>The new iCELLigence system is a unique, impedance-based system for cell-based assays, allowing for label-free and real-time monitoring of cellular processes such as cell growth, proliferation, cytotoxicity, adhesion, morphological dynamics, and modulation of barrier function. The system is composed of an electronic analyzer that fits inside the cell culture incubator, and an iPad which runs the software and operates the entire system in a wireless mode. At the core of the system are electronic plates (E-Plates L8) that have integrated microelectrode sensors in the bottom of the wells. The presence or absence of cells sensitively and precisely affects the electronic and ionic exchange between cell culture media and the microelectrodes when an electric field is applied to the system. Changes in electrical impedance reflect the biological status of the cells, thus the system allows monitoring of time-dependent perturbation effects in a tissue culture environment, providing dynamic information. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>ACEA Biosciences </bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 866-308-2232      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aceabio.com">www.aceabio.com</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>HOST CELL PROTEIN ANTIBODIES </title>
<p>Host Cell Protein (HCP) antibodies detect high, medium, and low molecular weight proteins. Host Cell Proteins are process-related impurities derived from a host cell expression system that may be present in trace amounts in a final drug substance. HCP antibodies are used to detect impurities in biologically based therapeutics. Assays are further developed using custom-manufactured process-specific antibodies. ELISA, the most widely used assay for determining the presence of HCPs, uses a polyclonal antibody mixture raised against host cell proteins. The accepted workflow for evaluating the immunocoverage of HCP antibodies involves 2-D gel electrophoresis followed by Western blotting. Antibodies and custom HCP assay development services are available to streamline and regulate this workflow. The newly developed Rockland antibodies have been fully evaluated using the 2-D electrophoresis workflow and provide efficient immunocoverage of<italic>E. coli</italic>HCP.</p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Rockland Immunochemicals</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 610-369-1008      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rockland-inc.com/hcp.aspx">www.rockland-inc.com/hcp.aspx</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="product-submission-instructions"><p>Electronically submit your new product description or product literature information! Go to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/products/newproducts.dtl">www.sciencemag.org/products/newproducts.dtl</ext-link> for more information.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="disclaimer"><p><italic>Newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of interest to researchers in all disciplines in academic, industrial, and governmental organizations are featured in this space. Emphasis is given to purpose, chief characteristics, and availabilty of products and materials. Endorsement by </italic>Science<italic> or AAAS of any products or materials mentioned is not implied. Additional information may be obtained from the manufacturer or supplier.</italic></p></fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
