<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Anthropology</subject><subject>Anatomy</subject><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ANTHRO</subject><subject>PALEO</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Ardi's a Hominin&#x2014;But How Did She Move?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>Ann</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>26</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6131</issue>
<fpage>427</fpage>
<lpage>427</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>

    <abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Researchers gave Ardi, the oldest and most complete skeleton of a potential human ancestor, new recognition as a hominin. They agreed with the discoverers that Ardi walked upright&#x2014;albeit in a weird way&#x2014;and that features in her teeth and skull make her a primitive member of the human family. But debate raged about whether she also climbed vertically in trees like an ape.</p></abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Researchers gave Ardi, the oldest and most complete skeleton of a potential human ancestor, new recognition as a hominin. They agreed with the discoverers that Ardi walked upright&#x2014;albeit in a weird way&#x2014;and that features in her teeth and skull make her a primitive member of the human family. But debate raged about whether she also climbed vertically in trees like an ape.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Ardi, the oldest and most complete skeleton of a potential human ancestor, has been a leading lady of human evolution ever since she got top billing on the cover of <italic>Science</italic> in 2009. But while everyone praised the completeness of the partial skeleton, some researchers reserved judgment on whether <italic>Ardipithecus ramidus</italic> was actually a hominin, or upright member of the human family.</p>
<p>At the meetings, a series of talks and posters gave Ardi new recognition as a hominin. Researchers who have had their first look at fossils or casts of the 4.4-million-year-old fossils agreed with the discoverers that Ardi walked upright&#x2014;albeit in a weird way&#x2014;and that features in her teeth and skull make her a primitive member of the human family. But debate raged about whether she also climbed vertically in trees like an ape.</p>
    <p>In 2009 (<italic>Science</italic>, 2 October 2009, p. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/326/5949/36.full">36</ext-link>), a team of 47 researchers co-led by Tim White of the University of California, Berkeley, showed that chimp-sized Ardi walked upright, planting her feet flat on the ground. Although she still clung to the safety of trees, the team suggested that she didn't climb vertically or swing through the branches like a chimp, but moved slowly on all fours when on top of branches, with an opposable big toe to grasp limbs. But other researchers continued to debate whether <italic>Ar. ramidus</italic> was part of the human lineage (<italic>Science</italic>, 29 January 2010, p. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/327/5965/532.full">532</ext-link>).</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Making headway.</title>
<p>The bones at the base of Ardi's skull suggest that she had human traits.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_427_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: TIM D. WHITE</attrib>
</fig>
<p>In one talk, William Kimbel of the Institute of Human Origins at Arizona State University, Tempe, working with White's team, used the cranial base&#x2014;the bones that form the base of the inside of the skull, around the opening for the spinal cord&#x2014;to support Ardi's status as a hominin. Kimbel, an expert on Lucy's species, <italic>Australopithecus afarensis</italic>, noted resemblances between that species and Ardi, which is half a million years older but from the same region in Ethiopia. For example, both have a shorter and wider cranial base than an ape's. "What struck me was just how spread out the landmarks were around the center of the cranial base," Kimbel says. "In apes, they are crowded together in the middle." Hominins have a wider base than apes to accommodate a more forward position of the spinal cord.</p>
<p>Others found Kimbel's talk convincing. "When I saw the cranial base, it struck me that it was reasonable as a hominin," says paleoanthropologist Eric Delson of the City University of New York. "Above the neck, I'm convinced."</p>
<p>Below the neck, interpreting Ardi's anatomy is more complicated. The position of one key hand bone, the capitate in the center of the wrist, supports the idea that Ardi's wrist was flexible, allowing her to walk on flat hands and feet atop branches, reported anatomist Michael Selby of the Philadelphia College of Osteopathic Medicine, Georgia Campus, in Suwanee. But that view was challenged by paleoanthropologist Caley Orr of Midwestern University, Downers Grove, in Illinois. Using a 3D analysis of the wrist bones, he found that Ardi's wrist was too rigid to put her weight flat on her hands, suggesting that she moved through the trees in another manner, perhaps by vertical climbing as chimpanzees do.</p>
<p>So while Ardi is on more secure footing as an upright walking hominin, the focus has shifted to what she did off the ground. "The big debate is how it was moving in the trees," says paleoanthropologist Will Harcourt-Smith of the American Museum of Natural History in New York City.</p>
</body>
</article>