<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1237128</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1237128</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Books <italic>et al.</italic></subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>books</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>PHYSICS</subject><subject>ENGINEERING</subject><subject>MAT SCI</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Materials-Science</subject><subject>Astronomy</subject><subject>Engineering</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Exhibitions: Materials Science</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Transit Shadows</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Junier</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Junier</surname><given-names>Pilar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics, Genopode Building, University of Lausanne, CH-1015 Lausanne, Switzerland.</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Laboratory of Microbiology, Institute of Biology, University of Neuch&#x00E2;tel, CH-2009 Neuch&#x00E2;tel, Switzerland.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>pilar.junier@unine.ch</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>26</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6131</issue>
<fpage seq="a">433</fpage>
<lpage>433</lpage>
<product product-type="book"><bold>SUPRA100</bold> Le temps suspendu Mus&#x00E9;um d'Histoire Naturelle Neuch&#x00E2;tel, Neuch&#x00E2;tel, Switzerland. Through 20 May 2013. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.museumneuchatel.ch/new/navigation.php?cat=5">www.museumneuchatel.ch/new/navigation.php?cat=5</ext-link></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>This exhibition celebrating superconductivity features sculptures by Etienne Kr&#xE4;henb&#xFC;hl that reveal fresh mechanical and artistic possibilities of metal alloys.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>This exhibition celebrating superconductivity features sculptures by Etienne Kr&#xE4;henb&#xFC;hl that reveal fresh mechanical and artistic possibilities of metal alloys.</p></abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sherman J. Suter</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Jeff Cook</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The deafening sound of Etienne Kr&#x00E4;henb&#x00FC;hl's <italic>Bing Bang</italic> greets visitors to <italic>SUPRA100</italic>, an exhibition of his work currently at the Museum of Natural History of Neuch&#x00E2;tel. Collaborating with the Swiss National Research Program in Materials with Novel Electronic Properties at the University of Geneva, the artist has found a way to present to the public the prospects of superconductivity, a research domain involved in fields as diverse as medicine, communication, and transport technologies. His sculptures demonstrate fresh ways of exploring the mechanical and artistic possibilities of metal alloys&#x2014;in particular, a superelastic nickel-titanium alloy that he used in many of the pieces on display.</p>
<p><italic>Bing Bang</italic> may be the star of the exhibition, in a more than metaphorical sense. It is an array of 850 iron rods of different lengths, each hanging from a wire. At rest, the structure forms a placid sphere. When squeezed together and suddenly released, however, the work seems to spring to life: its complex oscillations irresistibly evoke breathing or a heartbeat; despite being made of metal, its wobbling shape is uncannily organic. But the work's scope is far greater than the living world: it might as well stand for variable stars or simply the expanding (and contracting) universe. And it chimes. That a seemingly chaotic jumble of iron bars can produce a pleasant sound is a real wonder. Much has been speculated about the music of spheres; through <italic>Bing Bang</italic>'s cosmic music, one can almost hear the fossil radiation. The secret lies in technology: the wires are superelastic, and with ordinary wires the magic disappears.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Etienne Kr&#x00E4;henb&#x00FC;hl's <italic>Bing Bang</italic> (2010).</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_433a_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: &#x00A9; MUSEUM-PHOTOS ALAIN GERMOND</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Pieces such as <italic>Viagra Cube</italic>, which makes an evocative link between temperature and the rigidity of the material, illustrate interplay among temperature, material memory, and artistic expression. Through his association with material scientists, Kr&#x00E4;henb&#x00FC;hl has developed unique pieces that blur the frontier between expression and creation. One of the most impressive ones, <italic>SUPRAsph&#x00E8;re</italic>, consists of a sphere mysteriously floating over a surface that hides the supraconductive engine moving randomly underneath.</p>
<p>After visiting <italic>SUPRA100</italic>, you might wonder if the universe started with the big bang or if it was instead born from the inventive mind of a physicist considering the possibilities of elements and materials. The exhibition reminds us that scientists are hidden artists and that artists can be hidden scientists, too.</p>
</body>
</article>