<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Medicine</subject><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subject>Virology</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ASIA/PACIFIC NEWS</subject><subject>MEDICINE</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Public Enemy Number One</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>26</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6131</issue>
<fpage>422</fpage>
<lpage>425</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>North Korea has one of the highest TB rates outside sub-Saharan Africa and a burgeoning drug-resistance problem. A remarkable unusual collaboration is hoping to turn the tide.</p></abstract>
    <abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Tuberculosis (TB) has skyrocketed in the Democratic People's Republic of Korea (DPRK) during the past 20 years. Offering hope that North Korea can get control of the TB epidemic, DPRK's Ministry of Public Health and Stanford University opened a National Tuberculosis Reference Laboratory in Pyongyang. The effort is a rare example of scientific cooperation between North Korea and the United States and, at a time of heightened tensions, one of DPRK's few active links with the West. Last month, author Richard Stone joined U.S. humanitarian organization Christian Friends of Korea to visit four rural TB rest homes and two facilities in the capital. North Korea may believe that its enemies are poised to strike, but TB is already running rampant across the isolated nation.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Room for hope?</title>
<p>Thanks to donations and preferential grain rations, conditions are improving at the Ryokpo rest home and other TB facilities.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_422_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: R. STONE/<italic>SCIENCE</italic></attrib>
</fig>
<p><bold>UNPA, NORTH KOREA</bold>&#x2014;This village in rugged hills 2 hours south of Pyongyang has had it rough. Last summer, a typhoon wiped out most of its corn crop, and a second windstorm ripped stone tiles from roofs. Clinging to a slope facing the settlement, the Unpa tuberculosis (TB) rest home&#x2014;a tidy gray concrete building with a red roof&#x2014;took a battering. None of the staff members or 46 patients was harmed. But the hurricane-force gales shattered windows of a ward under construction that will house patients infected with multidrug-resistant (MDR) TB and sent its steel roof sailing down the valley. Surveying the damage, Heidi Linton, executive director of Christian Friends of Korea (CFK), a humanitarian organization based in Black Mountain, North Carolina, jots down a list of materials that CFK intends to purchase for the MDR wing. Occasional booms punctuate the stillness: Distant artillery fire as North Korea prepares for what it sees as an inevitable military conflict with the South.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Rough decade.</title>
<p>North Korea is struggling to rein in its TB epidemic.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_422_F2"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: <italic>GLOBAL TUBERCULOSIS REPORT 2012</italic>, WHO</attrib>
</fig>
<p>As war fever reached a frenzied pitch last month, Linton and six other Americans were in the countryside with North Korean scientists and physicians, joining forces against a common enemy: tuberculosis. TB has skyrocketed in the Democratic People's Republic of Korea (DPRK) in the past 20 years, according to the World Health Organization (WHO). Famines in the mid-1990s ignited the epidemic; chronic malnutrition ever since has added fuel to the fire. North Korea now has one of the highest TB incidences outside sub-Saharan Africa.</p>
<p>That makes it unusual. Nearly all other countries with high TB case rates also have high HIV/AIDS rates. HIV suppresses the immune system, allowing TB to flourish. In North Korea, "essentially there is no HIV," says Gary Schoolnik, an infectious disease researcher and physician at Stanford University School of Medicine in Palo Alto, California. "That's why," he says, "the magnitude of the TB problem in North Korea is so surprising." It also means that among infectious diseases, TB is the biggest killer in North Korea; globally, the mycobacterium is number two, after HIV/AIDS.</p>
<p>The TB menace unnerves North Korea's neighbors. China in recent weeks has tightened security along its border with DPRK, reportedly to stem a surge of refugees if conditions on the Korean Peninsula deteriorate. The potential burden is a real concern, says an official with China's health ministry in Beijing. "We're scared to death of its destabilizing effects," he says.</p>
<p>Offering hope that North Korea can get control of the TB epidemic, DPRK's Ministry of Public Health, CFK, and Stanford in October 2010 opened a National Tuberculosis Reference Laboratory (NTRL) in Pyongyang. The effort is a rare example of scientific cooperation between North Korea and the United States and, at a time of heightened tensions, one of DPRK's few active links with the West. NTRL researchers can now diagnose TB cases that are resistant to first-line drug combinations, making it possible to spot patients who need more aggressive therapy. And the lab will soon add capacity to screen for extensively drug-resistant TB, known as XDR&#x2014;the worst strains, some of which are close to impossible to treat. "This is a critical point in the development of their program, says Kathleen England, a Stanford microbiologist who is spending weeks at a time at North Korea's NTRL to help it win international accreditation, as early as 2015. Attaining that gold standard, says Schoolnik, who has been involved in the project since its inception, "would allow North Korea to join the global fight against TB."</p>
<boxed-text content-type="EditorialPromo" id="boxed-text-1">
<title>Slideshow</title>
<boxed-text content-type="sci-custom" id="boxed-text-2">
<p> </p>
</boxed-text>
</boxed-text>
<p>Last month, I joined Linton's team on visits to four rural TB rest homes and two facilities in the capital: NTRL and the pediatric ward of the Pyongyang District #3 TB Prevention Hospital. (The DPRK government cleared my visit as a journalist.) The trip came at a delicate time, as South Korea and the United States were conducting annual military exercises that included stealth bomber flights over South Korea. Angered by a fresh round of U.N. sanctions imposed last month over its third nuclear test, North Korea's response to the drills was to sever hotlines, "scrap" the armistice ending the Korean War, suspend operations at the Kaesong industrial park&#x2014;a joint venture with the South&#x2014;and issue bellicose threats. Last month, state television aired interviews with North Koreans railing against U.S. imperialists and showed leader Kim Jong Un inspecting garrisons and planning military maneuvers. Buses and locomotives were festooned with camouflage netting, and a new propaganda mural in Pyongyang depicts a missile bearing down on Capitol Hill. "I've never seen things ratcheted up so high," says Linton, who has made more than 40 trips to DPRK since 1998 on missions to renovate hospitals and oversee distribution of donated food and materials, mostly in the southwest.</p>
<p>North Korea may believe that its enemies are poised to strike. But TB, one of humanity's most enduring scourges, is already running rampant across the isolated nation.</p>
<sec>
<title>Empty bellies</title>
<p>Along the highway leading south from Pyongyang, work brigades are out in force. One group of villagers is tilling paddies in preparation for transplanting rice shoots later in the spring. Lines of red flags on wooden poles flutter in the breeze, a DPRK way to promote camaraderie. A brigade of women is working on railroad tracks, using their hands to even out gravel between the ties, their bicycles lying haphazardly along the elevated bed. In a field down the road, a line of red signboards, each emblazoned with a white Korean letter, declares "Comrade Kim Jong Un, live 10,000 years!"</p>
<p>At the Unpa TB rest home, Director Ko Gwang Sung invites us into a reception room. One wall shows a painted landscape of fractured granite peaks lapped by ocean waves: "Sea Kumgang," the coastal range of the Diamond Mountains in the southeast. Linton, who has been to Unpa nearly a dozen times, runs through a list of questions that she has prepared for each rest home. She takes the sanatorium's vital signs, quizzing Ko on how many doctors, patients, and beds the sanatorium has; the number of patients with infectious pulmonary TB; and whether drug stocks are sufficient.</p>
    <p>In much of the world, TB is in retreat. A 2012 WHO report notes that new TB cases have been falling for several years; since 1990, the mortality rate has decreased 41%. "[T]he world is on track to achieve the global target of a 50% reduction by 2015," WHO states. North Korea is bucking that trend. In 1994, it reported fewer than 50 cases per 100,000 people&#x2014;a third of the rate of South Korea. By 2011, North Korea's TB incidence had climbed to 374 cases per 100,000 people&#x2014;four times the rates in China and South Korea (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/340/6131/422/F2.expansion.html">graph</ext-link>). Although there "certainly could have been significant underreporting" over the years, Schoolnik says, "I think the increase is real." WHO estimates that among North Korea's 24 million people, there are 91,200 active TB cases. That figure is a stab in the dark. "We are not able to get numbers from everywhere, so we assume the rate is higher," England says. Officials in Pyongyang keep data close to the vest. "Data are not being shared," England says.</p>
<p>Ko, like other Korean TB workers, says that recently improved case detection could explain the stubbornly high incidence. In southwestern DPRK, at least, "cases are leveling off," says Ko, who witnessed how the epidemic began to unfold 2 decades ago. But by no means is there a consensus. "I'm not convinced it's slowing down. We may have a ways to go before we hit the top of that curve," Linton says.</p>
<p>One point of agreement is that the roots of the present crisis lie in an epic famine that North Koreans call the Arduous March. Between 1994 and 1998, hundreds of thousands of Koreans starved to death; hunger-weakened survivors were vulnerable to infections. TB rates "climbed significantly," England says. The bug is everywhere: One out of every three people in the world has a latent TB infection that a healthy immune system usually keeps at bay. But in malnourished people, TB can break out of its cage and multiply in the lungs. A person with untreated pulmonary TB infects 10 to 20 people on average, Schoolnik says.</p>
<p>Across North Korea, county governments oversee collective farms, gather up harvests, ship food to Pyongyang and to army outposts, and dole out what's left to the rest of the population. Linton's team has learned from its recent visits to rest homes that the government has set the grain ration for adult TB patients at 450 grams per day, handed out as corn or rice. The ration "is an improvement over previous years," Linton says. "It tells me that the DPRK government may finally recognize that TB patients should be prioritized in the distribution of food." But full rations are rarely met. Food consumption tends to tail off in spring, as stocks from the previous year dwindle. The lean months last until autumn, after the harvest. Meat is distributed only during holidays, such as last week's anniversary of the birth of Kim Il Sung, the nation's founder. To supplement diets, CFK distributes tons of donated canned meat to TB rest homes, accounting for 20% to 70% of patients' protein consumption. It also sends greenhouse kits, seeds, and soil inoculants.</p>
<p>Another driver of the TB epidemic is an inconsistent drug supply, especially before WHO opened its country office in Pyongyang in 2001. North Korean firms produce at least two drugs used to treat TB&#x2014;isoniazid and streptomycin&#x2014;but quality is uncertain and administration is uncontrolled. Stanford researchers have bought both in hotel convenience stores. The health ministry has no funds to import TB medications, so its supply of reliable drugs now comes primarily from the Stop TB Partnership's Global Drug Facility, which operates out of WHO, and the Eugene Bell Foundation, a humanitarian organization based in Washington, D.C.</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<caption>
<title>A deep bond.</title>
<p>Kim Ha's gift of pheasant eggs touched Heidi Linton.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_422_F3"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDITS: R. STONE/<italic>SCIENCE</italic> (2)</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Poor compliance with therapy has spurred TB rates higher. TB drugs must be taken daily for up to 2 years; abandoning a regimen in midstream breeds resistance and treatment failure. To ensure compliance, health departments around the world have implemented directly observed therapy, short-course, or DOTS, in which health workers watch patients take their medicine. North Korea began practicing DOTS routinely only about 10 years ago.</p>
</sec>
    <sec> <title>Rampant resistance</title> <p>A watershed moment for Linton came in the spring of 2007, on a visit to the Hwangju TB Rest Home. The director, Kim Ha, presented her with several bluish-green pheasant eggs. "His hands were hot with fever," Linton recalls. "He was trying not to cough on us." Ill with TB, Kim had spent 4 days in the hills gathering the eggs&#x2014;the most precious gift he could muster&#x2014;to present to the CFK team. "He needed that protein. His staff, his patients needed that protein, way more than we did. I was in tears," she says. "Some people back in the States ask me why we do this, helping 'those ungrateful people,'" Linton says, voice breaking. She tells them about Kim's gesture. "If that's not gratitude, I don't know what is."</p> <fig id="F4" position="float"> <caption> <title>Mounting toll.</title> <p>A health official logs sputum samples of suspected MDR patients in Unpa.</p> </caption> <graphic xlink:href="340_422_F4" /> <attrib>CREDIT: R. STONE/<italic>SCIENCE</italic></attrib> </fig> <p>Six years later, Kim, 58, is enduring his fifth bout of TB. This time it's MDR. "I was going to retire," he tells Linton, "but the food you sent us gave me the strength to work." After a stint in the army, Kim entered medical school and worked at Hwangju County TB Hospital before being assigned to the rest home. He vows to finish building an MDR ward here at the sanatorium before hanging up his stethoscope. MDR is a burgeoning problem in Hwangju, Kim says: "It's a big worry." He attributes the increase to frail health and poor nutrition, failure to adhere to drug regimens, and heavy alcohol consumption.</p> <p>Linton has a donation just for Kim: three pairs of handmade wool mittens. "The ladies didn't know how big your hands are, so they made these in different sizes," she says. "A lot of people are praying for you." Kim says thanks, and with a wan smile asks whether CFK can also donate a motorcycle.</p> <p>Each day before breakfast, Linton's CFK team gathers in their hotel for devotions. On Sunday mornings, they attend services at one of the three Christian churches in Pyongyang. CFK was founded after evangelist Billy Graham's visits to North Korea in 1992 and 1994 paved the way for Christian groups to come in. "It took a while for us to understand each other," says Schoolnik, who is not Christian. But Linton, he says, has been instrumental. "She has enormous on-the-ground experience and is extremely well-respected," he says. "I'm absolutely sure we could not have worked in North Korea without her."</p> <p>It will take more than prayer to tackle North Korea's MDR problem. DPRK's health ministry estimates that up to 15% of TB patients fail first-line treatment, which suggests that they are actively infected with drug-resistant strains. Based on those figures and drug resistance patterns elsewhere in Asia, North Korea could have as many as 15,000 people with drug-resistant TB, England says. Many, she says, are undiagnosed, untreated, or being treated inappropriately. Few MDR patients are isolated from others in TB wards or from healthy people. In the TB rest homes, "it's worrisome that a patient being treated for drugsusceptible TB could become infected with a drug-resistant strain by being exposed to another patient," says Edward Desmond, head of the mycobacteriology and mycology laboratory section at the California Department of Public Health in Richmond. "In the absence of data on the prevalence of drug resistance, it's impossible to calculate how serious this problem is," says Desmond, who has visited North Korea and worked on the TB project on his own time.</p> <fig id="F5" position="float"> <caption> <title>Lending a hand.</title> <p>CFK has distributed greenhouses and water systems to TB rest homes.</p> </caption> <graphic xlink:href="340_422_F5" /> <attrib>CREDIT: R. STONE/<italic>SCIENCE</italic></attrib> </fig> <p>Paek Myong Hwa, director of the Suan TB rest home, says that in his region the number of suspected MDR cases is "stable," but that patient health "is getting worse." Scientists can only guess which strains are circulating. "We have no idea what the drug-resistance patterns are," England says. One of her main tasks these days is to help NTRL researchers implement drug-susceptibility tests, or DSTs. "As soon as they can independently do their DSTs, it will be a big step," she says.</p> <p>Even for top-notch public health systems, MDR is a heavy burden; therapy lasts 2 years and costs as much as 200 times that of the four-drug combo used to vanquish susceptible strains. Modern care cannot prevent one in five MDR or XDR patients from succumbing to the disease. Since 2008, the Eugene Bell Foundation has taken the lead on MDR in North Korea; it sends sputum samples from suspected MDR patients to Seoul for DST panels, and it tailors drug regimens to individuals. MDR patients are treated at district-level rest homes. But it can take days or weeks before they get appropriate MDR drugs, and there aren't nearly enough of these to go around. During that gap, some rest homes give suspected MDR patients traditional medicine, such as a tincture of <italic>wonchuri</italic>, or day lily.</p> <p>As North Korea's TB epidemic gained momentum, the need for a modern lab for diagnoses and uncovering drug-resistance grew more urgent. By 2008, North Korea was the only country with a high TB burden lacking a modern facility for culturing the bug and probing drug resistance. In January that year, the Stanford-led Bay Area TB Consortium hosted a delegation from DPRK's health ministry; later, the Nuclear Threat Initiative awarded the consortium a grant to purchase state-of-the art equipment to establish an NTRL at District #3 TB Prevention Hospital in Pyongyang (<italic>Science</italic>, 12 March 2010, p. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/327/5971/1312.2.full">1312</ext-link>). Others that have pitched in to keep it going include the Richard Lounsbery Foundation, the Walter H. Shorenstein Asia-Pacific Research Center, and Zero TB World.</p> <p>Work on the lab never broke stride, even during acute political tensions that followed DPRK missile and nuclear tests, military drills, the sinking of South Korea's <italic>Cheonan</italic> naval vessel in March 2010, and the North's shelling of Yeonpyeong Island that November, which killed four South Koreans. "Our North Korean colleagues have overcome tremendous odds," Linton says.</p> </sec>
<sec>
<title>One step forward</title>
<p>In a room with negative air pressure to prevent airborne microbes from escaping, a reed-thin technician, Kim Myong Hyok, reaches into a centrifuge and removes plastic Falcon tubes from a bucket one by one. In each tube is a sample of sputum that had been treated with n-acetyl cysteine to break up the mucus and sodium hydroxide to kill off microbial flora other than mycobacteria. Malachite green, added to inhibit fungal growth, gives the samples an alien look.</p>
<p>After moving the centrifuge tubes to a biosafety cabinet, Kim takes one and decants off the supernatant, then dilutes the pellet in phosphate buffer. ("pH is important. Many little nuances are important," England says.) Kim pipettes some of the suspension onto the surface of a greenish gel in a test tube. Mycobacteria thrive on the Lowenstein-Jensen medium, a protein-rich goo made from antibiotic-free eggs. Another portion of the sample will later be smeared on a slide. "In the beginning here we used old-school, acid-fast staining," England says. They've since graduated to a fluorescent stain that lights up the bacterial rods bright yellow.</p>
<fig id="F6" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Identifying gaps.</title>
<p>"We have no idea what the drug-resistance patterns are," says Kathleen England, beside an NTRL sample incubator.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_422_F6"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: R. STONE/<italic>SCIENCE</italic></attrib>
</fig>
<p>The fact that this scene could be happening in any modern TB lab anywhere in the world is encouraging to England. She cut her teeth in the region in Zhengzhou, China, where from 2010 to 2011 she trained TB researchers involved in a U.S.-sponsored clinical trial. She next spent a year in Ulaanbaatar, where she designed labs for Doctors Without Borders and assisted Mongolia's National TB Reference Laboratory. The stint revealed to her the extent to which the disease blights impoverished communities in developing countries to this day. "Mongolia opened my eyes," she says.</p>
<p>England's role in Pyongyang is broader still. Besides training NTRL's 14 staff members, she is assisting the lab in strengthening diagnostics, establishing quality assurance for lab activities, planning a drug resistance survey, developing regional labs with WHO, and preparing for accreditation. "The lab is a big help for our people," says Kim Hyon Chol, an NTRL microbiologist who is working with England on the resistance screening. "We're developing a cadre of talented, hard-working young people," Schoolnik says. "There is a true sense of trust on both sides."</p>
<p>Last month, NTRL received a GeneXpert machine for rapid diagnosis of rifampicin resistance. MDR strains are defined as those resistant to isoniazid and rifampicin, the two most powerful drugs of the 6-month treatment for drug-sensitive TB. (The other two drugs are ethambutol and pyrazinamide.) Rifampicin resistance is used to diagnose MDR, because it almost invariably takes longer to develop than isoniazid resistance.</p>
<p>"We're moving into molecular testing," England says. But bringing NTRL up to speed has been slow going, she says. "Progress continues at a snail's pace, which is okay as long as we keep moving forward."</p>
<p>Before Stanford came on the scene, the only exposure to Western research practice that the TB specialists here had received was in southern India, from 2002 to 2004. With support from WHO, 19 Koreans each spent 15 days training at the National Institute for Research in Tuberculosis in Chennai. "It was difficult to judge how much they had understood and digested. They were not very communicative," says the institute's director, Soumya Swaminathan. A physician and a mycobacteriologist from Chennai paid visits to North Korea between 2004 and 2006. The doctor reported that patients "seemed severely malnourished," Swaminathan says, and the scientist "was frustrated" over the lack of a regular power supply that thwarted setting up TB cultures.</p>
<fig id="F7" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Out into the light.</title>
<p>Young TB patients get some fresh air at a pediatric ward in a northeast district of Pyongyang.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_422_F7"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: R. STONE/<italic>SCIENCE</italic></attrib>
</fig>
<p>Power woes continue to bedevil research facilities in Pyongyang, including NTRL. Last November, when power to the lab was cut, Schoolnik asked the Koreans why they hadn't switched on their backup generator. They explained that coupons used to purchase fuel at the local gas station were locked in the lab director's office, and he wasn't around. "I said, 'Let's go buy some diesel,'" Schoolnik says. Power outages can delay diagnoses and jeopardize patient care, England notes.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Making inroads</title>
<p>As TB case numbers rose in North Korea, villagers began to ostracize infected members of their communities. Here at Unpa, county officials planned to relocate the rest home in 2009. But "the new place found out it was a TB clinic and didn't want them to move in," Ko says. The idea was abandoned.</p>
<p>That paid off for Unpa. In November 2010, CFK installed a water tank up the hill from the sanatorium. Unpa's residents, Ko says, were glad that the rest home had stayed put: The tank supplies fresh water to the nearby village. Next on Unpa's wish list is a wind turbine to generate electricity; power is so spotty that the rest home isn't even fitted with light bulbs.</p>
<p>Back in Pyongyang, the CFK team drives past a diplomatic compound in Sadong District, in the northeast, and turns down a potholepocked lane packed with dilapidated dwellings. It's a poorer corner of the capital that few foreigners glimpse. Our van pulls up at a pink two-story building: the pediatric ward of the Pyongyang District #3 TB Prevention Hospital. It has a capacity of 100 patients, but today there are only 14 children, ages 6 to 15, and one infant. "As it gets warmer, we expect to have more," says the new director, Ri Sang Il. TB patients come out of the woodwork in spring, after being cooped up all winter huddling to stay warm, Linton says.</p>
<p>In some ways, Ri says, children are easier to treat than adults. "They are eager to follow what the doctors recommend," he says. "But they can also be naughty," one of Ri's colleagues chirps up, before adding, somberly, that the kids spend about 4 months on average in the ward and get really homesick. About a third of the children have digestive problems from the harsh TB drugs.</p>
<p>On this early spring morning, the pediatric ward is chilly. Nurses lead the children out into the sun for fresh air and warmth. The kids are wearing white pajamas with blue pinstripes over their clothes. "If people back home could spend 10 minutes here, driving through some of the areas we drive through, walking through patient wards, I think they'd get it," Linton says.</p>
<p>She sees reason to hope. The scientists and administrators, she says, "long for something that's real. They long for truth." But Linton knows that it will take more than a modern lab to bring TB to heel. "We need to be infused with a passion to do whatever it takes to stop this disease, and reverse it," she says, "for the sake of their people and this region and the world."</p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>