<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Zoology</subject><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subject>Medicine</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI COMMUN</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Around the World</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>26</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6131</issue>
<fpage seq="b">412</fpage>
<lpage>412</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>In science news around the world this week, public health officials in South Wales are trying to contain a measles outbreak; questions are still spinning around the legality of a geoengineering experiment conducted last summer in international waters; a magnitude-6.6 earthquake struck below the surface of Ya'an, China; and more.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>In science news around the world this week, public health officials in South Wales are trying to contain a measles outbreak; questions are still spinning around the legality of a geoengineering experiment conducted last summer in international waters; a magnitude-6.6 earthquake struck below the surface of Ya'an, China; and more.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="340_412b_F1"></graphic>
</fig>
<boxed-text content-type="story_index">
<def-list>
<def-item><term>1 - Swansea, U.K.</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec1">Measles Outbreak</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>2 - Ya'an, China</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2">Longmenshan Fault Ruptures Again</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>3 - Milan, Italy</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3">Protestors Steal Animals, Destroy Research</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>4 - Vancouver, Canada</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec4">Ocean Fertilization Experiment Still Making Waves</xref></p></def></def-item>
</def-list>
</boxed-text>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec1">
<title>Swansea, U.K.</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Measles Outbreak</title>
<p>Public health officials in South Wales are sending vaccination teams from school to school in an effort to contain a measles outbreak that could become the largest in the United Kingdom since the combination MMR vaccine (which also protects against mumps and rubella) was introduced in 1988. According to Public Health Wales, more than 800 people have fallen ill and 80 have been treated in hospitals since the epidemic, centered in the city of Swansea, began late last year. The body of a young man who died in the city last week while suffering from measles is also being examined to determine whether the virus caused his death.</p>
<p>Measles cases have increased in many European countries in recent years. In 2012, the Health Protection Agency counted 2016 measles cases in England and Wales, the highest number since 1994. The virus is highly contagious, and scientists estimate that 95% of people need to be vaccinated to protect against an outbreak. That coverage is rarely achieved in Europe, largely because many parents overestimate the risk of side effects of the vaccine and underestimate the risk that the disease poses.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec2">
<title>Ya'an, China</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Longmenshan Fault Ruptures Again</title>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
<caption>
<p>Firefighters search for survivors on 21 April.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_412b_F2"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: CDSB - IMAGINECHINA/AP PHOTO</attrib>
</fig>
<p>The dragon woke again, and this time scientists weren't caught off guard. On 20 April, a magnitude-6.6 earthquake struck 13 kilometers below the surface of Ya'an, a city of 1.5 million in western China's Sichuan Province. As <italic>Science</italic> went to press, Chinese authorities were reporting that more than 200 people lost their lives in collapsed buildings and quake-induced landslides.</p>
<p>The temblor struck about 130 kilometers southwest of the epicenter of the 2008 Wenchuan earthquake, a magnitude-8.0 event that killed more than 80,000 people. Five years ago, the northern segment of the Longmenshan fault ruptured; last weekend, it was the southern segment's turn. Before Wenchuan, few geophysicists paid attention to the fault, which "has a relatively low slip-rate" and hadn't uncorked a big earthquake for centuries, says Mian Liu, a geophysicist at the University of Missouri, Columbia. But in the past 5 years, he says, researchers have been studying the fault extensively, and they detected stress building up along the southern segment. Where the next big Sichuan earthquake will strike isn't clear&#x2014;but, Liu says, odds are on the Xianshuihe fault, west of Longmenshan.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec3">
<title>Milan, Italy</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Protestors Steal Animals, Destroy Research</title>
<p>Five people chained to the doors and valuable research mice wandering around free: That was the scene that greeted scientists with the University of Milan's Department of Medical Biotechnology and Translational Medicine on 20 April. During a national protest against vivisection that drew 400 demonstrators to the university, five members of the pro-animal movement <italic>Fermare Green Hill</italic> (Stop Green Hill) illegally entered the department's building, also home of the Institute of Neuroscience of the National Research Council (CNR).</p>
<p>After hours of negotiations, the researchers were able to convince the intruders not to free most of the facility's animals, which are mainly used as models for neurodegenerative diseases. However, the intruders did take about a hundred transgenic mice and one rabbit and destroyed the identification cards on all the animal cages.</p>
<p>The following day, a group of university scientists openly protested, for the first time in Italy, against pro-animal ideology, and the University of Milan sued Stop Green Hill. "Our animal models are treated according the European legislation. These people ruined years of research funded by national and European agencies" said Cecilia Gotti, a CNR researcher in Milan.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec4">
<title>Vancouver, Canada</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Ocean Fertilization Experiment Still Making Waves</title>
<p>Questions are still spinning around the legality of a geoengineering experiment conducted last summer in international waters. Last week, a native Canadian tribe filed a legal motion in provincial court in British Columbia to challenge a search warrant of its offices that was executed by Environment Canada in March. The search was part of an ongoing government investigation into the Haida Salmon Restoration Corp.'s controversial experiment, which involved dumping 100 tons of iron dust into an eddy 321 kilometers west of the Haida Gwaii islands to encourage the growth of algae and thereby increase fish stocks (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scim.ag/Haidafert">http://scim.ag/Haidafert</ext-link>).</p>
<p>Environment Canada says that two international treaties on ocean dumping to which Canada is party prohibit the practice unless it can be deemed "legitimate scientific research." An attorney for Haida, which is affiliated with the Old Masset Village, a First Nation group in British Columbia, says that those treaties are nonbinding and that only domestic Canadian legislation can actually bar ocean fertilization. If the motion to challenge the search warrant is successful, the confiscated materials, including scientific records and files, will be returned. No arrests have been made or charges filed.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
</article>