<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Genetics</subject><subject>Planetary-Science</subject><subject>Medicine</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>GENETICS</subject><subject>SCI COMMUN</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Intellectual Property</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>In a Flurry of Metaphors, Justices Debate a Limit on Gene Patents</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>Eliot</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
    <author-notes>
        <fn id="FN1"><label>*</label>
            <p>With reporting by Leigh Dayton.</p></fn></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>26</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6131</issue>
<fpage>421</fpage>
<lpage>421</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>The U.S. Supreme Court is trying to determine whether patents on the cancer-linked genes <italic><italic>BRCA1</italic> </italic>and <italic><italic>BRCA2</italic> </italic> are legitimate.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>The U.S. Supreme Court took a heady plunge into molecular biology on 15 April as it tried to determine whether patents on the cancer-linked genes <italic><italic>BRCA1</italic> </italic>and <italic>BRCA2</italic> are legitimate. The debate turns on whether DNA sequences patented by Myriad Genetics Inc. of Salt Lake City are human inventions, as Myriad claims. If not, the court could rule that they are "products of nature" and void the patents. A decision is expected before the end of June.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The U.S. Supreme Court took a heady plunge into molecular biology on 15 April as it tried to determine whether patents on the cancer-linked genes <italic>BRCA1</italic> and <italic>BRCA2</italic> are legitimate. The debate turns on whether DNA sequences patented by Myriad Genetics Inc. of Salt Lake City are human inventions, as Myriad claims. If not, the court could rule that they are "products of nature" and void the patents. A decision is expected before the end of June.</p>
<p>Challengers have been waging a legal campaign to topple Myriad's 15-year-old patents since 2009. A group of researchers, clinicians, and legal advocates represented by the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) argues that patents on <italic>BRCA</italic> genes&#x2014;the basis of Myriad's commercial test for breast and ovarian cancer risk&#x2014;lock up nature and impede research. In 2010, a New York federal court ruled that the patents are invalid; in 2011, the Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit overruled that decision. The challengers then appealed to the Supreme Court. (Australia's highest court last week also began considering whether to strike down <italic>BRCA</italic> patents owned by Myriad and the diagnostics company Genetic Technologies Ltd. of Melbourne.)</p>
<p>Judging by questions and answers in the U.S. proceedings last week, research findings could play an important part in the court's decision. The Supreme Court veered into scientific territory after Justice Stephen Breyer cited a technical analysis submitted by mathematician-biologist Eric Lander, a leader of the Human Genome Project and founder of the Broad Institute in Cambridge, Massachusetts. Claiming to speak for neither side, Lander filed an amicus brief arguing that the recent lower-court decision in favor of Myriad is simply wrong. That earlier ruling accepted Myriad's claim that "isolated" <italic>BRCA</italic> genes are laboratory products and that, unlike chromosomes, they do not occur in nature. Lander writes that this "is demonstrably incorrect."</p>
<p>Lander, who co-chairs the President's Council of Advisors on Science and Technology, writes in his brief that chromosomes are constantly breaking up in the body, yielding fragments of genomic DNA. Specifically, he points to studies published last year in <italic>Nature</italic> and <italic>Science Translational Medicine</italic> (a sister publication of <italic>Science</italic>) reporting that blood from pregnant mothers contains enough isolated DNA fragments from the fetus to enable one to reconstruct the fetus's entire genome. Data available online from Stanford University, according to Lander, show that "isolated fragments of fetal DNA in maternal blood cover the <italic>BRCA1</italic> and <italic>BRCA2</italic> genes." He concludes, "isolated DNA fragments from the human genome," including those claimed in Myriad's patents, "are products of Nature, not the handiwork of humans."</p>
<p>Breyer queried Myriad's lawyer, Gregory Castanias, many times about Lander's brief. "Have I misread what the scientists told us, or are you telling us the scientists are wrong?" Breyer asked. Castanias did not address the question directly. But he said that the DNA fragments that Lander described would not amount to "something that is new and useful and available to the public."</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Who owns genes?</title>
<p>Protesters gathered at the Supreme Court as it weighed the fate of <italic>BRCA</italic> gene patents.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_421_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: MLADEN ANTONOV/AFP/GETTY IMAGES</attrib>
</fig>
<p>For much of the session, the U.S. justices suggested different metaphors in an effort to fit the biology into a legal mold. They appeared to be looking for a way to distinguish between artificial DNA constructs (which might be patentable) and naturally occurring genes (which might not). Justices Samuel Alito and Ruth Bader Ginsburg compared Myriad's patented genes to a molecule taken from an imaginary tree deep in the Amazon. They suggested that the tree and its leaves might not be patentable, but a concentrate of sap used as medicine might be. At another point, the justices considered whether the <italic>BRCA</italic> genes might be like a baseball bat carved out of a tree. (The bat might be patentable but not the wood or the tree.) Justice Sonia Sotomayor compared the gene sequences to ingredients in a chocolate chip cookie. She said she could imagine a patent on a method of combining the ingredients, but, "I can't imagine getting a patent simply on the basic items of salt, flour, and eggs." The metaphors may not have been perfect, but Lander sees them as an attempt to express in lay language "a serious understanding" of the key issues. He says: "I was impressed by how the justices recognized that science is at the heart of the case."</p>
<p>Some justices also expressed concern about the economic impact of doing away with human gene patents. Justice Elena Kagan asked the ACLU attorney Christopher Hansen: "Why shouldn't we worry that Myriad or companies like it will just say, well, you know, we're not going to do this work anymore?" Hansen responded: "There were other labs doing <italic>BRCA</italic> testing" before Myriad began to enforce its patents, and "Myriad shut all that testing down." He added that the "whole point" of ACLU's argument is that "when you lock up a product of nature, it prevents industry from innovating and making new discoveries."</p>
<p>The Obama administration, in arguments presented by U.S. Solicitor General Donald Verrilli, proposed a compromise of sorts. Although the U.S. government has allowed gene patents in the past, Verrilli said, it now believes that "isolated" DNA of the kind in Myriad's patents should not be patentable "because it is simply native DNA extracted from the body." He said that patents should only be allowed on DNA sequences that are clearly an "artificial creation in the laboratory," such as complementary DNA, or cDNA. Myriad's lawyer, Castanias, said that virtually all the objections being made against the <italic>BRCA</italic> patents were considered in a thorough review 12 years ago by the U.S. Patent and Trademark Office&#x2014;and rejected. He didn't see the relevance of the new distinctions proposed by the government, but several justices seemed ready to adopt them.</p>
</body>
</article>