<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Medicine</subject><subject>Genetics</subject><subject>Biochemistry</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI COMMUN</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Newsmakers</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>26</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6131</issue>
<fpage seq="b">413</fpage>
<lpage>413</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Pharmacologists Garret FitzGerald and Carlo Patrono have won the prestigious Grand Prix Scientifique, given annually by the Institut de France for work in cardiovascular health, and French geneticist, World War II hero, and science writer Fran&#xE7;ois Jacob has died.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Pharmacologists Garret FitzGerald and Carlo Patrono have won the prestigious Grand Prix Scientifi que, given annually by the Institut de France for work in cardiovascular health, and French geneticist, World War II hero, and science writer Fran&#xE7;ois Jacob has died.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec>
<title>Take Two: Research on Aspirin and Heart Disease Earns Prize</title>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<p>FitzGerald</p>
<p>Patrono</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_413b_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: SABINA LOUISE PIERCE; COURTESY OF CARLO PATRONO</attrib>
</fig>
<p>A pair of pharmacologists has won the prestigious Grand Prix Scientifique, given annually by the Institut de France for work in cardiovascular health. <bold>Garret FitzGerald</bold> of the University of Pennsylvania and <bold>Carlo Patrono</bold> of the Catholic University in Rome will share just over $650,000 (&#x20AC;500,000) for disentangling how low-dose aspirin staves off heart disease.</p>

<p>"We competed, we collaborated, but we always remained friends," says FitzGerald of his relationship with Patrono.</p>
<p>Their work, performed mostly in the 1980s and early 1990s, came after years of clinical trials mysteriously failed to show low-dose aspirin helping the heart. "People were saying, &#x2018;We know in a test-tube aspirin inhibits platelet formation,&#x2019;" reducing clots, FitzGerald says. "&#x2018;Why doesn't it in people?&#x2019;"</p>
<p>Often racing each other, Patrono and FitzGerald sought to bridge the gap between test tube and human being. They elucidated how aspirin acts on platelets and identified both the ideal drug dose and who would benefit most: people with unstable angina, who experience a proliferation of platelets, leading to blood clots and heart attacks.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>France Loses Molecular Biology Pioneer</title>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
<caption>
<p>Jacob receiving his Nobel Prize.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_413b_F2"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: AP PHOTO</attrib>
</fig>
<p>French geneticist, World War II hero, and science writer <bold>Fran&#x00E7;ois Jacob</bold> died on 19 April at the age of 92. Jacob was one of the fathers of molecular biology. Initially trained as a medical doctor and surgeon, he was severely wounded while serving as a medical officer for the Free French Forces. He began his research career in 1950 at the Institut Pasteur, when he began investigating how genes control enzyme synthesis. For his development of the "operon model," in which structural and regulatory genes coding for related proteins are arranged in units called operons, Jacob won the Nobel Prize in physiology or medicine in 1965, together with colleagues Andr&#x00E9; Lwoff and Jacques Monod.</p>

<p>The operon model "had a major impact on biology as a whole," because it pooled biochemistry and genetics, and also "answered a question that geneticists had been asking for more than thirty years," said biologist and science historian Michel Morange, a former student of Fran&#x00E7;ois Jacob, in an obituary released by the Institut Pasteur. Jacob received the highest French military decoration for World War II and was a former Chancellor of the Order of the Liberation.</p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>