<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="letter" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Letter</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letters</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>letters</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Environment</subject><subject>Economics</subject><subject>Education</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
    <article-title>Readers' Poll Results: Funding Environment</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>26</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6131</issue>
<fpage>429</fpage>
<lpage>429</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="letters.pdf" />
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Jennifer Sills</meta-value></custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec> <title>Funding Environment</title> <fig id="F2" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="340_429_F2" />
</fig> 
    <p>In his 15 March Editorial &#x201C;Am I wrong?&#x201D; (p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-publication" vol="339" page="1252" issue="6125">1252</related-article>), B. Alberts lamented the decline of research funding available in the United States and predicted that misguided short-term decisions could severely affect the nation's future. He asked scientists to write in and tell him whether his impression was wrong. In a related poll, Alberts asked:</p> <p><bold>To what extent is the current grant funding environment undermining the intellectual environment and creativity in your institution?</bold></p> <p>More than 100 readers commented online (see all comments at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://comments.sciencemag.org/content/10.1126/science.1237434">http://comments.sciencemag.org/content/10.1126/science.1237434</ext-link>), and more than 1300 voted in the poll, from countries all around the world. Here are your results.</p> <p><bold>A selection of your thoughts:</bold></p> <p><italic>You are not wrong, but no one should be allowed to put demands on the treasury without some consideration of the budget and national debt.</italic></p> <p>&#x2014;<italic>Chuck Coltharp</italic></p> <p><italic>I share your concern about the national debt, [but].&#x2026;since the end of World War II, somewhere between 50 to 85% of the economic growth in the country has come from scientific and technological advances.&#x2026;The very nature of scientific research makes its returns uncertain, so companies can't afford to push the frontiers themselves, only we the taxpayers can do that. &#x2026;</italic></p> <p>&#x2014;<italic>Jake Searcy</italic></p> <p><italic>The NIH budget needs to stop being viewed as a welfare expenditure. This means making the NIH budget independent of [the Department of Health, and Human Services] and recognizing the NIH as part of the infrastructure of the biomedical industry. It should be funded like highways or airports that are supported by fees levied on the commerce they support.</italic></p> <p>&#x2014;<italic>Mark Ginsberg</italic></p> <p><italic>The lack of funding for fundamental research in the U.S. (and in Canada, where I live) appears to be directly linked to the politicians' and the general public's concentration on short-term goals and benefits (called &#x201C;innovations&#x201D; in Canada), and their lack of understanding of the benefits that ultimately accrue from basic research&#x2026;.</italic></p> <p>&#x2014;<italic>Don Baker</italic></p> <p><italic>The biggest problem for academic scientists is the divestment of state support, which has forced them to rely on grants for their salaries. This drives them into the grant writing frenzy that we see now. It also diminishes their productivity and proliferates mediocre and dubious science, a waste of federal funds. Dissociating research dollars from salary support ensures less stress, greater productivity, and higher quality. Considering that salaries form a big chunk of any grant, one could also run a lab effectively with smaller grants.&#x2026;</italic></p> <p>&#x2014;<italic>Sukumar Vijayaraghavan</italic></p> <p><italic>&#x2026;Periodic downturns in funding provide an opportunity to weed out the less than effective.&#x2026; In tough times, one redoubles the effort to exploit the stock of recently acquired new knowledge, rather than generate more new knowledge and leave it unexploited. This makes sound economic sense&#x2026;.</italic></p> <p>&#x2014;<italic>Michael Kelly</italic></p> <p><italic>It is a pity that &#x2026; the financing of science is still based on the national partitioning of the world &#x2026; There is a World Bank; why can't we have a world science fund replacing national funding systems?</italic></p> <p>&#x2014;<italic>Hans Rogl</italic></p> <p><italic>That is true! &#x2026;International colleagues are increasingly [saying] that they plan to return to their own countries because their countries can provide a better research environment, such as financial support, laboratory apparatus, and living conditions. [This] used to be the advantage of the U.S.&#x2026;</italic></p> <p>&#x2014;<italic>Xu Hou</italic></p> <p><italic>You are certainly not wrong, but sadly, U.S. scientists are still better off than here in New Zealand.&#x2026;</italic></p> <p>&#x2014;<italic>Jon Hickford</italic></p> <p><italic>If this is the grim situation in the U.S., you don't want to think about Spain: &#x2026;We have trained in the past two decades the best cohort of young people we ever had. Now&#x2026;the governmental cuts in science spoil all the recent efforts.&#x2026;.</italic></p> <p>&#x2014;<italic>Francisco X. Real</italic></p> <p><italic>&#x2026;In my country [Italy] &#x2026; most of the research is done thanks to people who don't get any money for their efforts.&#x2026;.</italic></p> <p>&#x2014;<italic>Christian Marinaccio</italic></p> <p><italic>Bruce's Editorial is right on the dot. Germany is doing very well in job creation, thanks to the massive investment in education, research, and technology.&#x2026;</italic></p> <p>&#x2014;<italic>Amar Nath</italic></p> </sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>Polling results reflect only the votes of those who choose to participate; they do not represent a random sample of the population.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>