<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="article-commentary" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">STM</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science Translational Medicine</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Sci. Transl. Med.</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1946-6234</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1946-6242</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3004722</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3004722</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Editors' Choice</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editors' Choice</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>STM EC</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>Medicine</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Cancer</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Sleepy Time for Tumor Cells</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mashour</surname><given-names>George A.</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff id="aff1">University of Michigan Medical School, Ann Arbor, MI, 48109, USA. E-mail: <email xlink:href="gmashour@med.umich.edu">gmashour@med.umich.edu</email></aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>147</issue>
<fpage>147ec146</fpage>
<lpage>147ec146</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>General anesthetics inhibit matrix metalloproteinase-9 and limit invasiveness of colon cancer cells.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>We know that general anesthetics can stop pretty much anyone in their tracks&#x2014;but what about cancer cells? For a cancer to metastasize, tumor cells must first break through the network of fibers and polysaccharides that provides structural support for healthy cells&#x2014;the extracellular matrix. This process can be triggered by surgical manipulation, in part because of the tissue damage resulting from slowed blood flow followed by reperfusion. Conversely, general anesthesia during surgery has recently been shown to positively influence cancer outcomes; however, how anesthetics attenuate tumor growth remains unknown. Now, M&#x00FC;ller-Edenborn and colleagues demonstrate that the inhaled anesthetics sevoflurane and desflurane impair the release and activity of matrix metalloproteinase-9 (MMP-9), which plays an important role in degradation of the extracellular matrix and subsequent tumor invasion.</p>
<p>The investigators cultured human neutrophils, the richest source of MMP-9 in the body, in the presence of interleukin-8 (IL-8), a proinflammatory cytokine that is released during reperfusion. Control neutrophils produced MMP-9 when exposed to IL-8; however, clinically relevant concentrations of sevoflurane or desflurane inhibited MMP-9 production. This difference was not related to neutrophil viability but was mediated through the IL-8 receptor. The same anesthetics also limited migration of human neutrophils through Matrigel, an experimental gel that simulates the extracellular matrix. Importantly, anesthetic treatment also limited migration of mouse colon cancer cells in the presence of neutrophils.</p>
<p>The findings of M&#x00FC;ller-Edenborn prompt further translational research into whether anesthetic technique during tumor operations can have a direct influence on cancer recurrence by modulating matrix-degrading activity that is triggered by surgery and required for invasiveness. Of course, the study is limited by the in vitro methodology and the use of murine cancer cells. However, if this finding is further validated in humans, perhaps we may yet be able to &#x201C;put tumors to sleep,&#x201D; at least long enough to successfully remove them from patients without the risk of further metastasis.</p>
<p>B. M&#x00FC;ller-Edenborn <italic>et al</italic>., Volatile anesthetics reduce invasion of colorectal cancer cells through down-regulation of matrix metalloproteinase-9. <italic>Anesthesiology </italic><bold>117</bold>, 293&#x2013;301 (2012). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22739763">[PubMed]</ext-link> </p>
</body>
</article>
