<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">sigtrans</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science Signaling</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Sci. Signal.</abbrev-journal-title>
    <issn pub-type="epub">1937-9145</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">1945-0877</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2003312</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scisignal.2003312</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>STKE Research Articles</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>CELL BIOL</subject><subject>MICROBIO</subject><subject>COMP/MATH</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Cell Biology</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Pheromone-Induced Morphogenesis Improves Osmoadaptation Capacity by Activating the HOG MAPK Pathway</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baltan&#x00E1;s</surname><given-names>Rodrigo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>Alan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Couto</surname><given-names>Alicia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Durrieu</surname><given-names>Luc&#x00ED;a</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Colman-Lerner</surname><given-names>Alejandro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Instituto de Fisiolog&#x00ED;a, Biolog&#x00ED;a Molecular y Neurociencias, Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Cient&#x00ED;ficas y T&#x00E9;cnicas y Departamento de Fisiolog&#x00ED;a, Biolog&#x00ED;a Molecular y Celular, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires C1428EHA, Argentina.</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>CIHIDECAR-Departamento de Qu&#x00ED;mica Org&#x00E1;nica, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires C1428EHA, Argentina.</aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Cell and Molecular Biology, University of Gothenburg, Gothenburg 413 90, Sweden.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. E-mail: <email xlink:href="colman-lerner@fbmc.fcen.uba.ar">colman-lerner@fbmc.fcen.uba.ar</email></corresp></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>23</day><month>04</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>272</issue>
<fpage>ra26</fpage>
<lpage>ra26</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>06</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>03</month><year>2013</year></date></history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>Crosstalk between MAPK pathways activated by a single sensory input enhances yeast responses to multiple simultaneous stimuli.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="editor">
<title>Crosstalk for Adaptability</title>
<p>Yeast use different mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathways to respond to distinct stimuli, such as mating pheromone, high external osmolarity, and cell wall integrity. Baltan&#x00E1;s <italic>et al.</italic> investigated how yeast cells respond to simultaneous distinct stimuli that activate different MAPK pathways. In cells adapted to high osmolarity, the MAPK that is normally responsive only to high osmolarity was further activated by pheromone in bursts that coincided with times when yeast cells underwent a mating-related shape change. This activation process required a third MAPK with a role in the cell wall integrity pathway. Thus, crosstalk between three MAPK pathways enhances the response of yeast to an external stress (such as high osmolarity) when exposed to a sensory stimulus (such as mating pheromone).</p>
</abstract>
<abstract>
<p>Environmental and internal conditions expose cells to a multiplicity of stimuli whose consequences are difficult to predict. We investigate the response to mating pheromone of yeast cells adapted to high osmolarity. Events downstream of pheromone binding involve two mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) cascades: the pheromone response (PR) and the cell wall integrity (CWI) response. Although the PR MAPK pathway shares components with a third MAPK pathway, the high osmolarity (HOG) response, each one is normally only activated by its cognate stimulus, a phenomenon called insulation. We found that in cells adapted to high osmolarity, PR activated the HOG pathway in a pheromone- and osmolarity-dependent manner. Activation of HOG by the PR was not due to loss of insulation, but rather a response to a reduction in internal osmolarity, which resulted from an increase in glycerol release caused by the PR. By analyzing single-cell time courses, we found that stimulation of HOG occurred in discrete bursts that coincided with the &#x201C;shmooing&#x201D; morphogenetic process. Activation required the polarisome, the CWI MAPK Slt2, and the aquaglyceroporin Fps1. HOG activation resulted in high glycerol turnover, which improved adaptability to rapid changes in osmolarity. Our work shows how a differentiation signal can recruit a second, unrelated sensory pathway to fine-tune yeast response in a complex environment.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Wei Wong</meta-value></custom-meta>
<custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>SPI</meta-value></custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Signal transduction systems have been traditionally studied in single-input conditions. However, natural environments often present multiple stimuli that simultaneously activate several regulatory systems. The responses elicited by these systems might be contradictory, for instance, when cells are simultaneously exposed to growth-promoting and growth-arresting stimuli. Little is known about how cells integrate such information to make adaptive decisions.</p>
<p>In haploid <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, two of the four mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK)&#x2013;based systems (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>), the high osmolarity glycerol (HOG) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>) and the cell wall integrity (CWI) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>), maintain homeostasis against environmental and developmental changes. The other two MAPK systems, the mating pheromone response (PR) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>) and the filamentation system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>), control developmental transitions in response to mating pheromone and certain nutritional metabolites, respectively.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption>
<title>The pheromone, HOG, and CWI pathways in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic representation of the three MAPK pathways relevant for this study. Activation of the PR pathway induces the P<sub><italic>PRM1</italic></sub>-mCherry transcriptional reporter (left). When phosphorylated and activated Hog1 translocates to the nucleus, it associates with transcription factors such as Hot1 to drive the expression of the P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP transcriptional reporter (middle). Right: CWI MAPK pathway. (<bold>B</bold> and <bold>C</bold>) Single-stimulus behavior of the transcriptional reporters used in this study. We stimulated exponentially growing wild-type (WT) (LD3342, &#x0394;<italic>bar1</italic> P<sub><italic>PRM1</italic></sub>-mCherry P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP P<sub><italic>BMH2</italic></sub>-CFP) cells with &#x03B1; factor (B) or the indicated concentrations of NaCl (C), and collected samples into cycloheximide at the indicated times for imaging and fluorescent protein quantification. Each input activated only one reporter. Addition of NaCl caused an increase in YFP fluorescence, followed by a decline to a lower steady state. Data represent the average total mCherry (B) or YFP (C) fluorescence intensity per cell. Error bars represent SEM (<italic>n</italic> ~ 700 cells for each data point). Plots show a representative experiment of three biological replicates.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="6_ra26_F1"></graphic></fig>
<p>Pheromones secreted by haploid yeast cells of opposite mating type (a and &#x03B1; factors, secreted by <italic>MAT</italic>a and <italic>MAT</italic>&#x03B1; cells) trigger a cell fate decision that leads to mating, which involves a G protein (heterotrimeric guanine nucleotide&#x2013;binding protein)&#x2013;coupled receptor and a scaffolded MAPK cascade that activates the extracellular signal&#x2013;regulated kinase (ERK) 1/2&#x2013;like MAPKs Fus3 and Kss1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>, left). The pathway is activated in <italic>MAT</italic>a cells when &#x03B1; factor binds to the receptor Ste2, ultimately culminating in the activation of the MAPKs Fus3 and Kss1. Activated Fus3 and Kss1 regulate cytoplasmic and nuclear targets, resulting in the induction of about 100 genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). Fus3 and Kss1 stimulate actin polarization toward the pheromone source, leading to a cell-shaping process called &#x201C;shmooing.&#x201D; This type of polarized cellular growth requires the assembly of a multiprotein complex called polarisome at the site of polarization. Deletion of some of its components, such as Spa2 and Pea2, does not affect the performance of the MAPK cascade or polarization itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>) but prevents the formation of the characteristic narrow, pointy shmoos exhibited by wild-type cells. Shmooing stresses the cell wall, leading to activation of the CWI MAPK cascade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). The CWI response mediates the turnover of cell wall material (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>) and is activated by many stimuli, including hypo-osmotic shock, cell wall disruptors, heat shock, and pheromone treatment. Mucin-like proteins connecting the plasma membrane and cell wall serve as sensors and indirectly activate protein kinase C in yeast, resulting in stimulation of the Bck1, Mkk1 and Mkk2, Slt2 MAPK cascade and modulation of transcription by Slt2. Activation of Slt2 by pheromone requires the polarisome component Spa2, which acts as scaffold for Mkk1 and Slt2. Deletion of the <italic>SLT2</italic> gene causes cell lysis during shmooing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>An increase in external osmolarity causes loss of turgor pressure and cell volume, triggering a homeostatic response leading to accumulation of glycerol, which acts as the compensating osmolyte and to which the plasma membrane is only slightly permeable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>). The response also includes a temporary cell cycle arrest, changes in enzyme and transporter activities, and stimulation of gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>), responses that are mediated by the HOG system. The two signaling branches, Sln1 and Sho1, converge on the activation of the MAPK kinase Pbs2, which phosphorylates the p38-like MAPK Hog1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>). Activation of the Sho1 branch by the mucin-like sensors Msb2 and Hrk1 causes the recruitment of Cdc42 to the membrane anchor Opy2, leading to activation of Ste20, which activates Ste11. Subsequently, Sho1 and the Opy2-Ste50 complex recruit Pbs2, enabling Ste11 to phosphorylate Pbs2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>). The Sln1 branch transduces the signal through a phosphorelay signaling module, Sln1-Ypd1-Ssk1. In the absence of hyperosmotic stress, Sln1 is active, maintaining Ssk1 in its phosphorylated form. After a hyperosmotic shock, Sln1 activity decreases, leading to dephosphorylation of Ssk1. Unphosphorylated Ssk1 activates the MAPK kinase kinases Ssk2 and Ssk22 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13"><italic>13</italic></xref>), which phosphorylate Pbs2. Phosphorylated Hog1 translocates to the nucleus, where it associates with transcription factors such as Hot1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>) and participates in the induction of various genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>), including those encoding enzymes and transporters required for glycerol accumulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Osmotic shock also triggers HOG-independent responses, such as rapid closure of the aquaglyceroporin Fps1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16"><italic>16</italic></xref>). Glycerol efflux through Fps1 occurs continuously in cells growing in low-osmolarity medium, but stops after osmotic shock and remains low after cells have adapted. When adapted cells are transferred into a low-osmolarity environment, Fps1 opens, resulting in glycerol efflux and alleviating excessive pressure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16"><italic>16</italic></xref>). Proper control of Fps1 activity seems to require two proteins, Rgc1 and Ask10, without which defects in Fps1 opening result in excessive accumulation of glycerol, leading to cell wall stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17"><italic>17</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Despite their similar core architecture consisting of two scaffolded MAPK cascades, the PR and HOG display substantially different dynamic responses to constant stimulation. Exposure to a constant high pheromone concentration results in sustained gene induction and prolonged cell cycle arrest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18"><italic>18</italic></xref>). In contrast, a hyperosmotic shock causes a transient HOG activation followed by a slower deactivation phase as cells adapt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). After adaptation, HOG is thought to return to its pre-shock state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19"><italic>19</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20"><italic>20</italic></xref>). This &#x201C;perfect adaptation&#x201D; implies that cells maintain a higher intracellular glycerol concentration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21"><italic>21</italic></xref>) without the need for further HOG activity. Although the Sho1 branch of HOG shares components with PR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>), activation of each pathway does not cause activation of the other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22"><italic>22</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24"><italic>24</italic></xref>). PR is insulated from cross-activation by high-osmolarity through an unknown, cytoplasmic mechanism that requires Hog1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23"><italic>23</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25"><italic>25</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Here, we examined the activity of HOG and its insulation from PR after adaptation to high osmolarity. We found that contrary to a previous report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19"><italic>19</italic></xref>), HOG activity persists after adaptation in a dose-dependent manner. Unexpectedly, in osmoadapted cells, PR activates HOG. This activation is not due to loss of insulation but to glycerol release caused by shmooing. HOG activation results in a state of high glycerol turnover that improves adaptability to rapid changes in osmolarity during mating. Our results illustrate the interplay between three MAPK pathways to mediate a cell shape change in the presence of external stress.</p>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="results" disp-level="1">
<title>Results</title>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>HOG remains active after adaptation to a hyperosmotic shock</title>
<p>To study the interaction between the PR and the HOG systems, we constructed haploid <italic>MAT</italic>a strains that contained three fluorescent protein&#x2013;based transcriptional reporters: P<sub><italic>PRM1</italic></sub>-mCherry, which is induced by pheromone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26"><italic>26</italic></xref>), P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP (yellow fluorescent protein), which is induced by HOG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>), and P<sub><italic>BMH2</italic></sub>-CFP (cyan fluorescent protein), which is constitutively expressed and insensitive to either pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). To accurately control external pheromone concentration, we used &#x0394;<italic>bar1</italic> strains, which lack the extracellular protease Bar1. We applied pheromone or high osmolarity (NaCl, sorbitol, glycerol, or equal amounts of the last two compounds) and measured YFP, CFP, and mCherry fluorescence by microscopy-based cytometry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29"><italic>29</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>As expected, each input activated only one reporter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, B and C) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>). Pheromone caused a steady, roughly linear accumulation of mCherry. Considering that degradation of these fluorescent proteins is negligible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>), and that cells are arrested by pheromone, the linear increase indicates that the expression of this reporter is constant, and suggests that the system is in steady state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>). High osmolarity caused a fast increase in YFP fluorescence followed by a slower decline. In cells adapted after overnight growth in high-osmolarity medium, the steady-state HOG transcriptional output did not return to pre-shock values, but instead, the output remained higher, in direct proportion to the external osmolarity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Expression of the constitutive P<sub><italic>BMH2</italic></sub>-CFP reporter was not significantly affected by external osmolarity (fig. S1A). The positive correlation between external osmolarity and steady-state activity of HOG suggests that Hog1 is required to maintain an increased internal concentration of glycerol during growth in high external osmolarities. At the same time, the chemical gradient across the membrane resulting from the increased internal glycerol concentration drives glycerol out of cells, which can be compensated by a higher synthesis rate. To test whether HOG was necessary to maintain a high internal glycerol concentration, we determined if its activity depends on the strength of the glycerol gradient. We compared reporter expression in cells grown in the presence of 1 M sorbitol or with 0.5 M sorbitol and 0.5 M glycerol. These two media present a similar osmotic challenge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30"><italic>30</italic></xref>). However, in the second solution, yeast experience a lower glycerol gradient and expression of the HOG reporter was lower than that in 1 M sorbitol, adopting a value intermediate between 1 M glycerol and 1 M sorbitol (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Hence, expression of the HOG reporter in steady-state cultures depends on the glycerol gradient rather than on the absolute external osmolarity, supporting the notion that HOG activity in these cultures is directed at maintaining internal glycerol concentrations.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption>
<title>Steady-state activity of HOG after adaptation is osmolarity-dependent.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) HOG transcriptional output. WT (LD3342) cells were adapted overnight to SC (synthetic complete) medium supplemented with sorbitol, glycerol, or both osmotica as indicated. Data represent the average total YFP fluorescence intensity per cell normalized to that in SC medium. Inset: HOG adaptive response. I1, initial external osmolarity; I2, final external osmolarity; Ops, HOG output pre-shock; Opeak, HOG output at maximum response; Oss, HOG output at steady state post-shock. Nomenclature was according to Ma <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58"><italic>58</italic></xref>). Oss &#x2212; Ops increases with the external osmolarity (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>). Error bars represent SEM. <italic>n</italic> ~ 700 cells for each data point. (<bold>B</bold>) HOG phosphorylation. LD3342 cells were cultured as in (A), and protein extracts were analyzed by Western blot. Representative Western blot with antibodies against the indicated proteins (left). Quantification of Hog1 phosphorylation under the indicated conditions (right). Data represent the indicated ratios, normalized to values at 0 added osM (<italic>n</italic> = 3 experiments). Hog1pp/GAPDH (glyceraldehyde-3- phosphate dehydrogenase) and Hog1 total/GAPDH increase with external osmolarity (<italic>P</italic> = 0.016 and <italic>P</italic> = 0.03, respectively). Hog1pp/Hog1 total between 0.5 and 1 osM increases significantly with respect to 0 osM (&#x03B1; = 0.05, Tukey&#x2019;s multiple contrasts). (<bold>C</bold>) HOG localization. WT yeast (ySP69) expressing Hog1-Venus and Hta2-CFP were cultured as in (A), and Z-stacks were acquired with a confocal microscope. Montage of cells with in-focus nucleus (left). Quantification of nuclear and cytoplasmic Hog1-Venus fluorescence intensity at the indicated osmolarity (right). Nuclear Hog1 increases with external osmolarity (76 &#x00B1; 4%/osM, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>). Cytoplasmic Hog1 slightly increases with osmolarity (20 &#x00B1; 6%/osM <italic>P</italic> = 0.014). See also figs. S2 and S3. Data represent means &#x00B1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 3 experiments). (<bold>D</bold>) PR transcriptional output. LD3342 cells were cultured as in (A) and treated with 1 &#x03BC;M &#x03B1; factor. At the indicated times, samples were collected into cycloheximide for imaging and fluorescent protein quantification. Data represent the mean total mCherry fluorescence intensity per cell &#x00B1; SEM of one representative experiment (<italic>n</italic> = 3). <italic>n</italic> ~ 700 cells for each data point. The transcription rate of mCherry decreased with external osmolarity (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup> for this experiment). (<bold>E</bold>) PR induced cell cycle arrest. Images correspond to halo assays performed with LD3342 yeast on SC plates with the indicated added osmoticum. The doubling time of yeast in these different media was similar: 86 &#x00B1; 1 min (SC with no additions), 93 &#x00B1; 1 min (SC + 1 M sorbitol), 93 &#x00B1; 3 (SC + 1 M glycerol), and 91 &#x00B1; 4 min (SC + 1 M mannitol). See also figs. S1 to S3.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="6_ra26_F2"></graphic></fig>
<p>To confirm that HOG was active after osmoadaptation, we measured phosphorylated Hog1, total Hog1, and Hog1 subcellular localization in cells cultured overnight at different osmotic strength. Phosphorylated Hog1 increased proportionally with external osmolarity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). This increase was due in part to an increase in total Hog1, especially at osmotic strengths higher than 1 osM. In cells adapted to 1 M sorbitol, phosphorylation of Hog1 was similar to that observed after 5 min of osmoshock with 0.1 M NaCl (fig. S1B). Also, the amount of nuclear Hog1 in adapted cells increased with osmolarity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref> and fig. S2) and exhibited large cell-to-cell variability (fig. S3). The fluorescence of cytoplasmic Hog1-Venus increased to a lesser extent than that of nuclear Hog1. Together, and in contrast to the perfect adaptation concept (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19"><italic>19</italic></xref>), these findings suggest that HOG remains active after osmoadaptation.</p>
<p>To examine the effect of osmoadaptation on the activity of the pheromone pathway, we measured pheromone-dependent gene expression in cells grown at different osmotic strengths and stimulated with mating pheromone. Increased osmolarity resulted in decreased pheromone-dependent transcription (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>) (for example, about 65% in medium with 1.6 M sorbitol compared to unstressed cells). Pheromone-induced cell cycle arrest was monitored by a halo assay, in which the size of the &#x201C;halo&#x201D; indicates the area of growth inhibition and the sensitivity of the cells to &#x03B1; factor. Cells spread on plates with 1 M sorbitol or mannitol formed smaller halos than those spread on medium without added osmoticum (about 72 and 65% shorter diameter, respectively), whereas cells spread on plates with 1 M glycerol formed halos of normal size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2E</xref>). Thus, when cells need to maintain the HOG system in an active state, the PR is partly inhibited. This is consistent with reports that show that hyperosmolarity dampens the mating response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24"><italic>24</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31"><italic>31</italic></xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>PR activates HOG</title>
<p>Whereas steady-state HOG activity inhibited the pheromone pathway, pheromone further stimulated the HOG system. When cells preadapted to sorbitol were stimulated with pheromone, the expression of the HOG transcriptional reporter P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP began to increase after about 50 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>) and was delayed compared to the PR reporter (fig. S4A). Consistent with the increase in transcriptional activity, the amount of dually phosphorylated MAPK Hog1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>) and that of nuclear Hog1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>) also increased. HOG reporter gene expression under these conditions was dependent on Hog1 because its activity was negligible in pheromone-stimulated, high osmolarity&#x2013;adapted &#x0394;<italic>hog1</italic> cells (fig. S5).</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption>
<title>Mating pheromone activates HOG.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) HOG transcriptional output. WT (LD3342), &#x0394;<italic>sho1</italic> (RB3704), &#x0394;<italic>ssk1</italic> (RB3382a), and &#x0394;<italic>ssk2</italic> (RB3642) cells adapted to sorbitol were stimulated with &#x03B1; factor and collected into cycloheximide at the indicated time points for imaging. Data represent the mean total YFP fluorescence intensity &#x00B1; SEM per cell of one experiment (<italic>n</italic> = 3 experiments) (<italic>n</italic> ~ 700 cells for each data point). YFP fluorescence significantly increased 50 min after pheromone treatment for WT (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>) and &#x0394;<italic>sho1</italic> (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>), but not for &#x0394;<italic>ssk1</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.31) or &#x0394;<italic>ssk2</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.07). (<bold>B</bold>) HOG phosphorylation. Representative Western blot with protein extracts from LD3342 cells cultured as in (A) with antibodies against the indicated proteins (left). Quantification of Hog1 phosphorylation under the indicated conditions (right). Data represent the means &#x00B1; SEM of the indicated ratios, normalized to values at time 0 (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Hog1-pp to total Hog1 increased after pheromone treatment (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>). (<bold>C</bold>) HOG localization. WT yeast (ySP69) expressing Hog1-Venus and Hta2-CFP were cultured as in (A) and imaged in a confocal microscope. Montage showing cells with in-focus nucleus (left). Quantification of nuclear Hog1-Venus fluorescence localization at the indicated osmolarity (right). Data represent the mean ratios &#x00B1; SEM of nuclear YFP to CFP signal (<italic>n</italic> = 3 experiments). Nuclear YFP-to-CFP ratio increased 50 min after pheromone treatment (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>). (<bold>D</bold>) Model of pheromone-dependent activation of HOG through stimulation of the Sln1 branch. See also figs. S4 to S7.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="6_ra26_F3"></graphic></fig>
<p>To demonstrate the involvement of the PR MAPK cascade in pheromone-dependent HOG activation, the experiment was repeated in &#x0394;<italic>fus3</italic> cells. Induction of the HOG reporter, as well as the increase in Hog1 dual phosphorylation, was diminished (figs. S6A and S14 and table S1). Although the PR and the Sho1 branch of the HOG system share components (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), deletion of the Sln1 branch components <italic>SSK1</italic> or <italic>SSK2</italic>, but not of <italic>SHO1</italic>, blocked reporter gene induction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>) as well as phosphorylation of Hog1 in response to pheromone (fig. S14 and table S1). Hence, only the Sln1 branch mediates pheromone-dependent activation of HOG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>).</p>
<p>We next determined whether activation of HOG by PR takes place during mating. We mixed <italic>MAT</italic>a reporter strains with <italic>MAT</italic>&#x03B1; cells, both preadapted to growth in high osmolarity. As with synthetic pheromone, the HOG reporter P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP in the <italic>MAT</italic>a strain showed increased activity (fig. S7). Together, these results suggest that during mating in high-osmolarity environments, the PR, through the Sln1 branch, activates HOG.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>PR activates HOG in bursts</title>
<p>In response to pheromone, average HOG reporter activity increased at a constant rate similar to that of the PR reporter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref> and fig. S4). However, at single-cell level, the two reporters behaved differently. Whereas cells induced the PR reporter steadily over time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>), the HOG reporter was regulated in a seemingly stochastic manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). In addition, the activity of these two reporters was not substantially correlated (fig. S8).</p>
<fig id="F4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption>
<title>Pheromone-dependent activation of HOG occurs in unsynchronized bursts.</title>
<p>WT (LD3342) cells were adapted to sorbitol, attached to a glass-bottom 96-well plate, and followed under a microscope after pheromone stimulation. (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) PR (A) or HOG (B) transcriptional output in single cells. Each trace corresponds to mCherry (P<sub><italic>PRM1</italic></sub>-mCherry; A) or YFP (P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP; B) fluorescence intensity over time, normalized to the maximum and minimum values for each cell. (<bold>C</bold>) Heat map representation of single-cell HOG transcriptional output time-course profiles. Cells were ordered (bottom up) on the basis of the time at which they showed their first burst of HOG activity, and those cells with equal burst time of first burst were sorted on the basis of their second burst. &#x0394;YFP/&#x0394;<italic>t</italic>, time derivative of the YFP fluorescence density. See also figs. S9 to S11.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="6_ra26_F4"></graphic></fig>
<p>To understand the mechanism of HOG activation, we identified cells with similar temporal expression patterns with an adapted hierarchical clustering approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32"><italic>32</italic></xref>). Individual cells were clustered in rows according to a similar P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP expression pattern over time (fig. S9A), which revealed that reporter induction was not random and occurred in transient bursts that typically lasted around 60 min. Cells exhibited bursts early or relatively late after pheromone stimulation. In general, there was a continuous temporal variation, from early to late bursts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>). Moreover, some cells exhibited more than one burst, separated by a variable interval (figs. S9B and S10).</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>PR activation of HOG coincides with shmooing</title>
<p>Inspection of individual time courses revealed that bursts in HOG activity usually occurred around the time a mating projection formed (shmooing) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref> and figs. S10 and S11). To analyze the overall population behavior, we calculated the time interval between the moment the shmoo was first evident and the peak in HOG reporter expression for each cell. We found a large distribution of intervals, with a mode of about 50 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>). To further support the idea that HOG activation occurs after shmooing, we correlated the onset of this shape change with the entry of Hog1 to the nucleus during PR and showed that pheromone-induced Hog1 translocation tends to occur after shmoos have formed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>). This sequence of events, during which shmooing formation precedes HOG activation, suggested that the former might be necessary for the latter.</p>
<fig id="F5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption>
<title>Pheromone-dependent activation of HOG correlates with shmooing.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Time course (left) of a cell with three bursts of HOG activity, selected from the time courses in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> (see also figs. S10 and S11). Plots show HOG and PR transcriptional output, overlaid with shmooing times (light purple L-shaped arrows mark shmooing periods, starting at the time each mating projection is first apparent). Photomontage (right) shows the bright-field time-lapse images used to determine the timing of shmooing. Numbers mark shmoos, and arrows highlight the position of the nascent mating projection in each cell. Accumulation of the HOG reporter is slightly delayed (about 30 to 40 min) from the time of shmooing because of the slow (40 min) maturation of YFP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>). Data represent the fluorescence intensity normalized to the maximum and minimum values. (<bold>B</bold>) Distribution of times between the first frame at which a shmoo was detectable and the time of the peak expression (highest &#x0394;YFP/&#x0394;<italic>t</italic>) of the subsequent HOG burst. (<bold>C</bold>) Heat map representation of single-cell Hog1-Venus nuclear localization time-course profiles from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>. Cells were ordered (bottom up) on the basis of the time they show their first shmoo (black dots). Data represent nuclear YFP over CFP signal at each time point, which is significantly higher after than before shmoo formation (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>).</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="6_ra26_F5"></graphic></fig>
<p>A requirement for shmooing in pheromone-dependent HOG activation would explain why cells do not activate HOG simultaneously, because cells reach the G<sub>1</sub> cell cycle stage, when shmooing can occur, at different times after pheromone addition. The timing of entry into G<sub>1</sub> correlated with the beginning of shmooing and the onset of HOG reporter expression (fig. S11). The dependence of HOG activation on shmooing would also explain why some cells exhibit more than one activation burst: Cells continuously exposed to pheromone develop new mating projections periodically. Although all bursts of HOG activity coincided with the formation of a mating projection, not all mating projections were accompanied by a burst in HOG activity (figs. S10 and S11).</p>
<p>We explored the possibility of a causal link between shmooing and HOG activation by testing if PR activation of HOG occurred exclusively in conditions that promote proper shmooing. The polarisome is a multiprotein complex required for this type of polarized cellular growth. &#x0394;<italic>spa2</italic> and &#x0394;<italic>pea2</italic> mutants lacking two polarisome components (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>) responded normally to pheromone and grew in a polarized manner but did not form the narrow, pointy shmoos characteristic of wild-type cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>, A and B). Addition of pheromone to either of these mutants resulted in reduced HOG activation. We further investigated the dose dependence of PR activation of HOG by exploiting the fact that the concentration of pheromone required for shmooing is larger than that required for full transcriptional induction of pheromone-inducible genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33"><italic>33</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34"><italic>34</italic></xref>). Therefore, if HOG activation required shmooing, the induction of the HOG reporter (P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP) should also require more pheromone for activation than the PR reporter (P<sub><italic>PRM1</italic></sub>-mCherry). Indeed, although maximum PR reporter expression required 10 nM pheromone, the HOG reporter required more than 30 nM. In addition, the dose-response curves of HOG reporter and of the fraction of cells exhibiting pointy shmoos were not significantly different (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>; for our shape classification criteria, see figs. S12 and S13). Together, the data indicate that pheromone-stimulated activation of HOG requires shmooing.</p>
<fig id="F6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption>
<title>Pheromone-dependent HOG activation requires an intact polarisome and the CWI MAPK Slt2.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) WT (LD3342 or RB3406), &#x0394;<italic>pea2</italic> (RB3862), &#x0394;<italic>spa2</italic> (RB3865), and &#x0394;<italic>slt2</italic> (RB3376a) cells were cultured as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, stimulated with pheromone, and collected for imaging in cycloheximide. Data represent the average HOG reporter expression &#x00B1; SEM. YFP (top) or CFP (bottom) fluorescence intensity per cell over time. HOG reporter expression is reduced in &#x0394;<italic>pea2</italic> (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>), &#x0394;<italic>spa2</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.0097), and &#x0394;<italic>slt2</italic> (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>) as compared to the correspondent WT strains. Images of each strain at time 0 and 300 min after pheromone stimulation are also shown. Note the typical &#x201C;peanut&#x201D; morphology of the polarisome mutants. (<bold>B</bold>) WT (LD3342) cells were cultured as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, stimulated with the indicated pheromone concentrations, and collected for imaging in cycloheximide. Data represent the average YFP (circles) or mCherry (diamonds) expression &#x00B1; SEM, normalized to maximum value (left <italic>y</italic> axis), or the percentage &#x00B1; SD of cells with the different mating projection morphology categories (from 1 to 4), aggregated as indicated (right <italic>y</italic> axis). The effective concentration of half maximal response (EC<sub>50</sub>) for the HOG output differs significantly from the PR output (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>), but not from the fraction of &#x201C;sharp shmoos&#x201D; (<italic>P</italic> = 0.64). Sample bright-field images are shown below the plot. Numbers on top of selected cells illustrate the morphology classification used (category 5 corresponds to dividing cells). Note that sharp shmoos (category 1) form only above 10 nM. Results from a representative experiment are shown (<italic>n</italic> &gt; 3). <italic>n</italic> ~ 700 cells for each data point. See also figs. S12 and S13.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="6_ra26_F6"></graphic></fig>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Activation of HOG by PR requires the CWI MAPK Slt2</title>
<p>The polarisome assists in activating the CWI MAPK cascade through the scaffold Spa2, which interacts and recruits to the shmoo tip Slt2 and its MAPK kinase Mkk1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35"><italic>35</italic></xref>). This process results in transient activation of Slt2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) during shmooing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>). Because phosphorylation of Slt2 after pheromone addition occurred at around the same time as Hog1 phosphorylation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref> and fig. S4), we hypothesized that activated Slt2 could be the signal that connected PR to the activation of HOG during shmooing. When &#x0394;<italic>slt2</italic> cells were adapted to high osmolarity and treated with pheromone, they formed normal shmoos but failed to activate HOG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>), indicating that morphogenesis is not sufficient to activate HOG and that Slt2 plays a critical role in this process. It also suggested that failure to activate Slt2 is the reason for the lack of activation of HOG in &#x0394;<italic>spa2</italic> cells. Consistent with this notion, phosphorylation of Slt2 was reduced in the polarisome mutants &#x0394;<italic>spa2</italic> and &#x0394;<italic>pea2</italic> as compared to wild-type (fig. S14)<italic>.</italic></p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>PR activates HOG by blocking a homeostatic negative feedback</title>
<p>The intracellular glycerol concentration is determined by the rates of synthesis, degradation, and efflux. Glycerol efflux occurs through the aquaglyceroporin Fps1, which has been implicated in cell fusion during mating (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36"><italic>36</italic></xref>). We speculated that pheromone might cause a rapid increase in glycerol efflux, thereby leading to a burst in HOG activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="F7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption>
<title>Pheromone activates HOG by stimulating glycerol loss.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic model of HOG activation by pheromone in cells growing in a high-osmolarity environment. Addition of pheromone (or the presence of a mating partner) activates the MAPK Fus3, leading to the mating projection formation (shmooing). The machinery involved in shmooing (the polarisome) and cell wall stress activate the CWI pathway and its MAPK Slt2. Activated Fus3 together with Slt2 increases glycerol loss. Intracellular glycerol is required to maintain normal turgor pressure (P&#x03C4;). The pheromone-induced loss of glycerol (E!) results in low turgor pressure and in activation of HOG, leading to a compensatory increase in the glycerol synthesis rate (S!) accomplished by HOG activity. (<bold>B</bold> to <bold>E</bold>) Testing four predictions of the model in (A). (B) Extracellular accumulation of glycerol. WT (LD3342) cells were cultured overnight in sorbitol and collected at the indicated times from cultures stimulated (squares) or not (diamonds) with pheromone to measure the amount of glycerol in the supernatant. Data represent the average concentration of glycerol in the supernatant divided by the number of cells at each time point (see fig. S15). Bars represent SD (<italic>n</italic> = 3 independent experiments). Glycerol production is significantly increased in pheromone-treated cells (<italic>P</italic> = 0.0028). (C) Replacement of sorbitol by glycerol as extracellular osmoticum. WT (LD3342) cells were cultured overnight in sorbitol (squares) or glycerol (triangles) and then stimulated with pheromone; samples were collected into cycloheximide at the indicated times to measure reporter expression by microscopy. The HOG reporter was induced in the sorbitol-adapted cells (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>), but not in the glycerol-adapted ones (<italic>P</italic> = 0.39). (D) Pheromone-mediated HOG activation requires the aquaglyceroporin Fps1. WT (LD3342), &#x0394;<italic>fps1</italic> (RB3396a), &#x0394;<italic>rgc1</italic> (RB3710), &#x0394;<italic>ask10</italic> (RB3717), and &#x0394;<italic>rgc1</italic> &#x0394;<italic>ask10</italic> (RB3722) cells were cultured overnight with 1 M sorbitol, stimulated with pheromone, and collected into cycloheximide to measure reporter gene expression by microscopy. All mutants had significantly lower HOG reporter transcription than WT cells (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>). (E) Pheromone-mediated HOG activation increases with increased external osmolarity. WT (LD3342) cells were cultured overnight with the indicated concentrations of sorbitol, stimulated with pheromone, and collected into cycloheximide to measure reporter gene expression by microscopy. YFP transcription rate increased with external osmolarity (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>). (C to E) Data represent the average YFP fluorescence intensity per cell &#x00B1; SEM of one representative experiment. <italic>n</italic> = 3 experiments in all panels. <italic>n</italic> ~ 700 cells for each data point. <italic>P</italic> values were calculated for the shown data.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="6_ra26_F7"></graphic></fig>
<p>Consistent with this idea, the extracellular glycerol concentration per cell increased to a greater extent in supernatants of cells treated with pheromone than in those of control cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>). To determine whether the release of glycerol was necessary for HOG activation, we reduced the chemical gradient of glycerol by using glycerol instead of sorbitol as the osmoticum. In this condition, pheromone treatment failed to activate HOG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7C</xref>). Moreover, in cells with diminished plasma membrane permeability for glycerol [deletion mutants for <italic>FPS1</italic> or either <italic>RGC1</italic> or <italic>ASK10</italic>, which encode proteins required for Fps1 opening (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17"><italic>17</italic></xref>)], pheromone did not activate HOG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7D</xref>). We further surmised that in cells adapted to osmolarities higher than 1 M sorbitol, because they need to accumulate more glycerol, pheromone treatment would lead to a larger outward flux of glycerol. Under these conditions, cells would compensate for glycerol loss by more strongly activating HOG. Indeed, PR-mediated activation of HOG increased with increasing concentrations of extracellular sorbitol (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7E</xref>). These experiments indicate that pheromone-stimulated glycerol loss through Fps1 is necessary for the activation of HOG.</p>
<p>We also monitored phosphorylation of Hog1 by Western blot in mutants with reduced reporter activity. Strains that showed reduced activation of the HOG transcriptional reporter in response to pheromone (&#x0394;<italic>rgc1</italic>, &#x0394;<italic>ask10</italic>, &#x0394;<italic>rgc1</italic>&#x0394;<italic>ask10</italic>, &#x0394;<italic>fps1</italic>, &#x0394;<italic>fus3</italic>, &#x0394;<italic>ssk1</italic>, &#x0394;<italic>ssk2</italic>, &#x0394;<italic>slt2</italic>, &#x0394;<italic>pea2</italic>, and &#x0394;<italic>spa2</italic>) also showed less increase in phosphorylation of Hog1 (fig. S14 and table S1). In contrast, these strains displayed a normal ability to activate HOG in response to a hyperosmotic shock (fig. S16), indicating that these proteins are specifically involved in PR activation of HOG. Finally, we tested whether these strains failed to activate HOG due to a defect in the PR system itself. However, expression of the PR reporter P<sub><italic>PRM1</italic></sub>-mCherry was similar in all mutants to wild-type, except for &#x0394;<italic>fus3</italic>, which lacks the main MAPK of the PR (figs. S6 and S14).</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Pheromone activation of HOG facilitates acute response to high osmolarity shock</title>
<p>Pheromone-mediated activation of glycerol efflux appears to lead to a new steady state in which cells maintain their intracellular concentration of glycerol by compensating for glycerol loss with increased rate of production (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A</xref>). Such regulation provides for faster turnover, enabling systems to adapt faster to changing signals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8B</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37"><italic>37</italic></xref>). Thus, we hypothesized that pheromone-treated osmoadapted cells might respond faster to further hyperosmotic stress. To test this idea, we shocked yeast adapted to sorbitol and pretreated with pheromone with NaCl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8C</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29"><italic>29</italic></xref>) and monitored their change in volume over time. Indeed, pheromone-treated cells recovered twice as fast as untreated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8D</xref>, left), although cells in both populations lost the same fraction of their initial volume after the NaCl shock. In contrast, &#x0394;<italic>rgc1</italic> cells, which cannot induce HOG in response to pheromone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7D</xref>), recovered their original volume at the same speed independently of pheromone treatment and comparably to untreated wild-type cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8D</xref>). Similarly, control cells grown without osmoticum recovered from a 0.65 M NaCl shock only slightly faster when pretreated with pheromone (fig. S17). Together, these results indicate that pheromone treatment results in an enhanced ability of cells to respond to osmotic shock.</p>
<fig id="F8" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption>
<title>Pheromone-stimulated cells display improved osmoadaptation.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Cells maintain an internal glycerol concentration, depending on the external osmolarity. In the absence of pheromone, glycerol concentration has a given turnover rate. Pheromone increases the rate of glycerol loss, accelerating its turnover rate. (<bold>B</bold>) The effect of turnover rate on the dynamics of a putative system in which molecule <italic>X</italic> is synthesized at a rate &#x03B2; and lost/degraded at a rate &#x03B1;, following the equation d<italic>X</italic>/d<italic>t</italic> = &#x03B2; &#x2212; &#x03B1;<italic>X</italic>. The plot shows the dynamics of this system starting at <italic>X</italic> = 0 for three different values of &#x03B2; and &#x03B1; (0.1, 0.05, and 0.025 in units of 1/time). The faster the turnover rate, the faster the system reaches steady state. (<bold>C</bold>) Cells cultured overnight in sorbitol were stimulated with pheromone, then NaCl was added, and cell volume was monitored by microscopy. (<bold>D</bold>) WT (LD3342) (left) or &#x0394;<italic>rgc1</italic> (RB3710) (right) cells. Data represent the average volume &#x00B1; SEM, normalized to time 0. The horizontal dotted line marks 50% volume recovery. The vertical dotted line marks the time at which this recovery was achieved. WT cells treated with pheromone recover faster than untreated cells (<italic>P</italic> = 0.0083), but &#x0394;<italic>rgc1</italic> do not (<italic>P</italic> = 0.88). See also fig. S16. <italic>n</italic> = 3 experiments.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="6_ra26_F8"></graphic></fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>We report a link between the pheromone and the high osmolarity response: In cells adapted to high osmolarity, pheromone leads to HOG activation. We demonstrate that this effect is not due to direct crosstalk but rather to pheromone-induced drop in turgor pressure, which in turn is caused by glycerol release, probably mediated by the MAPK Slt2. Consequently, a discrete morphogenetic event links all four yeast MAP kinases: Fus3 and Kss1 as part of the pheromone pathway as well as periodic activation of Slt2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>) and Hog1 (this work) by the morphogenetic changes induced by pheromone. Throughout the process, all MAPKs maintain proper responsiveness to their canonical stimulus.</p>
<p>A previous study did not detect the link between PR and HOG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24"><italic>24</italic></xref>). The discrepancy might be due to differences in experimental design, such as culture density. We have observed that PR activation of HOG is sensitive to this variable. In addition, we monitored HOG output at later time points and at higher external osmolarity. In one of the experiments reported by Patterson <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24"><italic>24</italic></xref>), HOG output seems to be higher in the costimulated sample, suggesting that HOG activation by PR actually occurs in this experiment.</p>
<p>The PR and HOG systems have been reported to inhibit each other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38"><italic>38</italic></xref>), but we and others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24"><italic>24</italic></xref>) have not been able to reproduce those results. In contrast, we detected a mild dampening of the PR pathway by high osmolarity, consistent with another report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31"><italic>31</italic></xref>). This diminished PR output may be due to Hog1-mediated inhibition of Ste50 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31"><italic>31</italic></xref>).</p>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Increased glycerol release may have several functions</title>
<p>We report here that pheromone stimulation of osmoadapted cells leads to a steady state with higher glycerol turnover. Such cells are able to adjust faster to changes in external osmolarity: Faced with a new osmotic shock, pheromone-treated cells recovered twice as fast than untreated cells. Such an advantage may justify the energy invested in seemingly futile cycles of synthesis and degradation or loss.</p>
<p>In general, the increased glycerol turnover should help cells to control turgor faster and more precisely through the opening and closing of Fps1. Fast and precise turgor control maybe important specifically during mating. In support of this view, inability to control the osmotic balance in &#x0394;<italic>fps1</italic> cells prevents mating at the prezygote step before cell wall degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36"><italic>36</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>There could be additional roles for the increased release of glycerol induced by pheromone. For example, altered medium viscosity caused by glycerol might affect the shape of the pheromone gradient. Also, the role of glycerol efflux in redox regulation may be relevant: Cells exposed to high pheromone concentrations produce increased amounts of reactive oxygen species (ROS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39"><italic>39</italic></xref>). High glycerol turnover provides an alternative path to mitochondrial reoxidation of NADH (reduced form of nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide), thus helping to reduce mitochondrial ROS production during mating. Consistent with this notion, cells with a deficient CWI pathway, which cannot activate HOG and thus are unable to increase the rate of glycerol turnover, produce increased ROS concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39"><italic>39</italic></xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>A cascade of MAPK cascades controls glycerol turnover rate</title>
<p>Mutations that prevent shmooing or that disrupt the CWI pathway greatly reduce pheromone-mediated HOG activation in osmoadapted cells. Because CWI is activated by shmooing, a straightforward interpretation is that HOG activation by PR is caused by the PR-stimulated CWI. This leads to the hypothesis that CWI might stimulate Fps1-mediated glycerol release, which causes HOG activation to compensate turgor loss. Because both CWI and Fps1 are required for adaptation to hypo-osmotic shock, it appears reasonable to propose that CWI controls Fps1-mediated glycerol release, although there is no experimental evidence to support it. Deletion of <italic>SLT2</italic> and <italic>FPS1</italic> causes synthetic lethality, which has been interpreted as genetic evidence that these two gene products act in parallel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36"><italic>36</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40"><italic>40</italic></xref>). On the other hand, <italic>slt2</italic> mutants display a weaker cell wall, which, in combination with a defect in glycerol release, explains the observed hyper-fragility of the <italic>slt2 fps1</italic> double mutant, without excluding a direct regulation of Fps1 by Slt2. Here, we report a condition in which the CWI pathway is required to activate HOG. Cell wall stress has been previously reported to activate the CWI pathway in a HOG-dependent manner through an osmolarity-independent mechanism that uses the Sho1 branch of HOG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41"><italic>41</italic></xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>The HOG pathway remains active after osmoadaptation</title>
<p>Our work highlights a role for HOG activity during growth under high osmolarity. The glycerol production machinery has been postulated to have &#x201C;memory&#x201D; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19"><italic>19</italic></xref>): HOG sets glycerol production to a desired amount during the acute response, which is later maintained without further HOG activity. In a continuously dividing cell population, this does not seem to be the case. Our findings suggest that although HOG activity peaks and declines after an osmolarity increase, HOG activity is sustained at an osmolarity-dependent amount to maintain appropriate glycerol accumulation. Thus, the dynamics of HOG does not display perfect adaptation. The need for a sustained osmolarity-dependent activity of HOG appears logical. When cell volume increases during growth, glycerol-producing enzymes would become diluted unless their synthesis matches the rate of volume change. It seems reasonable that HOG activity is continually required to maintain a high capacity for glycerol production with enhanced steady-state abundance of the enzymes involved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42"><italic>42</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43"><italic>43</italic></xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Not every shmoo results in a burst of HOG activity</title>
<p>Although PR-mediated HOG activation always coincides with mating projection formation, not all projections, even those of the same cell, lead to induction of the HOG transcriptional reporter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref> and figs. S10 and S11). This behavior could be due to stochastic transitions in the state of the chromatin at the loci inducible by Hog1 activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44"><italic>44</italic></xref>). Such stochastic effects are more evident when cells are exposed to mild osmostress, and indeed, the extent of Hog1 phosphorylation achieved after pheromone treatment is similar to a mild osmoshock (100 mM NaCl) (fig. S1B). Hence, HOG activity might burst in every cell during every shmoo, but this activity might not always be translated into enhanced gene expression, our experimental output. As an alternative explanation, glycerol might be released only during some of the shmooing events. We have previously shown that the activity of the PR system displays large cell-to-cell variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>). Given our findings that activation of HOG requires activation of two MAPK cascades, it is conceivable that cell-to-cell differences in the activity of components necessary for HOG activation result in some cells being unable to release glycerol.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Definition of pathways depends on context</title>
<p>A signaling pathway is commonly defined by a specific stimulus resulting in a distinct output. This experimental definition may not hold for many natural conditions. For instance, activation of the HOG pathway is not an output triggered by pheromone under low-osmolarity conditions. However, low osmolarity might not necessarily be a normal condition for yeast. Yeast thrives in environments with high sugar concentrations that constitute a high-osmolarity condition, such as grape juice, which has an osmolarity around 1 osM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45"><italic>45</italic></xref>), similar to the experimental conditions used in this study. Consequently, in such a condition, activation of the HOG pathway appears to be a normal output for the stimulus pheromone. Thus, in &#x201C;real life,&#x201D; classically defined pathways might operate in a far more flexible manner, using different connectivity depending on context.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Integration of signals in eukaryotic cells expands pathway&#x2019;s functions</title>
<p>As with yeast PR and HOG systems, which respond to different types of signals (developmental and stress), many apparently independent signaling pathways in eukaryotic cells might have evolved mechanisms of interaction. These mechanisms might only become apparent in the appropriate signaling context. The consequence of the activation of one system by another is to bring about different functional properties to the overall behavior. In the case presented here, the HOG system enables volume control during mating response. This type of interaction is likely to be common in multicellular eukaryotes, in both normal and pathological conditions. For example, growth factors and morphogens drive cellular and tissue differentiation, often involving cell shape changes, as well as changes in cell-cell and cell-matrix interactions. In turn, these mechanical stresses activate pathways that shape the response to the growth signal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46"><italic>46</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47"><italic>47</italic></xref>). Similarly, misregulation of this interplay between mechano- and growth factor&#x2013;initiated signaling might enhance cancer progression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48"><italic>48</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49"><italic>49</italic></xref>). Such multiple signals modulate one another, resulting in system-level behaviors that are hard to guess a priori. Understanding the nature and consequences of these interactions might help design new strategies that block (or enhance) the ability of one pathway to recruit another.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" disp-level="1">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Genetic and molecular biological methods</title>
<p>Nucleic acid and yeast manipulations were performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50"><italic>50</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51"><italic>51</italic></xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Yeast strains</title>
<p>Strains are detailed in table S2. ACL379 was used as the parental strain, which is a &#x0394;<italic>bar1</italic> strain derived from YAS245-5C (<italic>can1::HO-CAN1 ho::HO-ADE2 ura3 ade2 leu2 trp1 his3</italic>), which in turn is a W303-1a descendant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>LD3342 was constructed in three steps. First, we transformed ACL379 with plasmid pRS406-P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP, which bears the HOG-inducible reporter <italic>STL1</italic>. The plasmid was linearized with Afl II within the <italic>STL1</italic> promoter and transformed into yeast, and transformants were selected for uracil prototrophy. To make ACL3341, we replaced the open reading frame of <italic>PRM1</italic>, a pheromone-inducible gene, with mCherry. Replacement was achieved by homologous recombination using a polymerase chain reaction (PCR) product containing mCherry followed by a hygromycin resistance cassette, flanked by 40 nucleotides (nt) of homology with the borders of <italic>PRM1</italic> coding sequence. In a third step, we obtained LD3342 by transforming ACL3341 with plasmid pBMH2-CFP-404 linearized within the <italic>BMH2</italic> promoter using Nde I, and selecting transformants for uracil and tryptophan prototrophy. The resulting strain expressed CFP constitutively and maintained inducibility of YFP and mCherry.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Plasmids</title>
<p>pRS404-P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-CFP and pRS406-P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP were constructed as follows. As backbone, we used pTC414-CFP and pTC416-YFP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>), which are derivatives of pRS414 and pRS416 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52"><italic>52</italic></xref>) and contain the CEN-ARS (centromere and autonomously replicating sequence) region flanked by Aat II sites. pTC414-CFP and pTC416-YFP contain the <italic>GAL1</italic> promoter cloned between Acc 65I and Eco RI driving the expression of CFP or YFP, respectively. pTC414-CFP and pTC416-YFP were cut with Acc 65I and Eco RI, and the backbone was gel-purified from the <italic>GAL1</italic> promoter. In parallel, we PCR-amplified the <italic>STL1</italic> promoter region (&#x2212;950 to &#x2212;1 with respect to the START codon) using primers 5&#x2032; STL1p (ctcggaattaaccctcactaaagggaacaaaagctgggtaccCAGTCTGATATTACGAGCGAC) and 3&#x2032; STL1p (cagtgaaaagttcttctcctttactcatggatccgaattcGGTCTAAAACTTTCTATGTTCTA) and yeast genomic DNA as template. These primers contain a 40-nt tail (denoted by the lowercase letters) homologous to the ends of the purified backbone of pTC414-CFP and pTC416-YFP. The PCR product with the <italic>STL1</italic> promoter was cotransformed with either of the cut backbones into the ACL379 yeast strain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>), and colonies were selected on SC-Trp (SC medium lacking tryptophan) or SC-Ura plates. Plasmids were recovered from colonies that expressed CFP or YFP in 1 M NaCl SC medium. CEN-ARS from these plasmids were removed by digestion with Aat II and religated to create pRS404-P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-CFP and pRS406-P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP. pRS404-P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-CFP or pRS406-P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP was used to integrate the <italic>STL1</italic> promoter driving CFP or YFP, at the <italic>TRP</italic>1 and <italic>URA3</italic> locus, respectively. pP<italic><sub><sc>BMH2</sc></sub></italic>-CFP-TRP1 was used to integrate the P<sub><italic>BMH2</italic></sub>-CFP construct at the <italic>BMH2</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>). <italic>fps1</italic>&#x0394;<italic>::HIS3</italic>-long was used to delete <italic>FPS1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42"><italic>42</italic></xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Single-cell microscopy methods</title>
<p>Cultures were maintained in exponential growth for at least 15 hours. We typically inoculated two or three cultures with different amount of cells to ensure that after overnight growth at 30&#x00B0;C with agitation, at least one of the cultures was at an absorbance (<italic>A</italic><sub>600 nm</sub>) between 0.05 and 0.1. This low absorbance minimizes cellular autofluorescence, especially in the vacuole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53"><italic>53</italic></xref>). In addition, we have observed that PR activation of the HOG reporter is reduced in cultures at absorbances higher than 0.3.</p>
<p>For samples taken at different times from a liquid culture, cycloheximide was added to samples at a final concentration of 100 &#x03BC;g/ml, and cells were incubated for at least 3 hours before imaging, which stops further translation but allows for full maturation of the reporter fluorescent proteins YFP, CFP, and mCherry produced at each given time point (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27"><italic>27</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>For movies, cultures were sonicated to disperse clumps, and 100 &#x03BC;l of cell suspension (~10<sup>6</sup> cells) was applied to 96-well glass-bottom plates that had been precoated with concanavalin A type V (Sigma-Aldrich; 10 &#x03BC;g per well). After allowing yeast to settle and attach for 10 min, unbound cells were washed off. At this point, we manually selected three or more image fields per well, acquired time 0 images, replaced the medium with fresh medium containing &#x03B1; factor (Sigma-Aldrich), and started time-lapse imaging.</p>
<p>For imaging, a 60&#x00D7; PlanApo objective [numerical aperture (NA), 1.4] was used under oil immersion in an Olympus IX81 inverted microscope equipped with a mercury lamp, a motorized XYZ stage, and a CoolSnapHQ2 cooled charge-coupled device camera (Photometrix) in a 30&#x00B0;C room. We automatically and repeatedly imaged multiple wells over time using MetaMorph 7.5 software (Universal Imaging Corporation). MetaMorph was also used to control the built-in motorized XYZ motor and cube changer.</p>
<p>To avoid nonspecific binding of &#x03B1; factor to plastic, &#x03B1; factor was prepared in BSM (Q-Bio gene, MP Biomedicals) medium containing casein (20 &#x03BC;g/ml) as a blocking reagent (from the DIG Nucleic Acid Detection Kit, Roche Diagnostics Corporation). Blocking nonspecific adsorption enabled reproducibility when performing experiments with low doses of &#x03B1; factor.</p>
<p>For each time and field, we acquired a bright-field image and mCherry, YFP, and CFP fluorescence images using filter sets 41004, 31044v2, and 41028 from Chroma Technologies Corp.</p>
<p>To extract quantitative information, we processed images with VCell-ID as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28"><italic>28</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29"><italic>29</italic></xref>). Data extracted from VCell-ID were further analyzed using R (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org">http://www.r-project.org</ext-link>) and the package Rcell (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/Rcell/index.html">http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/Rcell/index.html</ext-link>).</p>
<p>To calculate the transcriptional output of each pathway per cell (defined as the total corrected fluorescence signal in a cell from the corresponding reporter gene), the background signal measured outside the cells was subtracted from the integrated total fluorescence for a given cell (the sum of the fluorescence values of all the pixels that VCell-ID associated with that cell).</p>
<p>To quantify the nuclear localization of Hog1, we acquired images in an Olympus IX81 inverted microscope coupled to a spectral confocal module FV1000 (Olympus) with a 60&#x00D7; 1.35 NA oil immersion objective. Excitation and filters were as follows: for Hta2-CFP, excitation 458 nm, emission 470 to 510 nm; for Hog1-Quadruple-Venus, excitation 515 nm, emission 530 to 630 nm. Different channels were acquired sequentially in Kalman line filtering mode. The pinhole diameter was 300 &#x03BC;m. We acquired six Z slices with a 0.21-&#x03BC;m step to obtain maximum fluorescence corresponding to the focal plane of the nucleus. Images were processed in VCell-ID, and the fluorescent nuclear tag was specified as the CFP channel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29"><italic>29</italic></xref>). We used the variables <italic>f.nucl4.y</italic> (quantifies the fluorescence of a disc with a radius of 5 pixels) and <italic>a.nucl4.y</italic> for the nuclear fluorescence and nuclear area, respectively. We used <italic>f.tot.y</italic> minus <italic>f.nucl6.y</italic> and <italic>a.tot</italic> minus <italic>a.nucl6</italic> to estimate the fluorescence and the area of the cytoplasm, respectively. <italic>f.tot.y</italic> corresponds to the yellow fluorescence of all pixels inside the cell. <italic>f.nucl6.y</italic> accounts for all the nuclear fluorescence in all cells analyzed (fig. S2). Because the equatorial planes of cells were at slightly different Z positions, resulting in different cells having their maximum fluorescence intensity in different Z slices, and because nuclei are not necessarily located at the equatorial plane of each cell, we used Rcell&#x2019;s function &#x201C;append.in.focus&#x201D; to find the nucleus focal plane for each cell. This plane is defined as the one that maximizes <italic>f.nucl1.c</italic>.</p>
<p>To analyze a large number of cells for statistical analysis, we sampled seven different fields. Because the time courses were long, we started the movies with a low number of cells in each field to avoid cells dividing and growing too close to each other. After VCell-ID processing, we used Rcell to filter cells that were recognized with incorrect boundaries and cells that were not recognized in most of the time points of the movies. We preferred using YFP density variable because it is more robust to cell boundary artifacts. After filtering, 200 cells were analyzed.</p>
<p>Hierarchical clustering of the cells was performed with the software &#x201C;Gene cluster 3.0&#x201D; (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bonsai.hgc.jp/~mdehoon/software/cluster/">http://bonsai.hgc.jp/~mdehoon/software/cluster/</ext-link>). Cells were clustered with the following variable for each cell:<disp-formula><mml:math display="block" id="m1"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x0394;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>YFP</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x00A0;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>density</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x0394;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>time</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></disp-formula>which corresponds to the change in the abundance of the HOG reporter from time <italic>i</italic> and time <italic>i</italic> &#x2212; 1.</p>
<p>Several similarity metrics and clustering methods were tested with the conclusion that the &#x201C;centered correlation&#x201D; metric clustered using the &#x201C;average linkage&#x201D; algorithm worked best to separate the different group of cells.</p>
<p>To determine the HOG bursts in single-cell time courses, we calculated the time of YFP fluorescence increase (time of burst) by applying a local polynomial regression fitting (loess) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54"><italic>54</italic></xref>) to the time-dependent YFP fluorescence signal of each cell, calculating the time derivative of the smoothed traces, and selecting the local maxima of these derivatives as the time for a burst. The time of shmoo formation was manually annotated for a random subset of cells on the basis of the transmission images.</p>
<p>To quantify mating projection morphology, we assigned shape categories as shown in fig. S12. A &#x201C;shmoo&#x201D; was defined as those cells presenting a sharp mating projection with concave curvatures in its base (category 1). The fractions of shmoos and the other morphologies were quantified with the ImageJ plug-in &#x201C;cell counter.&#x201D; We provide the images with the labels used in the quantitation (fig. S13).</p>
<p>We measured volume recovery as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55"><italic>55</italic></xref>). Briefly, we acquired a Z-stack of eight slices of 0.4 &#x03BC;m covering 2 &#x03BC;m on either side of the focused image. Images were acquired for 10 min to quantify the pre-shock volumes of the pheromone-stimulated or control cells. Cells were then stimulated by hyperosmotic shock, which resulted in a 30-s gap in the time lapse. We then acquired images every minute for 100 to 120 min. For each Z stack, we selected the picture in focus as follows. The &#x201C;Kurtosis coefficient&#x201D; of the distribution of pixel intensities of bright-field images calculated by ImageJ (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/">http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>) shows a maximum at the slice of the bright-field picture that is in focus. In addition, the SD of this pixel distribution presents a minimum value in the picture that is in focus. Thus, we created a new variable in R called &#x201C;kurtosis.focus&#x201D; that is 0 (zero) for the image in focus (maximum kurtosis) and increases for images of slices above focus (for example, 1, 2, 3, and so on) and decreases for images below focus (for example, &#x2212;1, &#x2212;2, &#x2212;3, and so on). The defocused images 1.2 &#x03BC;m below the focal plane were processed using VCell-ID. We used the VCell-ID variable <italic>sphere.vol</italic> to quantify cell volume.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Protein methods</title>
<p>Samples were prepared with a modified protocol of Yu <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53"><italic>53</italic></xref>). For each time point, 5.0 ml of exponentially growing cells (<italic>A</italic><sub>600 nm</sub> &#x2264; 0.3) were mixed with 412.5 &#x03BC;l of 10 M NaOH and 50 &#x03BC;l of 100% 2-mercaptoethanol (premixed immediately before the experiment). Samples were incubated at room temperature for at least 5 min, then 750 &#x03BC;l of 100% trichloroacetic acid (Sigma-Aldrich) was added. The mixture was incubated on ice for at least 10 min. The samples were sedimented at 4500<italic>g</italic> for 30 min at 4&#x00B0;C the supernatant was aspirated, and 700 &#x03BC;l of ice-cold acetone solution [70% (v/v) acetone in 100 mM tris-HCl, pH 6.8] was added, and the samples were incubated for 5 min on ice. The pellet was sonicated for 20 s at 40% amplitude (Sonic Dismembrator, Fisher Scientific), transferred to a microfuge tube and sedimented at &gt;16,000<italic>g</italic> for 2 min, aspirated, and air-dried.</p>
<p>For protein quantitation, samples were prepared by resuspending the pellets in 40 &#x03BC;l of resuspension buffer [100 mM tris (pH 8.8), 3% SDS] at 65&#x00B0;C for 30 min and in a disruptor genie (Scientific Industries) for 2 min, followed by centrifugation for 10 min at &gt;16,000<italic>g</italic> (at 4&#x00B0;C) to clear cellular debris before quantitation. Protein concentration was quantified with the BCA Protein Assay Kit (Pierce catalog no. 23225).</p>
<p>After quantitation, protein solutions were mixed with an equal volume of SDS&#x2013;polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis loading buffer [10 mM tris (pH 6.8), 0.002% bromophenol blue, 100 mM dithiothreitol, 2% SDS, 50% glycerol], boiled for 5 min, and loaded onto the electrophoresis gel.</p>
<p>Protein samples were separated with 12% tris-HCl/glycine polyacrylamide gels (Bio-Rad), then transferred onto a 0.2-&#x03BC;m Immobilon-FL polyvinylidene difluoride membrane (IPFL00010, Millipore). Membranes were blocked for at least 1 hour at room temperature in tris-buffered saline [TBS; 10 mM tris (pH 7.4), 150 mM NaCl] plus 1/10th volume of Western Blocking Reagent (WBR) (Roche). Phosphorylated MAPKs Fus3, Kss1, and Mpk1/Slt2 were detected with rabbit anti&#x2013;phospho-p44/p42 at 1:1000 dilution (Cell Signaling Technology, catalog no. 9101 L). Hog1 was detected with mouse anti&#x2013;phospho-p38 at 1:1000 dilution (Cell Signaling Technology, catalog no. 9216 L), which detects only dually phosphorylated MAPK, in primary antibody binding buffer (TBS, 1/10th volume WBR, and 0.05% Tween). Total Hog1 was detected with anti-Hog1 (yC-20 SC-6815) at 1:5000 dilution (Santa Cruz Biotechnology Inc.). GAPDH was detected with a 1:10,000 dilution of mouse anti-GAPDH antibody (Sigma, catalog no. A9521-1VL). Blots were washed in TBS with 0.05% Tween and probed for 1 hour at room temperature with 800 nm donkey anti-rabbit [926-32213 IRDye 800CW Donkey Anti-Rabbit IgG (H+L), Li-Cor Biosciences], 800 nm donkey anti-mouse [926-32212 IRDye 800CW Donkey Anti-Mouse IgG (H+L), Li-Cor Biosciences], and 680 nm donkey anti-goat [926-68074 IRDye 680RD Donkey Anti-Goat IgG (H+L)] fluorophore-conjugated secondary antibodies (Invitrogen), diluted 1:15,000 in secondary antibody binding buffer (TBS, 1/20th volume WBR, 0.05% Tween). Blots were washed in TBS and then scanned on a Li-Cor infrared imaging system (Li-Cor Biosciences). Band intensities were quantified with Odyssey ImageStudio software (Li-Cor Biosciences) using median top/bottom background correction.</p>
<p>For some experiments, we used peroxidase-labeled secondary antibodies (1:10,000, Bio-Rad), incubated for 1 hour at room temperature in TBS with 1/20th volume of WBR and 0.05% Tween. After washing three times (10 min each) in TBS at room temperature, blots were developed with the Pierce SuperSignal ECL Western Blotting Detection Reagents (catalog no. 34075) with a luminescence image analyzer (LAS-1000, FujiFilm).</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Glycerol measurements</title>
<p>Yeast cells were grown overnight in SC medium with 1 M sorbitol at 30&#x00B0;C starting with an absorbance such that on the following day, the absorbance was 0.2. The culture was filtered (cellulose ester filtering discs of 0.45-&#x03BC;m pore size and 25-mm diameter; Millipore, catalog no. HAWP02500) in a &#x201C;1225 manifold&#x201D; (Millipore, catalog no. XX2702550) and resuspended in fresh medium. This step is necessary to remove glycerol produced before the experiment. Cells were divided into two cultures of 30 ml. One of these cultures was treated with 5 &#x03BC;M &#x03B1; factor. As a reference value for glycerol release, cells were subjected to a hypo-osmotic shock to induce release of glycerol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16"><italic>16</italic></xref>) by resuspending 6.5 ml of the filtered untreated culture in SC medium without sorbitol at 0, 100, 200, and 300 min of the time-course experiment. The samples were evaporated in a Speed-Vac for 30 min to remove ethanol, dialysis-filtered with Amicom Ultra &lt;3 kD (UFC500396, Millipore) to remove high&#x2013;molecular weight compounds, and subjected to high-performance liquid chromatography for glycerol quantification.</p>
<p>In the same experiments, we collected samples at 0, 50, 100, 150, 200, 250, and 300 min; added cycloheximide to a final concentration of 100 &#x03BC;g/ml; measured absorbance; and imaged cells to quantify cell volume and reporter expression.</p>
<p>The concentration of glycerol was measured by high-pH anion exchange chromatography with pulse amperometric detection in an ICS-3000 chromatographic system (Dionex), as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56"><italic>56</italic></xref>). We used a CarboPac MA1 column (4 &#x00D7; 250 mm, Dionex) and a CarboPac MA1 guard column (4 &#x00D7; 50 mm, Dionex). An isocratic program with 200 mM NaOH was used at a flow rate of 0.5 ml/min and a loop of 20 &#x03BC;l. The standard curve was measured between 0 and 4000 ng of glycerol. Samples were diluted as necessary to obtain data in this range.</p>
<p>The following mathematical transformation was used to calculate the amount of glycerol produced per cell.<disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math display="block" id="m2"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Glycerol</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>pmol</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Cell</mml:mtext></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tx</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow>
    <mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Glycerol</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tx</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>ng</mml:mtext><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00B5;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>OD</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>tx</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x00D7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>OD</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x00D7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mtext>cells</mml:mtext><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>ml</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">V</mml:mi><mml:mtext>rel</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x00D7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>rel</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>tx</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x00D7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x00A0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00B5;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x00A0;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>ml</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>where <italic>V</italic><sub>rel<sub>tx</sub></sub> is the relative volume of cells at a certain time (<italic>tx</italic>) relative to the volume of cells at time 0. In fig. S15, changes in cell number and cell volume over time are shown for these experiments.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Osmolarity determination</title>
<p>The osmolarity of all media was measured with a Vapro 5520 osmometer (Wescor Inc.).</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Halo assays</title>
<p>Halo assays were performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50"><italic>50</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51"><italic>51</italic></xref>). Briefly, 10<sup>6</sup> cells were plated on agar plates with different media: SC or SC supplemented with either sorbitol, mannitol, or glycerol at several concentrations. After plating the cells, a sterile disc of Whatman paper (5-mm diameter) was placed in the middle of the petri dish, and 3 &#x03BC;l of 1 mM &#x03B1; factor was applied.</p>
</sec>
<sec disp-level="2">
<title>Statistical methods</title>
<p>Several statistical methods were used throughout this work. For the analysis of fluorescence transcriptional reporters (P<sub><italic>STL1</italic></sub>-YFP, P<sub><italic>PRM1</italic></sub>-mCherry) and localization reporters (Hog1-Venus) and for the analysis of Western blots data, linear mixed-effects models were fitted to the data using the <italic>nlme</italic> package for R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57"><italic>57</italic></xref>). When analyzing the dependence of a response variable with a continuous covariate (namely, time or osmolality), a polynomial model of adequate order was used. As examples, a cubic term was needed to fit the data of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>, and linear terms on the variables were required to fit the data of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>.</p>
<p>Random effects were used to explain systematic differences among repetitions of an experiment. For example, if three repetitions of a Western blot were done in three independent gels, a random &#x201C;gel effect&#x201D; was used to account for gel-to-gel variations (that might derive from small differences in incubation times, antibody concentrations, etc.). This procedure reduces the unexplained variability and therefore increases the power of the analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57"><italic>57</italic></xref>). Tukey&#x2019;s multiple comparisons were implemented with the <italic>multcomp</italic> package for R when required. The quality of the fits was inspected visually by comparing the predicted values with the measured data and by looking at the distribution of the residuals. Models that account for heteroscedastic data were used when appropriate.</p>
<p>The dose-response curves in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref> were independently fitted by nonlinear least squares to Hill functions, and the EC<sub>50</sub> values were compared on the basis of the estimated values and SEs.</p>
<p>To test whether there was a significant correlation between the time of shmoo formation and the increase in nuclear Hog1-Venus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>), a permutation analysis was done. The integral of the nuclear Hog1-Venus to Hta2-CFP ratio after the time of shmoo was used as a statistic (region to the right of the dotted line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>). The distribution of the statistic under the null hypothesis was calculated by permutations of the time of shmoo formation between cells. Only 1 of the 10,000 permutations resulted in a value greater than the one observed. Similar results are obtained with other statistics.</p>
<p>For the volume recovery experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8D</xref> and fig. S17), the volume traces for each cell were smoothed with a loess regression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54"><italic>54</italic></xref>), and the ET<sub>25</sub> (effective time it takes each cell to recover 25% of the volume lost after the shock) were calculated. A mixed-effects model was fitted to the distribution of ET<sub>25</sub>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back><app-group><app>
<title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencesignaling.org/cgi/content/full/6/272/ra26/DC1">www.sciencesignaling.org/cgi/content/full/6/272/ra26/DC1</ext-link></p>
<p>Fig. S1. Behavior of the constitutive control reporter in cells adapted to high external osmolarity and comparison of Hog1 phosphorylation in cells acutely shocked and cells adapted to high osmotic strength media.</p>
<p>Fig. S2. Quantification criteria for Hog1 subcellular localization.</p>
<p>Fig. S3. Hog1-Venus nuclear localization at different external osmolarities in single cells.</p>
<p>Fig. S4. PR outputs during HOG activation induced by &#x03B1; factor.</p>
<p>Fig. S5. &#x0394;<italic>hog1</italic> cells do not induce P<italic><sub>STL1</sub>-YFP</italic> in response to pheromone.</p>
<p>Fig. S6. Fus3 is necessary for the pheromone-induced activation of HOG.</p>
<p>Fig. S7. HOG transcriptional output is induced during mating in high external osmolarity.</p>
<p>Fig. S8. Large cell-to-cell variability in the pheromone-dependent activation of HOG.</p>
<p>Fig. S9. Alternative ordering of cells on the basis of HOG transcriptional bursts and the timing of shmoo formation.</p>
<p>Fig. S10. Correlation between shmooing and HOG output during pheromone-dependent HOG activation.</p>
<p>Fig. S11. The effect of the cell cycle position on the timing of HOG activation by pheromone.</p>
<p>Fig. S12. Mating projection classification and their distribution in response to different pheromone concentrations.</p>
<p>Fig. S13. Examples of mating projection classification at different pheromone concentrations.</p>
<p>Fig. S14. Quantification of MAPK phosphorylation in wild-type and mutant strains in response to pheromone.</p>
<p>Fig. S15. Additional data from the extracellular glycerol accumulation experiments.</p>
<p>Fig. S16. HOG reporter activation in wild-type and mutant strains in response to an acute hyperosmotic shock.</p>
<p>Fig. S17. Additional volume recovery experiments.</p>
<p>Table S1. Statistical analysis of phosphorylation of MAPKs related to fig. S14.</p>
<p>Table S2. Yeast strains.</p></supplementary-material></app></app-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Osmotic stress signaling and osmoadaptation in yeasts.</article-title> <source>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev.</source> 
<volume>66</volume>, 
<fpage>300</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>372</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Regulation of cell wall biogenesis in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>: The cell wall integrity signaling pathway.</article-title> <source>Genetics</source> 
<volume>189</volume>, 
<fpage>1145</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1175</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohlman</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorner</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Regulation of G protein-initiated signal transduction in yeast: Paradigms and principles.</article-title> <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source> 
<volume>70</volume>, 
<fpage>703</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>754</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madhani</surname><given-names>H. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The control of filamentous differentiation and virulence in fungi.</article-title> <source>Trends Cell Biol.</source> 
<volume>8</volume>, 
<fpage>348</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>353</lpage> (<year>1998</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marton</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoughton</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyers</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boone</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friend</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Signaling and circuitry of multiple MAPK pathways revealed by a matrix of global gene expression profiles.</article-title> <source>Science</source> 
<volume>287</volume>, 
<fpage>873</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>880</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chenevert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valtz</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herskowitz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Identification of genes required for normal pheromone-induced cell polarization in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title> <source>Genetics</source> 
<volume>136</volume>, 
<fpage>1287</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1296</lpage> (<year>1994</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Errede</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cade</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yashar</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamada</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Irie</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Dynamics and organization of MAP kinase signal pathways.</article-title> <source>Mol. Reprod. Dev.</source> 
<volume>42</volume>, 
<fpage>477</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>485</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buehrer</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Errede</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Coordination of the mating and cell integrity mitogen-activated protein kinase pathways in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title> <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source> 
<volume>17</volume>, 
<fpage>6517</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6525</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zarzov</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzoni</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The SLT2(MPK1) MAP kinase is activated during periods of polarized cell growth in yeast.</article-title> <source>EMBO J.</source> 
<volume>15</volume>, 
<fpage>83</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>91</lpage> (<year>1996</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lages</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albertyn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilian</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Characteristics of Fps1-dependent and -independent glycerol transport in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title> <source>J. Bacteriol.</source> 
<volume>179</volume>, 
<fpage>7790</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7795</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Nadal</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ammerer</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Posas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Controlling gene expression in response to stress.</article-title> <source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source> 
<volume>12</volume>, 
<fpage>833</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>845</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatebayashi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Dynamic control of yeast MAP kinase network by induced association and dissociation between the Ste50 scaffold and the Opy2 membrane anchor.</article-title> <source>Mol. Cell</source> 
<volume>40</volume>, 
<fpage>87</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>98</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Posas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Activation of the yeast SSK2 MAP kinase kinase kinase by the SSK1 two-component response regulator.</article-title> <source>EMBO J.</source> 
<volume>17</volume>, 
<fpage>1385</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1394</lpage> (<year>1998</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrigno</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Posas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koepp</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Regulated nucleo/cytoplasmic exchange of HOG1 MAPK requires the importin &#x03B2; homologs NMD5 and XPO1.</article-title> <source>EMBO J.</source> 
<volume>17</volume>, 
<fpage>5606</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5614</lpage> (<year>1998</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x2019;Rourke</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herskowitz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Unique and redundant roles for HOG MAPK pathway components as revealed by whole-genome expression analysis.</article-title> <source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source> 
<volume>15</volume>, 
<fpage>532</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>542</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albertyn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skibbe</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thevelein</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Fps1, a yeast member of the MIP family of channel proteins, is a facilitator for glycerol uptake and efflux and is inactive under osmotic stress.</article-title> <source>EMBO J.</source> 
<volume>14</volume>, 
<fpage>1360</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1371</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beese</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Negishi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Identification of positive regulators of the yeast fps1 glycerol channel.</article-title> <source>PLoS Genet.</source> 
<volume>5</volume>, 
<fpage>e1000738</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, &#x03B1;
<article-title>-Factor inhibition of the rate of cell passage through the &#x201C;start&#x201D; step of cell division in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> yeast: Estimation of the division delay per &#x03B1;-factor receptor complex.</article-title> <source>Exp. Cell Res.</source> 
<volume>171</volume>, 
<fpage>411</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>425</lpage> (<year>1987</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muzzey</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x00F3;mez-Uribe</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mettetal</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Oudenaarden</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A systems-level analysis of perfect adaptation in yeast osmoregulation.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> 
<volume>138</volume>, 
<fpage>160</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>171</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miermont</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhlendorf</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McClean</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hersen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The dynamical systems properties of the HOG signaling cascade.</article-title> <source>J. Signal Transduct.</source> 
<volume>2011</volume>, 
<fpage>930940</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Expression studies of <italic>GUP1</italic> and <italic>GUP2</italic>, genes involved in glycerol active transport in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, using semi-quantitative RT-PCR.</article-title> <source>Curr. Genet.</source> 
<volume>46</volume>, 
<fpage>140</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>146</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Posas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Osmotic activation of the HOG MAPK pathway via Ste11p MAPKKK: Scaffold role of Pbs2p MAPKK.</article-title> <source>Science</source> 
<volume>276</volume>, 
<fpage>1702</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1705</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x2019;Rourke</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herskowitz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The Hog1 MAPK prevents cross talk between the HOG and pheromone response MAPK pathways in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title> <source>Genes Dev.</source> 
<volume>12</volume>, 
<fpage>2874</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2886</lpage> (<year>1998</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klimenko</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Single-cell analysis reveals that insulation maintains signaling specificity between two yeast MAPK pathways with common components.</article-title> <source>Sci. Signal.</source> 
<volume>3</volume>, 
<fpage>ra75</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westfall</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Stress resistance and signal fidelity independent of nuclear MAPK function.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>105</volume>, 
<fpage>12212</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12217</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heiman</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Prm1p, a pheromone-regulated multispanning membrane protein, facilitates plasma membrane fusion during yeast mating.</article-title> <source>J. Cell Biol.</source> 
<volume>151</volume>, 
<fpage>719</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>730</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colman-Lerner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Resnekov</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Endy</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pesce</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Regulated cell-to-cell variation in a cell-fate decision system.</article-title> <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>437</volume>, 
<fpage>699</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>706</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colman-Lerner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Single-cell quantification of molecules and rates using open-source microscope-based cytometry.</article-title> <source>Nat. Methods</source> 
<volume>4</volume>, 
<fpage>175</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>181</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chernomoretz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colman-Lerner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Using Cell-ID 1.4 with R for microscope-based cytometry.</article-title> <source>Curr. Protoc. Mol. Biol.</source> 
<volume>Chapter 14</volume>, 
<fpage>Unit 14.18</fpage> (<year>2008</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karlgren</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettersson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordlander</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathai</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodsky</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeidel</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bill</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Conditional osmotic stress in yeast: A system to study transport through aquaglyceroporins and osmostress signaling.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>280</volume>, 
<fpage>7186</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7193</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagiec</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohlman</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Checkpoints in a yeast differentiation pathway coordinate signaling during hyperosmotic stress.</article-title> <source>PLoS Genet.</source> 
<volume>8</volume>, 
<fpage>e1002437</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spellman</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>P. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Cluster analysis and display of genome-wide expression patterns.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>95</volume>, 
<fpage>14863</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>14868</lpage> (<year>1998</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Comparison of dose-response curves for &#x03B1; factor-induced cell division arrest, agglutination, and projection formation of yeast cells. Implication for the mechanism of &#x03B1; factor action.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>258</volume>, 
<fpage>13849</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>13856</lpage> (<year>1983</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pryciak</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartwell</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title><italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> cells execute a default pathway to select a mate in the absence of pheromone gradients.</article-title> <source>J. Cell Biol.</source> 
<volume>131</volume>, 
<fpage>845</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>861</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Drogen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Spa2p functions as a scaffold-like protein to recruit the Mpk1p MAP kinase module to sites of polarized growth.</article-title> <source>Curr. Biol.</source> 
<volume>12</volume>, 
<fpage>1698</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1703</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Philips</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herskowitz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Osmotic balance regulates cell fusion during mating in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title> <source>J. Cell Biol.</source> 
<volume>138</volume>, 
<fpage>961</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>974</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="book">U. Alon, <italic>An Introduction to Systems Biology: Design Principles of Biological Circuits</italic> (Chapman &amp; Hall, Boca Raton, FL, 2006).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClean</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mody</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Broach</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramanathan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Cross-talk and decision making in MAP kinase pathways.</article-title> <source>Nat. Genet.</source> 
<volume>39</volume>, 
<fpage>409</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>414</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudgeon</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paliwal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levchenko</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grote</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>K. W.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Multiple signaling pathways regulate yeast cell death during the response to mating pheromones.</article-title> <source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source> 
<volume>17</volume>, 
<fpage>3409</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3422</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R40"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamas</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albertyn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valadi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilian</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thevelein</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Fps1p controls the accumulation and release of the compatible solute glycerol in yeast osmoregulation.</article-title> <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source> 
<volume>31</volume>, 
<fpage>1087</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1104</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R41"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez-Pe&#x00F1;a</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nombela</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arroyo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The high-osmolarity glycerol (HOG) and cell wall integrity (CWI) signalling pathways interplay: A yeast dialogue between MAPK routes.</article-title> <source>Yeast</source> 
<volume>27</volume>, 
<fpage>495</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>502</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R42"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rep</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albertyn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thevelein</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>,
<article-title> Different signalling pathways contribute to the control of <italic>GPD1</italic> gene expression by osmotic stress in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title> <source>Microbiology</source> 
<volume>145</volume>, (<supplement>Pt. 3</supplement>)
<fpage>715</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>727</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R43"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klipp</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordlander</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x00FC;ger</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gennemark</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Integrative model of the response of yeast to osmotic shock.</article-title> <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source> 
<volume>23</volume>, 
<fpage>975</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>982</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R44"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelet</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudolf</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadal-Ribelles</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Nadal</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Posas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Transient activation of the HOG MAPK pathway regulates bimodal gene expression.</article-title> <source>Science</source> 
<volume>332</volume>, 
<fpage>732</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>735</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R45"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wendland</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbus</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Oral fluid therapy: Sodium and potassium content and osmolality of some commercial &#x201C;clear&#x201D; soups, juices and beverages.</article-title> <source>Can. Med. Assoc. J.</source> 
<volume>121</volume>, 
<fpage>564</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>566, 568, 571</lpage> (<year>1979</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R46"><label>46</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Streuli</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Signal co-operation between integrins and other receptor systems.</article-title> <source>Biochem. J.</source> 
<volume>418</volume>, 
<fpage>491</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>506</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R47"><label>47</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bill</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moores</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muthuswamy</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>V. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugge</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miranti</surname><given-names>C. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Epidermal growth factor receptor-dependent regulation of integrin-mediated signaling and cell cycle entry in epithelial cells.</article-title> <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source> 
<volume>24</volume>, 
<fpage>8586</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8599</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R48"><label>48</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butcher</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alliston</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A tense situation: Forcing tumour progression.</article-title> <source>Nat. Rev. Cancer</source> 
<volume>9</volume>, 
<fpage>108</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>122</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R49"><label>49</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boudreau</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bissell</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Tissue architecture and function: Dynamic reciprocity via extra- and intra-cellular matrices.</article-title> <source>Cancer Metastasis Rev.</source> 
<volume>28</volume>, 
<fpage>167</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>176</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R50"><label>50</label><citation citation-type="edited-book">F. M. Ausubel, R. Brent, R. E. Kingston, D. D. Moore, J. G. Seidman, J. A. Smith, K. Struhl, in <italic>Current Protocols in Molecular Biology,</italic> F. M. Ausubel, R. Brent, R. E. Kingston, D. D. Moore, J. G. Seidman, J. A. Smith, K. Struhl, Eds. (John Wiley and Sons Inc., New York, 1987&#x2013;2006).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R51"><label>51</label><citation citation-type="edited-book">C. Guthrie, G. R. Fink, in <italic>Methods in Enzymology</italic>: <italic>Guide to Yeast Genetics and Molecular Biology</italic>, C. Guthrie, G. R. Fink, Eds. (Academic Press, San Diego, CA, 1991).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R52"><label>52</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sikorski</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hieter</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A system of shuttle vectors and yeast host strains designed for efficient manipulation of DNA in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title> <source>Genetics</source> 
<volume>122</volume>, 
<fpage>19</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>27</lpage> (<year>1989</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R53"><label>53</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pesce</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colman-Lerner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lok</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pincus</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Negative feedback that improves information transmission in yeast signalling.</article-title> <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>456</volume>, 
<fpage>755</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>761</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R54"><label>54</label><citation citation-type="edited-book">W. S. Cleveland, E. Grosse, W. M. Shyu, in <italic>Statistical Models in S</italic>, J. M. Chambers, T. J. Hastie, Eds. (Wadsworth and Brooks/Cole, Pacific Grove, CA,1992).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R55"><label>55</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaber</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baltanas</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klipp</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colman-Lerner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Modelling reveals novel roles of two parallel signalling pathways and homeostatic feedbacks in yeast.</article-title> <source>Mol. Syst. Biol.</source> 
<volume>8</volume>, 
<fpage>622</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R56"><label>56</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tarocco</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecuona</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Couto</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcas</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Optimization of erythritol and glycerol accumulation in conidia of <italic>Beauveria bassiana</italic> by solid-state fermentation, using response surface methodology.</article-title> <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source> 
<volume>68</volume>, 
<fpage>481</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>488</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R57"><label>57</label><citation citation-type="book">J. C. Pinheiro, D. M. Bates, <italic>Mixed-Effects Models in S and S-PLUS</italic> (Springer Verlag, New York, 2000).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R58"><label>58</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trusina</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Samad</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Defining network topologies that can achieve biochemical adaptation.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> 
<volume>138</volume>, 
<fpage>760</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>773</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We are grateful to G. Pesce for constant feedback and advice. We thank S. Pelet (Matthias Peter lab), M. Tam&#x00E1;s, G. Pesce, R. Yu, and E. Serra (Molecular Sciences Institute) for providing strains and plasmids and D. Levin for sharing unpublished information on Rgc1 and Ask10. We also thank S. Regot (Francesc Posas lab), R. Salcedo, E. Petelenz, D. Ahmadpour (Stefan Hohmann lab), C. Waltermann (Edda Klipp lab), and A. Kornblihtt for helpful discussions. <bold>Funding:</bold> Work in the laboratory of S.H. was supported by the Swedish Research Council and the European Commission (UNICELLSYS, contract 201142). Work in the laboratory of A.C.-L. was supported by grants PICT2005-33624, PICT-2007-847, and PICT2010-2248 from the Argentine Agency of Research and Technology (ANPCyT) and grant 1R01GM097479-01, subaward 0000713502, from the National Institute of General Medical Sciences, NIH. <bold>Author contributions:</bold> R.B. performed most of the experiments and constructed most of the strains used in the study. A.C. measured glycerol content of samples. R.B. and A.B. performed Hog1-Venus nuclear localization and volume recovery experiments. A.B. performed all the statistical analysis of the data. L.D. made strain LD3342. R.B. processed all the data of the paper. R.B., A.B., and A.C.-L. analyzed the results. R.B. and A.C.-L. wrote the paper. S.H. contributed to framing the research questions, interpretation of the data, and editing of the manuscript. <bold>Competing interests:</bold> The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
</ack></back>
</article>