<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Astronomy</subject><subject>Physics</subject><subject>Economics</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ASTRONOMY</subject><subject>PHYSICS</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Physics</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Two-Billion-Dollar Cosmic Ray Detector Sees Signs of <italic>Something</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Adrian</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>12</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage>135</fpage>
<lpage>135</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Physicists confirmed a previously reported excess of antiparticles from space that could emanate from dark matter.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>This week, physicists working with a $2 billion cosmic ray detector aboard the International Space Station confirmed a previously reported excess of antiparticles from space that could emanate from dark matter, the mysterious stuff whose gravity binds the galaxies. If so, the observation could help scientists determine the nature of dark matter. But the excess measured by the Alpha Magnetic Spectrometer could also be subatomic exhaust from a pulsar or some other mundane astronomical object. And determining which explanation is correct may require entirely different types of experiments and could take years.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>One and only.</title>
<p>AMS is the only major experiment on the International Space Station.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_135_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: NASA</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Don't scratch "discover what dark matter is" off your cosmological to-do list just yet. This week, physicists working with a $2 billion cosmic ray detector aboard the International Space Station confirmed a previously reported excess of antiparticles from space that could emanate from dark matter, the mysterious stuff whose gravity binds the galaxies. If so, the observation could help scientists determine the nature of dark matter. But the excess measured by the 6.7-tonne Alpha Magnetic Spectrometer (AMS) could also be subatomic exhaust from a pulsar or some other mundane astronomical object. And determining which explanation is correct may require entirely different types of experiments and could take years.</p>
<p>"The question is, now what?" says St&#x00E9;phane Coutu, a cosmic ray physicist at Pennsylvania State University, University Park, who does not work on AMS. "The answer is, that's a good question."</p>
<p>The brainchild of Samuel C. C. Ting, a 77-year-old Nobel Prize&#x2013;winning particle physicist, AMS was bolted to the space station on 19 May 2011 after a long gestation in which the international project was killed and resurrected (<italic>Science</italic>, 22 April 2011, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-publication" vol="332" page="408" issue="6028">408</related-article>). Since then, he and the 347 members of the AMS collaboration have measured the ratio of antielectrons, or positrons, to the total number of electrons and positrons, as Ting reported in a talk on 3 April at the European particle physics laboratory, CERN, near Geneva, Switzerland. According to standard astrophysics, that "positron fraction" should be small and should fall as energy increases. Instead, AMS found that the positron fraction increases from 5% at an energy of 10 gigaelectron volts (GeV) to more than 15% at an energy 35 times as high, Ting reported.</p>
<p>The extra positrons could arise from dark matter. According to popular theories, dark matter could consist of weakly interacting massive particles, or WIMPs. When two WIMPs collide, they could annihilate each other to produce an electron-positron pair, bumping the positron fraction closer to 50%. Such an excess had been previously reported, but physicists questioned the reliability of those results. The AMS data prove that the excess is real, Coutu and others says.</p>
<p>But does it point to dark matter? The positrons could instead emanate from a spinning neutron star called a pulsar, if it were close enough to Earth. Ting and the AMS team acknowledge the point. In a paper in <italic>Physical Review Letters</italic>, they do not mention dark matter as the source of the excess but instead refer to "new physical phenomena."</p>
<p>AMS can ultimately determine the source on its own, Ting says. If the positrons come from the annihilation of dark matter particles, then their energy must be limited by the mass of those particles. So the positron fraction should plummet as energy increases beyond a distinct "cutoff." In contrast, an excess from an astrophysical source should ebb away with increasing energy, Ting says. "If we have a sharp drop-off, it is a very strong indication of dark-matter collisions," he says. The AMS data suggest that the positron fraction levels off at the highest energies analyzed so far, and additional data should reveal whether it goes over a cliff.</p>
<p>Not everyone buys it. An astrophysical source can crank out particles with a sharp energy cutoff, too, says Gregory Tarl&#x00E9;, a cosmic ray physicist at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. "It's very easy to put a cutoff into an astrophysical model," he explains. "All you have to do is limit the size of the particle-accelerating region." So even if AMS sees a cutoff, the observation will remain ambiguous, Tarl&#x00E9; says.</p>
<p>In fact, details of the AMS results themselves could make it harder to explain the excess in terms of dark matter, says John Ellis, a theorist at King's College London. The AMS data show that the positron excess extends to energies higher than previous measurements could probe. That implies that WIMPs must weigh at least 300 or 400 GeV, which strains theoretical models, Ellis says. "AMS is painting dark matter into a rather small corner," he says. "Whether there's enough room for it to stand up, I don't know."</p>
<p>Perhaps ironically, cosmic ray physicists argue that the positron excess can never be deciphered by staring at the sky. Instead, they seek insight from a different source: an atom smasher, such as CERN's Large Hadron Collider (LHC). According to some models, it ought to be possible to make WIMPs with the LHC. Spotting such production would be necessary to clinch a dark-matter explanation for AMS's observations, Coutu and Tarl&#x00E9; say.</p>
<p>How long will it take to settle this? Don't wait up. AMS may have to collect data for another few years to see if there is a cutoff in the positron fraction, Ting says. And the LHC has shut down until 2015 for repairs. "I'm 47," Coutu says. "I'd like the answer before I keel over, but who knows?"</p>
<p>The uncertainty aside, the results mark a triumph for Ting, who all but willed AMS into orbit. Proposed in 1994, the detector made a test flight on NASA's Space Shuttle in 1998. But it appeared permanently grounded after the shuttle Columbia disintegrated on reentry in 2003 and NASA rethought the shuttle program. Undaunted, in 2008 Ting secured a congressional mandate that NASA launch AMS, to which the United States is one of 16 contributing nations. The AMS paper acknowledges nine current and former senators and representatives for their support.</p>
</body>
</article>