<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Planetary-Science</subject><subject>Chemistry</subject><subject>Atmospheric-Science</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>GEOCHEM PHYS</subject><subject>PLANET SCI</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Lunar and Planetary Science Conference</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Snapshots From the Meeting</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>Richard A.</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>12</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage seq="b">139</fpage>
<lpage>139</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>The Curiosity rover has come across hints of chemical react ions on Mars that could have produced the organic &#x22;building blocks of life,&#x22; but without any life. And big impacts on the moon and Mars have blasted off bits of rock that have been picked up on Earth, so could it be possible that a researcher has found a meteorite from Mercury?</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>The Curiosity rover has come across hints of chemical react ions on Mars that could have produced the organic &#x22;building blocks of life,&#x22; but without any life. And big impacts on the moon and Mars have blasted off bits of rock that have been picked up on Earth, so could it be possible that a researcher has found a meteorite from Mercury?</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <caption>
            <title>Mercurian?</title>
            <p>Although its composition resembles Mercury's, this meteorite may be too old to be from there.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="340_139b_F1"></graphic>
        <attrib>CREDIT: STEFAN RALEW</attrib>
    </fig>
<p><bold>Hot time on the ol' Mars?</bold> The Curiosity rover has come across hints of chemical reactions on Mars that could have produced the organic "building blocks of life," but without any life. Jennifer Stern of NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Maryland, and fellow Curiosity team members reported that when Curiosity gradually heated windblown dust, the process produced molecular fragments at about 800&#x00B0;C. These appear to be cyanide (a carbon-nitrogen compound) and hydrogen cyanide. Another Curiosity team member, Andrew Steele of the Carnegie Institution of Science's Geophysical Laboratory in Washington, D.C., reported the high-temperature release of the same molecules from another martian sample, a piece of the Tissint meteorite recently arrived from Mars. Using high-powered instruments in the lab, Steele could see that the nitrogen-containing compounds in Tissint likely formed when hot water interacted with martian rock. Another product of those reactions appears to have been organic matter. So if Curiosity turns up organic matter on Mars, the next chore will be telling whether it was ever alive.</p>
<p><bold>A messenger from Mercury?</bold> Big impacts on the moon and Mars have blasted off bits of rock that have been picked up on Earth, so why not a meteorite from Mercury? At the meeting, meteoriticist Anthony Irving of the University of Washington, Seattle, and colleagues proposed 345-gram Northwest Africa 7325 as a Mercurial meteorite. "No one has a rock like this," he says. It's a unique combination of elements, minerals, and isotopes that in many ways matches the properties of Mercury's surface as determined by the still-orbiting MESSENGER spacecraft. But "I was unimpressed," says planetary scientist William Vaughan of Brown University. Some of the chemistry doesn't match at all, he notes. What's more, the meteorite is much older than the relatively youthful lavas that cover most of Mercury's surface, where it presumably would have to have originated. Most discouraging, perhaps: "I don't know how we'll get a conclusive result," Irving says.</p>

</body>
</article>