<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="other" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>New Products</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Products &amp; Materials</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>products</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Computer-Science</subject><subject>Applied-Physics</subject><subject>Engineering</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>New Products</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>12</day><month>04</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage seq="a">223</fpage>
<lpage>223</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>A weekly roundup of information on newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of potential interest to researchers.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary">
<p>A weekly roundup of information on newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of potential interest to researchers.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>IMAGE ANALYSIS SYSTEMS</title>
<fig id="F1" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="340_223a_F1"><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text></graphic></fig>
<p>The new PXi Touch range of high-resolution, multi-application image analysis systems is ideal for scientists wanting a rapid touchscreen driven method of accurately imaging chemiluminescent and fluorescent blots, as well as 1-D and 2-D gels stained with any type of visible or fluorescent dye. Each PXi Touch features a camera with a large fixed aperture lens, which enables scientists to quickly capture images without having to adjust the camera's settings. The PXi Touch is available in three versions with a high-resolution four, six, or eight megapixel camera for chemiluminescence and 1-D and 2-D gel applications. To enable researchers to choose the best and safest lighting for their fluorescent gel and blot applications, the PXi Touch fits a number of lighting and filter options, making the system versatile enough to use with Syngene's ultraviolet and blue light transilluminators as well as white, infrared, red, blue, or green epi lighting.  </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Syngene</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: +44-(0)-1223-727123      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.syngene.com/pxi-pxi-touch">www.syngene.com/pxi-pxi-touch</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>LUMINEX ASSAY ANALYSIS SOFTWARE</title>
<p>Milliplex Analyst 5.1 is designed for analysis and interpretation of Luminex bead-based assay results. The newly released software includes unique features such as autofit and potency calculation and offers superior quality of data reduction analytics compared with other Luminex software packages. Superior algorithms yield better data at the low- and high-end of the standard curve. The autofit feature saves time by automatically using the best curve fit method for the curve presented. The potency calculation feature compares two or more standard curves, giving researchers a choice when reducing their data. Data acquisition and analysis integrates seamlessly with all Luminex instruments. Milliplex Analyst 5.1 is accessed using a code flash drive making it possible to use the software on multiple systems. More user-friendly plate setup means there are no limitations to where the standard curve can be put on the plate. Other software requires the standard curve to be placed vertically in the first column.</p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>EMD Millipore</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-645-5476      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.millipore.com">www.millipore.com</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>CONFOCAL IMAGING</title>
<p>The new FluoView FV1200 confocal laser scanning microscope is optimized for live cell imaging. The new system uniquely combines the accuracy of the newly engineered IX83 frame with enhanced fluorescence sensitivity and simultaneous laser stimulation of cells, making it ideal for advanced life science applications such as FRAP, FLIP, and photo-activation. In particular, the new highly reflective, silver-coated galvanometer scanning mirrors and dual channel GaAsP FluoView PMT module both act to maximize light transfer and detection. This allows for reduced laser power, protecting against the effects of photobleaching and phototoxicity. The generation of insightful confocal imaging data from living cells depends on optimally balancing laser power and sensitivity to minimize the effects of phototoxicity and photobleaching. To meet this challenge, the FV1200 is designed to maximize sensitivity via a new dual channel GaAsP FluoView high-sensitivity PMT module, which delivers up to 45% quantum efficiency. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Olympus</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: +49-40-23773-5913      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.microscopy.olympus.eu">www.microscopy.olympus.eu</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>USB FLUORESCENCE CAMERA </title>
<p>The ultrasensitive SPOT Pursuit USB digital camera combines superb image quality with excellent temporal resolution for rapid time-lapse recordings, allowing researchers to document live cells and photobleaching fluorescence specimens with ease. The camera is equipped with a high quantum efficiency CCD sensor and Peltier cooling, which makes it a suitable solution for a range of applications, from simple fluorescence documentation to the demanding process of live cell imaging and ratiometric experiments. The SPOT Pursuit USB live cell imaging camera achieves high-speed acquisition rates of 11 frames per second at full resolution without sacrificing read noise. New images can be captured while the previous image is still being read out. The user-friendly SPOT software included with the camera is compatible with both Windows and Mac. Data is transferred to the computer via the USB 2.0 interface, making it a snap to get up and running quickly. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>SPOT Imaging Solutions</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 586-731-6000      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.spotimaging.com/camPRUSB.html">www.spotimaging.com/camPRUSB.html</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>CYANINE DYES </title>
<p>A new range of high-quality cyanine dye products support the demand for fluorescent labeling in biological imaging and molecular diagnostics. In addition to a new range of 3'-CPG solid supports modified with Cyanine 540 and Cyanine 650, Link Technologies now also manufactures and supplies the commonly used phosphoramidites, allowing researchers to source an extended range of cyanine reagents. Until now, 3'-cyanine modification of an oligonucleotide could only be done postsynthetically, normally to an amino-modified oligo, or by the use of a cyanine phosphoramidite onto a universal or modified support that will not interfere with the intended use of the oligo. With the innovative 3'-modified 1,000&#x00C5;CPG supports, cyanine dyes can be added directly to oligos of interest without additional modification steps. Used as fluorescent markers in oligonucleotide synthesis, dyes are central to numerous detection techniques, such as real-time polymerase chain reaction, fluorescence in situ hybridization, SERRS-based DNA detection assays, and FRET studies. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Link Technologies </bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: +44-(0)-1698-849911      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.linktech.co.uk">www.linktech.co.uk</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="product-submission-instructions"><p>Electronically submit your new product description or product literature information! Go to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/products/newproducts.dtl">www.sciencemag.org/products/newproducts.dtl</ext-link> for more information.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="disclaimer"><p><italic>Newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of interest to researchers in all disciplines in academic, industrial, and governmental organizations are featured in this space. Emphasis is given to purpose, chief characteristics, and availabilty of products and materials. Endorsement by </italic>Science<italic> or AAAS of any products or materials mentioned is not implied. Additional information may be obtained from the manufacturer or supplier.</italic></p></fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
