<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="reply" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1234203</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1234203</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Technical Response</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Technical Comments</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>t-comment</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>GEOCHEM PHYS</subject><subject>TECH COMMENT</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Astronomy</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Response to Comments on &#x201C;Apatite <sup>4</sup>He/<sup>3</sup>He and (U-Th)/He Evidence for an Ancient Grand Canyon&#x201D;</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Farley</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Geological Sciences, University of Colorado at Boulder, 2200 Colorado Avenue, UCB 399, Boulder, CO 80309, USA.</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Division of Geological and Planetary Sciences, California Institute of Technology, MS 170-25, Pasadena, CA 91125, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. E-mail: <email xlink:href="rebecca.flowers@colorado.edu">rebecca.flowers@colorado.edu</email></corresp></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>12</day><month>04</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage seq="c">143</fpage>
<lpage>143</lpage>
<history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>01</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>02</month><year>2013</year></date></history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We reiterate that geological observations do not require Grand Canyon carving coeval with Colorado River integration. (U-Th)/He data from the western canyon, totaling 29 reproducible analyses from six samples and two labs, compellingly support an ancient canyon. Three dispersed analyses from one anomalous sample do not refute this conclusion, nor do the claimed shortcomings of our modeling have validity.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Nicholas Wigginton</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Cynthia Howe</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>We presented apatite <sup>4</sup>He/<sup>3</sup>He and (U-Th)/He (AHe) evidence for carving of the western Grand Canyon to within a few hundred meters of modern depths by ~70 million years ago (Ma) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). These data contradict the prevailing view of post-6 Ma carving of the entire canyon and instead support an ancient canyon model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). Below, we first offer an alternative explanation for the geological observations of Lucchitta (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). We then address the claims of Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>), which are based almost entirely on selected data interpretation, and show that the additional results support, rather than refute, an ancient canyon.</p>
<p>We appreciate the care and detail of the classic geologic mapping studies in the Grand Wash Trough west of the Grand Canyon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). However, we disagree that the observations outlined by Lucchitta (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>) preclude the presence of an ancient canyon. First, the argument that substantial ~70-Ma western canyon carving is not possible because the canyon looks young is disproved by the presence of nearby major paleocanyons of similarly ancient age (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The well-characterized Milkweed, Hindu, and Peach Springs paleocanyons contain relief of &#x2265;1200 m, intersect the western Grand Canyon, are Late Cretaceous&#x2013;early Tertiary in age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>), and record east-northeastward drainage similar to the ancestral river proposed to have excavated the 70-Ma Grand Canyon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). These gorges provide concrete and uncontroversial evidence for a paleocanyon system of which an ancient Grand Canyon would logically have been part. Several hundred meters of post&#x2013;6 Ma canyon deepening and widening would have imparted the more precipitous form of the modern Grand Canyon after integration of the Colorado River drainage.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption>
<title>Grand Canyon shaded relief map showing all western canyon-bottom sample locations, mean AHe dates, uncertainties, and number of individual analyses.</title>
<p>Gray box denotes the anomalous western canyon sample, which is characterized by extreme AHe data scatter, and forms the basis of the arguments in Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>). The ancient Grand Canyon would logically have been part of the well-documented system of Late Cretaceous&#x2013;early Tertiary paleocanyons. (<bold>B</bold>) The distribution of measured AHe dates from the reproducible samples in (<bold>A</bold>) strengthens the case for an ancient western canyon.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="340_143c_F1"></graphic></fig>
<p>Second, we again emphasize that the absence of pre&#x2013;6 Ma Colorado River deposits in the Grand Wash Trough does not preclude pre&#x2013;6 Ma carving of the western Grand Canyon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>). In the model of (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>), during most of Miocene time the river flowing westward through the Grand Canyon would have contained &lt;5% of the modern discharge and occupied a far smaller drainage basin in predominantly carbonate lithologies. Combined with a more arid Miocene climate, such a system would not transport substantial fluvial detritus to the trough. Moreover, the evidence of any limited aggradation would have been removed during the 530-m excavation of the Grand Wash Trough after integration of the modern, far larger Colorado River (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>). Pierce Canyon fan deposition in the Grand Wash Trough was accomplished by a high-gradient stream issuing from a steep channel and yet was restricted to within a few kilometers of its canyon. Thus, contrary to Lucchitta&#x2019;s assertion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>), a coeval Grand Canyon containing a river with an order-of-magnitude shallower gradient and the drainage basin characteristics described above would not be expected to have deposited abundant detritus over a broad area of the trough. In addition, debris delivered by high-gradient tributaries into the Grand Canyon itself could choke the gorge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>), which would further limit transport into the Grand Wash Trough.</p>
<p>We are eager to continue a scientifically rigorous discussion of the origin of the Grand Canyon. Unfortunately, the Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>. Comment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) is based on an abstract (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>) that includes neither the analytical data nor a description of the methodology used to generate the models shown. In the absence of such critical information, we used the master&#x2019;s thesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>) that is the source of the primary data. Contrary to the claims of (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>), we find that these data reinforce our original interpretation.</p>
<p>Both (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>) and (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>) report mean AHe dates for three western canyon samples, two of which yield reproducible results of 82.5 &#x00B1; 7 Ma (seven analyses) and 69.8 &#x00B1; 8.7 Ma (three analyses). These 10 measurements are entirely consistent with our 19 individual analyses from four western canyon samples, with mean AHe dates from 71 &#x00B1; 3 Ma to 89 &#x00B1; 7 Ma [uncertainties are 1&#x03C3; sample standard deviation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>)]. Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) ignore these two additional samples and instead mention only sample 01GC86. The three individual AHe dates for 01GC86 are extremely scattered (43% 1&#x03C3;), and the mean date of 50 &#x00B1; 21.6 Ma is obviously anomalous when compared with all other western canyon results. The mean of the scattered AHe dates for this sample yields the thermal history shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref> of (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>), clearly different from what would be concluded from any other western canyon sample (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>).</p>
<p>We disagree with Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) that a modeling result based on three scattered AHe dates from a single sample disproves the conclusions drawn from 29 reproducible single-grain AHe dates from the six other western canyon samples analyzed by two different labs. Indeed, exclusion of the suspect 01GC86 results from the date histogram yields a combined data distribution that even more compellingly supports an ancient canyon than our initial data set and increases the deviation from a &#x201C;young&#x201D; canyon model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). We maintain that the reproducibility of the western canyon data eliminates the need for speculation about substantial displacement along unidentified faults in the western canyon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) also suggest that our effort to fit multiple samples simultaneously has inadvertently mixed samples with possibly different thermal histories and therefore may be invalid. Our rationale for honoring data from multiple samples was to meet a more challenging standard than one using a single sample by demanding internal consistency of AHe and <sup>4</sup>He/<sup>3</sup>He data for the entire western canyon. Nevertheless, it is straightforward to perform the modeling using just the single sample for which we have <sup>4</sup>He/<sup>3</sup>He and AHe data: CP06-69. The key conclusions from such modeling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>) are identical to those of our original broader approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>), with all statistically acceptable paths requiring cooling to temperatures &lt;30&#x00B0;C by ~70 Ma. Although we excluded the <sup>4</sup>He/<sup>3</sup>He data for one spectrum (grain b) of CP06-69 from the simulations in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>) owing to an anomalous final step in the spectrum, including these <sup>4</sup>He/<sup>3</sup>He results as another constraint in the modeling also leaves our conclusions unchanged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Thus, contrary to the contention of Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>), even modeling of a single sample supports ancient canyon carving and is incompatible with a young canyon.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption>
<title>Thermal history simulation results for the western and eastern Grand Canyon.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Western canyon-bottom thermal history results from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>) (upper panel) compared with simulation results using only the normalized <sup>4</sup>He/<sup>3</sup>He step age profiles [goodness-of-fit parameter G = 0.32 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>)] and AHe data (<italic>G</italic> = 0.3) for sample CP06-69. Middle panel shows statistically valid time-temperature paths using spectra from grains c and d, and bottom panel depicts the results that also fit the spectrum of grain b. Blue line represents the conventional post&#x2013;6 Ma incision history model. (<bold>B</bold>) Predicted correlation of date and eU when apatites are incompletely annealed at ~90 Ma. The cooling path shown in the inset includes the &#x201C;young canyon model&#x201D; after ~90 Ma, and an approximate path, consistent with that proposed by (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17"><italic>17</italic></xref>) for the period 600 to 90 Ma. The peak temperature at 90 Ma was selected to yield the observed date for sample CP06-69 with its eU concentration when modeled for an apatite with an equivalent spherical radius of 65 &#x03BC;m using the radiation damage accumulation and annealing model (RDAAM) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>). Black curves show predicted AHe dates for varying eU. Red points are observations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>), clearly inconsistent with the predicted date-eU correlation of the partial-annealing model. The time-temperature path is illustrative and does not imply that the AHe observations constrain the pre&#x2013;90 Ma path. (<bold>C</bold>) Fields of statistically viable time-temperature paths for eastern canyon-bottom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>) and rim (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>) samples using the RDAAM model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>). Results are characterized by similar temperatures from Late Cretaceous through mid-Tertiary time, compatible with the presence of a substantial eastern paleocanyon as proposed in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>).</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="340_143c_F2"></graphic></fig>
<p>Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) imply that western canyon apatites may be more He retentive than our modeling allowed because we did not consider the possibility of incomplete radiation damage annealing during peak burial at ~80 to 90 Ma. However, incomplete annealing of radiation damage is inconsistent with apatite fission-track date and length data in the region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13"><italic>13</italic></xref>). Furthermore, in addition to the old He dates, a key feature of the western canyon AHe data set is a lack of correlation between He date and effective U (eU) concentration, despite a factor of 15 variation in eU among dated grains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Models that invoke incomplete annealing of radiation damage and associated He retention before peak heating instead invariably yield extremely strong date-eU correlations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). We thus conclude that this criticism has no merit.</p>
<p>Our eastern Grand Canyon results were also challenged by Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>). In (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>), we argued for carving of a kilometer-scale paleocanyon by 55 Ma in this region based on AHe data indicating that rim and canyon-bottom samples experienced similar early through mid-Tertiary temperatures. Use of a revised He diffusion kinetic model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>) and comparing rim-sample simulation results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>) with all statistically viable thermal histories for eastern canyon-bottom samples in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>) similarly supports carving of a paleocanyon by early Tertiary time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>). Unfortunately, the Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) criticism of this conclusion compares results from the earlier kinetic model with those of the later model; although either model alone is internally consistent, it is inappropriate to compare across them. Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>.&#x2019;s analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) is also problematic because they use selected time-temperature paths rather than the larger suite of thermal histories that are statistically viable. Finally, plotting the youngest individual AHe dates from samples across the larger region at a single arbitrarily selected temperature on this thermal history diagram [green stars in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref> in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>)] is nonsensical.</p>
<p>Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) include other misleading statements that bear on Colorado River integration but not on canyon carving, do not support post&#x2013;6 Ma canyon carving as contended in the Comment, or have no backing in the cited literature. For example, the authors declare that (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>) describes the southward-transported 60- to 50-Ma Hindu fanglomerate, yet inspection of this reference reveals no mention of the Hindu fanglomerate or its age or documentation of any southward-transported gravel of any kind. The Comment states that semisteady incision rates over the past 4 million years would be sufficient to carve the canyon, but this conflicts with the fact that the oldest direct constraint on western canyon incision is 3.9 Ma and only 290 m above river level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16"><italic>16</italic></xref>), which constrains just ~30% of total canyon incision here (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Our results imply that the remainder of canyon carving occurred ~70 Ma.</p>
<p>In summary, contrary to the assertions of the Comments, we maintain that the geologic evidence is compatible with ancient carving of much of the western Grand Canyon. The additional thermochronologic data discussed by Karlstrom <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) only strengthens the case for the canyon&#x2019;s antiquity.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farley</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Apatite 4He/3He and (U-Th)/He evidence for an ancient Grand Canyon</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>338</volume>, 
<fpage>1616</fpage> (<year>2012</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1229390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23196906</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wernicke</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The California River and its role in carving Grand Canyon</article-title>. <source>Geol. Soc. Am. Bull.</source> 
<volume>123</volume>, 
<fpage>1288</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1130/B30274.1</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucchitta</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Comment on &#x201C;Apatite 4He/3He and (U-Th)/He evidence for an ancient Grand Canyon&#x201D;</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>340</volume>, 
<fpage>143</fpage> (<year>2013</year>); <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/340/6129/143-a">www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/340/6129/143-a</ext-link>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karlstrom</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Comment on &#x201C;Apatite 4He/3He and (U-Th)/He evidence for an ancient Grand Canyon&#x201D;</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>340</volume>, 
<fpage>143</fpage> (<year>2013</year>); <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/340/6129/143-b">www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/340/6129/143-b</ext-link>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="book">I. Lucchitta, in <italic>Landscapes of Arizona: The Geological Story</italic>, T. L. Smiley, J. D. Nations, T. L. Pewe, J. P. Schafer, Eds. (University Press of America, Lanham, MD, 1984), pp. 269&#x2013;301.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elston</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Cretaceous-Eocene (Laramide) landscape development and Oligocene-Pliocene drainage reorganization of Transition Zone and Colorado Plateau, Arizona</article-title>. <source>J. Geophys. Res.</source> 
<volume>96</volume>,
<fpage>12389</fpage> (<year>1991</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/90JB01978</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Laramide deformation, erosion and plutonism along the southwestern margin of the Colorado Plateau</article-title>. <source>Tectonophysics</source> 
<volume>61</volume>, 
<fpage>25</fpage> (<year>1979</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0040-1951(79)90290-7</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="book">R. A. Young, in <italic>Colorado River Origin and Evolution</italic>, R. A. Young, E. E. Spamer, Eds. (Grand Canyon Association, Grand Canyon, AZ, 2001), pp. 7&#x2013;16.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="book">R. A. Young, in <italic>Late Cenozoic Drainage History of the Southwestern Great Basin and Lower Colorado River Basin: Geologic and Biologic Perspectives,</italic> M. C. Reheis, R. Hershler, D. M. Miller, Eds. (Geological Society of America Special Paper, 2008), vol. 439, pp. 319&#x2013;333.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="book">J. P. Lee, D. F. Stockli, S. A. Kelley, J. Pederson, &#x201C;Unroofing and incision of the Grand Canyon region as constrained through low-temperature thermochronology,&#x201D; U.S. Geological Survey Open File Report 2011-1210 (USGS, Washington, DC, 2011).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="thesis">J. P. Lee, thesis, University of Kansas, Lawrence (2007).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wernicke</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farley</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Unroofing, incision and uplift history of the southwestern Colorado Plateau from (U-Th)/He apatite thermochronometry</article-title>. <source>Geol. Soc. Am. Bull.</source> 
<volume>120</volume>, 
<fpage>571</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1130/B26231.1</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="book">S. A. Kelley, C. E. Chapin, K. E. Karlstrom, in <italic>Colorado River Origin and Evolution</italic>, R. A. Young, E. E. Spamer, Eds. (Grand Canyon Association, Grand Canyon, AZ, 2001), pp. 37&#x2013;42.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ketcham</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuster</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farley</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Apatite (U-Th)/He thermochronometry using a radiation damage accumulation and annealing model</article-title>. <source>Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</source> 
<volume>73</volume>, 
<fpage>2347</fpage> (<year>2009</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gca.2009.01.015</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="confproc">R. A. Young, in <italic>Geology of Grand Canyon, Northern Arizona,</italic> D. P. Elston, G. H. Billingsley, R. A. Young, Eds. (American Geophysical Union, 28th International Geological Congress Fieldtrip Guidebook T115/315, Washington, DC, 1989), pp. 166&#x2013;173.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polyak</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asmerom</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Age and evolution of the Grand Canyon revealed by U-Pb dating of water table-type speleothems</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>319</volume>, 
<fpage>1377</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1151248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18323451</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farley</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>(U-Th)/Ne and multidomain (U-Th)/He systematics of a hydrothermal hematite from eastern Grand Canyon</article-title>. <source>Earth Planet. Sci. Lett.</source> 
<volume>359&#x2013;360</volume>, 
<fpage>131</fpage> (<year>2012</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epsl.2012.10.010</pub-id></citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by NSF grant EAR-1019896 to K.A.F.</p>
</ack></back>
</article>