<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Virology</subject><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subject>Medicine</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ASIA/PACIFIC NEWS</subject><subject>MEDICINE</subject><subject>VIROLOGY</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Decade After SARS, China's Flu Response Wins Cautious Praise</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hvistendahl</surname><given-names>Mara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn id="FN1">
<label>*</label>
<p>With reporting by Jon Cohen.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>12</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage>130</fpage>
<lpage>130</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Coming at the 10-year anniversary of the SARS outbreak, the Chinese government's announcement that a new influenza virus is killing people elicited suspicion from many Chinese, but scientists are praising the country this time around.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Coming at the 10-year anniversary of the SARS outbreak, the Chinese government's announcement that a new influenza virus is killing people elicited suspicion from many Chinese. Why, some asked, did it take nearly 6 weeks after the first patient fell ill for the government to identify the H7N9 virus? But many scientists say that, while there are plenty of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/340/6129/129">questions surrounding the new virus</ext-link>, China has actually come a long way when it comes to monitoring health and has been forthcoming with the international health community&#x2014;a sharp contrast with the SARS episode, when it was unable to identify the new pathogen and tried to sweep a deadly epidemic under the rug.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <caption>
            <title>Limited spread.</title>
            <p>Ten days after reporting the first case of H7N9, Chinese officials had found only 27 others, all in Shanghai and surrounding provinces.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="340_130_F1"></graphic>
        <attrib>CREDIT: ADAPTED FROM EUROPEAN CENTRE FOR DISEASE PREVENTION AND CONTROL</attrib>
    </fig>
<p><bold>SHANGHAI</bold>&#x2014;Coming at the 10-year anniversary of the SARS outbreak, the Chinese government's announcement that a new influenza virus is killing people elicited suspicion from many Chinese. Why, some asked, did it take nearly 6 weeks after the first patient fell ill for the government to identify the H7N9 virus? And was there a connection to the thousands of dead pigs floating in Shanghai's Huangpu River?</p>
<p>But many scientists say that, while there are plenty of questions surrounding the new virus (see main story, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="340" page="129" issue="6129">129</related-article>), China has actually come a long way when it comes to monitoring health and has been forthcoming with the international health community&#x2014;a sharp contrast with the SARS episode, when it was unable to identify the new pathogen and tried to sweep a deadly epidemic under the rug (<italic>Science</italic>, 15 March, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-publication" vol="339" page="1264" issue="6125">1264</related-article>).</p>
<p>Reporting of the virus's initial discovery, and subsequent cases, appears to have been timely, says virologist Malik Peiris of the University of Hong Kong. "One should not underestimate the work and challenge" in identifying, confirming, and double-checking a new influenza strain, Peiris says. "The Chinese are getting out information as fast they can," adds virologist Robert Webster of St. Jude Children's Research Hospital in Memphis, Tennessee.</p>

<p>SARS was a turning point, says Yanzhong Huang, a global health fellow at the Council on Foreign Relations in New York City. "In the post-SARS era, the central health authorities have become more transparent in sharing disease-related information with the international community," Huang says. China has also boosted public health funding, set up a comprehensive disease prevention and control system, established a task force to combat avian influenza, and set up hundreds of monitoring stations for animal disease.</p>
<p>But China's Ministry of Agriculture&#x2014;which will be critical in tracing H7N9's animal origins&#x2014;remains a weak link. In 2006, the ministry was slow to share virus samples from poultry with the international community after researchers found a new strain of H5N1 in birds in six provinces (<italic>Science</italic>, 10 November 2006, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-publication" vol="314" page="905" issue="5801">905</related-article>). Now, there is again concern that the ministry "might not be very enthusiastic" to share with foreign labs, Huang says. Current regulations require Chinese scientists to get the ministry's permission to collect and study avian flu samples, effectively limiting research to three labs.</p>
<p>There are other reasons for concern. Many health labs are still not adequately equipped, Huang says: "Hospitals at the grassroots level probably are still unable to tell the difference among cold, annual flu, and avian influenza." The government has censored posts on Weibo, China's most popular microblog, about links to the dead pigs and alleged hidden cases. And in another sign that not everything has changed, some local disease centers have touted the traditional Chinese medicine banlangen as treatment for H7N9&#x2014;the same unproven product that was trotted out 10 years ago as a remedy for SARS.</p>
</body>
</article>