<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subject>Physiology</subject><subject>Biochemistry</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>NEUROSCIENCE</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Tissue Imaging Method Makes Everything Clear</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Underwood</surname><given-names>Emily</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>12</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage>131</fpage>
<lpage>132</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Karl Deisseroth's new technique, CLARITY, may fundamentally change the way labs study and image the brain.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Karl Deisseroth is on a roll. In March, he was awarded a share of the world's largest neuroscience prize; last week, he was appointed to advise President Barack Obama's new $100 million brain research initiative. Now, this week in <italic>Nature</italic>, Deisseroth presents a new way of imaging the brain, which many researchers say will fundamentally change the way labs study the intricate organ. CLARITY, Deisseroth's new technique, can be used to make any organ transparent, but it was the challenges of imaging the brain that motivated Deisseroth, who hopes to dissect psychiatric disorders such as schizophrenia and depression.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Crystal clear.</title>
<p>CLARITY allows researchers to image specific neurons and molecules within an intact mouse brain (<italic>left</italic>) and hippocampus (<italic>right</italic>) without making a single cut.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_131_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: KWANGHUN CHUNG AND KARL DEISSEROTH, HOWARD HUGHES MEDICAL INSTITUTE/STANFORD UNIVERSITY</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Karl Deisseroth is on a roll. In March, the neuroscientist-psychiatrist-engineer of Stanford University in Palo Alto, California, was awarded a share of the world's largest neuroscience prize for his work developing optogenetics, a tool which allows researchers to manipulate neuronal activity with light. Last week, he was appointed to advise President Barack Obama's new $100 million brain research initiative. Now, this week in <italic>Nature</italic>, Deisseroth presents a new way of imaging the brain, which many researchers say will fundamentally change the way labs study the intricate organ.</p>
<p>"This is one of those singular events in the history of neuroscience," says Terrence Sejnowski, a neuroscientist at the Salk Institute for Biological Studies in San Diego, California, referring to CLARITY, Deisseroth's new method of rendering tissue transparent. Sejnowski compares the technique to the Golgi stain, which more than a century ago allowed scientists to trace specific neurons and their projections. "Until you actually see it, you don't quite appreciate how spectacular [CLARITY] is," he says. "You can see not just very detailed images of single neurons but whole populations of neurons, their projections, the inner structure of the brain. It's very revealing and has almost infinite potential to image anything that could be labeled."</p>
<p>The technique can be used to make any organ transparent, but it was the challenges of imaging the brain that motivated Deisseroth, who hopes to dissect psychiatric disorders such as schizophrenia and depression. Creating a 3D image of a brain today requires carving its tissue into hundreds or thousands of hair-thin slices, scanning an image of each slice in microscopic detail into a computer, and then painstakingly realigning the sections. Digitally stitching axons back together&#x2014;each roughly a hundredth the diameter of a human hair&#x2014;not only takes a lot of computational time, but is also prone to significant error, says neuroscientist Arthur Toga of the University of California (UC), Los Angeles. After spending decades refining techniques for slicing and imaging brains, Toga says CLARITY may soon make that work irrelevant: "I'm gonna go up there and talk to these guys," he says, impressed.</p>
<p>The CLARITY technique, which Deisseroth and colleagues have been working on for about 6 years, skips over slicing entirely and instead tackles the biggest obstacle to traditional brain imaging: the fatty molecules, called lipids, that form the cellular membranes that keep neurons and other brain cells and organelles intact. Much as oil on sunlit water produces a rainbow sheen, these molecules scatter light in all directions, making it impossible to use light-based microscopy to see more than a few hundred microns deep into the brain. Lipids also repel many substances, such as antibodies, making it difficult to label specific types of cells without cutting the brain into sections.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Disappearing act.</title>
<p>CLARITY-treated mouse brain (<italic>right</italic>) reveals quote from famous neuroanatomist Santiago Ram&#x00F3;n y Cajal.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_131_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: KWANGHUN CHUNG AND KARL DEISSEROTH, HOWARD HUGHES MEDICAL INSTITUTE/STANFORD UNIVERSITY</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Because lipids maintain the brain's structure, just getting rid of them isn't an option, Deisseroth says. "Everything would just slosh around." Instead, CLARITY first replaces the lipids with a water-based gel by infusing a brain, or any other tissue, with single molecules of acrylamide&#x2014;the same clear, jelly-like substance used to separate and analyze DNA molecules through electrophoresis. The fatty molecules are then flushed out with a combination of electrical current and detergent. For a roughly 4-mm-diameter mouse brain, the process takes about 9 days, Deisseroth says.</p>
<p>"This is a significant improvement" over previous methods of removing lipids from brain tissue, notes neurophysicist David Kleinfeld of UC San Diego. Although other labs have attempted to render the brain clear, he says, previous attempts have left the tissue far too fragile to work with. Kleinfeld says that he plans to use CLARITY to study the human brainstem, a region that is difficult to image because of all the lipid-packed myelin that surrounds neurons in that area. "We're pretty psyched."</p>
<p>One of the most exciting things about the technique is that it allows researchers to infiltrate the brain with labels for specific cell types, neurotransmitters, or proteins; wash them out; and image the brain again with different labels, Sejnowski says. "In one shot, you can look at every molecule in the brain that has that label." Digitizing the process will speed up by a hundredfold tasks such as counting all the neurons in a given brain region, he adds.</p>
<p>In the <italic>Nature</italic> paper, Deisseroth and colleagues describe using the technique to image not only the mouse brain, but also small blocks of post mortem brain tissue from a person with autism. The experiment confirmed that the method works with brains preserved in formalin, a common fixative.</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<caption>
<title>On a roll.</title>
<p>Karl Deisseroth wants to revolutionize neuroscience.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_131_F3"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: STEVE FISCH/STANFORD UNIVERSITY</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Will scientists ever be able to use CLARITY to look at an entire human brain? Although the notion is "not outrageous," it would require building a much, much bigger microscope lens, Kleinfeld says. "We haven't pushed that limit yet," Deisseroth says. Now, existing microscopes can image up to only 6 to 8 mm in diameter of clarified brain tissue at a time&#x2014;about the size of a whole adult mouse brain, he says. That's convenient, Deisseroth says, because it's about the size of what many researchers believe to be the core computational unit of the human cortex.</p>
<p>Although he agrees that CLARITY will lead to a "major advance" in tissue morphology, the technique may be dangerous and expensive for other labs to adopt, warns neuroimaging expert Hans Ulrich Dodt of the Vienna University of Technology, who has been exploring other methods to render tissues transparent. For one thing, acrylamide is highly toxic and carcinogenic, "so it's going to be a mess, and severe safety precautions have to be taken." Deisseroth acknowledges the need for caution, but he expects that other labs will find the new technique easy to adopt. He has already run several workshops to share the method.</p>
<p>Nora Volkow, director of the National Institute on Drug Abuse in Bethesda, Maryland, and one of the reviewers of the National Institutes of Health Director's Transformative Research Award that funded the experiment, describes CLARITY as "magnificent." Deisseroth is an "extraordinary individual and extremely creative," she says.</p>
</body>
</article>