<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Anatomy</subject><subject>Anthropology</subject><subject>Paleontology</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ANTHRO</subject><subject>PALEO</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Paleoanthropology</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Human Smile and Funny Walk for <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>Ann</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>12</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage>132</fpage>
<lpage>133</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.sciencemag.org/extra/sediba">New analyses</ext-link> detail many traits shared with our genus <italic>Homo</italic>, in the spine, vertebral column, knee, teeth, and jaws.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Six new papers this week in <italic>Science</italic> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.sciencemag.org/extra/sediba">analyze two partial skeletons of <italic>Au</italic>. <italic>sediba</italic>, plus a shinbone of a third individual</ext-link>. They offer the most detailed picture yet of how this species moved and its relationship with other hominins, including our own ancestors. The remarkably complete skeletons reveal a strange creature with a small brain and primitive walk&#x2014;but some surprisingly human teeth.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<boxed-text content-type="sci-custom 6129-sediba"><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/site/extra/sediba/index.xhtml">Index to <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic> special section</ext-link></p></boxed-text>
<p>If you happened to be in South Africa about 2 million years ago, you might have seen an odd sight: an older female hominin sashaying down a wooded slope, perhaps in search of water. She walked upright, but she wasn't human, and she moved with what to our eyes would have looked like a distinctly strange gait. She was a member of <italic>Australopithecus sediba</italic>, and according to new analyses of fossils published online in <italic>Science</italic> this week (see p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="340" page="163" issue="6129">163</related-article>), she may have twisted from side to side, rolling her feet inward with each step.</p>
<p>"Sediba's got swag," says paleoanthropologist Lee Berger of the University of the Witwatersrand in Johannesburg, South Africa. At least, she would have had swag until she fell into a death pit&#x2014;a deep cave&#x2014;at the site of Malapa, where she was buried with a youth and at least one other of her kind for nearly 2 million years before Berger and his son found them in 2008 (<italic>Science</italic>, 9 April 2010, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-publication" vol="328" page="154" issue="5975">154</related-article>).</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Jaw dropper.</title>
<p><italic>Au. sediba's</italic> skull shows a surprising mix of primitive features, such as a small brain, coupled with more human features in the jaw and teeth.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_132_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: BRETT ELOFF, COURTESY OF LEE R. BERGER AND THE UNIVERSITY OF THE WITWATERSRAND</attrib>
</fig>
<p>The six new papers analyze two partial skeletons of <italic>Au. sediba</italic>, plus a shinbone of a third individual. They offer the most detailed picture yet of how this species moved and its relationship with other hominins, including our own ancestors. The remarkably complete skeletons reveal a strange creature with a small brain and primitive walk&#x2014;but some surprisingly human teeth. "When you look at <italic>Au. sediba</italic> from head to toe, you get a package that's very different from anything we've ever seen or predicted," Berger says. The analyses detail many traits shared with our genus <italic>Homo</italic>, in the spine, vertebral column, knee, teeth, and jaws, and Berger argues that <italic>Au. sediba</italic> could be the long-sought species that gave rise to <italic>Homo</italic>.</p>
<p>Few paleoanthropologists agree. But they say that at the very least, the new papers offer a detailed view of a novel way to be a member of the extended human family. They also show how evolution remodels the same body plan in diverse ways in different habitats. "If you look at the discoveries of hominins 2 to 3 million years ago, each one seems to shuffle the deck [of traits] in different ways," says paleoanthropologist William Kimbel of Arizona State University, Tempe. "It adds another subtle layer of information about the diversity of African hominins."</p>
<p>The outlines of <italic>Au. sediba</italic> have been presented before, but the latest work brings this strange hominin into ever sharper focus. For example, ever since Berger's team discussed a chimpanzeelike heel from one of the skeletons at a meeting last year (<italic>Science</italic>, 4 May 2012, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-publication" vol="336" page="538-a" issue="6081">538</related-article>), researchers have wondered how the species could walk upright. The bottom of the heel, preserved in the older female, is "exceptionally small," twisted, and pointed as in a chimp, compared with the broad, flat base of a human heel bone, the authors write in <italic>Science</italic> (see image, p. 133). The narrow heel offers far less surface area on which to distribute weight when the foot strikes the ground, explains biological anthropologist Jeremy DeSilva of Boston University, first author of the foot and leg paper. (Chimps knuckle-walk, using their arms for added stability to support their skinny heels.)</p>
<p>In their analysis of bones from the female skeleton's leg, DeSilva and his colleagues propose that <italic>Au. sediba</italic> had an arched foot that allowed it to put weight simultaneously on its heel and the outside of its midfoot. As it took each step, it must have pronated the foot, rolling it markedly inwards.</p>
<p>If modern humans try such a maneuver, they'll quickly find that the hyperpronation puts torque on the foot, and also causes the lower leg and thigh to rotate excessively, straining the muscles that cross the knees and hips. Indeed, the new papers reveal signs of such strain in the ankle, knee, and hip, showing that <italic>Au. sediba</italic> compensated for the pronated walk. For example, the female's knee showed an "extreme" bony protrusion that may have helped to alleviate this stress and prevent the kneecap from dislocating, the authors write. Both partial skeletons also have flexible vertebral columns that have the curvature of the spine, or lordosis, that is considered a hallmark of upright walking.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Twisted sister.</title>
<p>This composite of <italic>Au. sediba</italic> is partly based on a female skeleton that would have walked with a twist, because her heel (<italic>inset, center</italic>) was pointed like a chimp's (<italic>inset, left</italic>) rather than flat like a humans (<italic>inset, right</italic>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_132_F2"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDITS (TOP TO BOTTOM): BRETT ELOFF, COURTESY OF LEE R. BERGER AND THE UNIVERSITY OF THE WITWATERSRAND; J. DESILVA <italic>ET AL., SCIENCE</italic></attrib>
</fig>
<p>Other researchers agree that despite the chimplike heel, the rest of the bones show that <italic>Au. sediba</italic> walked upright: "It's definitely a biped," says anatomist Bruce Latimer of Case Western Reserve University in Cleveland, Ohio. But it sure had an odd walk. "This particular hominid is walking in a different way than all earlier hominids," says paleoanthropologist Brian Richmond of George Washington University in Washington, D.C., who calls the team's reconstruction of the gait "provocative." He and others wonder if the older female's style of walking might have looked odd even to another <italic>Au. sediba</italic>, perhaps because of injury. "The key question is whether this was typical for the species."</p>
<p>The other new papers tackle different parts of the anatomy, such as the shoulder and arm, which are primitive and chimplike. This shoulder and the long arm show that <italic>Au. sediba</italic> was still spending a lot of time climbing trees or scrambling up rocky cliffsides, Berger says. Yet, an earlier analysis revealed a more humanlike hand.</p>
<p>The female skeleton's teeth, which are often considered useful for sorting out evolutionary relationships, also show an interesting mix of primitive and human traits. Bioarchaeologist Joel Irish of Liverpool John Moores University in the United Kingdom and collaborators compared <italic>Au. sediba</italic>'s teeth to those of more than 340 fossils of seven species of hominins to sort out how they are related to each other. Irish did a cladistic analysis of 22 inherited dental traits, such as small cusps or a shovel shape. Not surprisingly, the team found that <italic>Au. sediba</italic> is most closely related to <italic>Au. africanus</italic>, a species close to it in both space and time, living in South Africa roughly 3 million to 2 million years ago.</p>
<p>But the analysis also found that both of these species are more closely related to early <italic>Homo</italic> than they are to other members of <italic>Australopithecus</italic> from east Africa. This suggests, as Berger has argued for years, that the South African species may knock the queen of australopithecines, Lucy&#x2014;a member of <italic>Au. afarensis</italic>&#x2014;off her long-held perch as the most likely ancestor of <italic>Homo</italic>.</p>
<p>That's a radical view. Some paleoanthropologists critique the methodology of the dental analysis, which identifies inherited traits that vary among modern humans and are used to distinguish lineages within our species. It's unclear whether those traits are the best ones for sorting out relationships among hominins that lived millions of years ago. "These are minor differences in the crowns [of teeth]," Kimbel says. "To try to apply this to hominins that are millions of years old is fraught with difficulty." Paleoanthropologist Bernard Wood of George Washington University is concerned that the method used by Irish doesn't include confidence intervals, showing which family trees are most reliable. "Without more information, I don't know whether this is something I want to bet $5 on, $50 on, or $500 dollars on," Wood says.</p>
<p>Others point out that <italic>Au. sediba</italic> was alive after <italic>Homo</italic> came on the scene: The first fossil assigned to our genus is a lower jaw in Ethiopia dated to 2.4 million years ago. "<italic>Sediba</italic> is unique and very interesting, but <italic>sediba</italic> came too late to the party to be the ancestor of <italic>Homo</italic>," Richmond says. But Berger wonders if that jaw, which was found isolated, not connected to a skull or skeleton, is truly <italic>Homo</italic>. An isolated <italic>Au. sediba</italic> jaw would look a lot a <italic>Homo</italic> jaw, he notes.</p>
<p>However <italic>Au. sediba</italic> is related to us, what's exciting about this set of discoveries, Richmond says, is that the "fossils are complete enough that we're starting to understand how these regions of anatomy are related to other regions of anatomy," connecting jaws to spines and feet.</p>
<p>Despite the wealth of fossils, researchers want more: They say another heel or more bones from the forefoot could "test the model" of how the species walked, Latimer says. Comparisons with other australopithecines would also help, but the tiny bones of the foot are so rarely preserved that the <italic>Au. sediba</italic> foot bones don't overlap with the handful known for other ancient hominins. For example, the primitive foot of a still unnamed species of <italic>Australopithecus</italic> from Burtele, Ethiopia, has an opposable toe bone, but it's not clear if it pronated, and those toe bones are missing for <italic>Au. sediba</italic>. An answer might come from the 2-millionto 3-million-year-old Little Foot skeleton&#x2014;named for its many foot bones&#x2014;found just 15 kilometers away at Sterkfontein Caves. But that skeleton is being excavated by a rival team of fossil hunters who have yet to publish in detail (<italic>Science</italic>, 9 September 2011, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-publication" vol="333" page="1374" issue="6048">1374</related-article>).</p>
<p>More will be coming: The remainder of the defining type specimen of <italic>Au. sediba</italic> still lies inside a rock, waiting to be excavated. Berger's team plans to return to Malapa to begin digging for new fossils this summer.</p>
</body>
</article>