<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1236842</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1236842</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Books <italic>et al.</italic></subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>books</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>EVOLUTION</subject><subject>SCI HISTORY PHILO</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="display-ad"><subject>Evolution</subject><subject>Genetics</subject><subject>Zoology</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Biography</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Nature's True Self</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Boomsma</surname><given-names>Jacobus J.</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff>The reviewer is at the Centre for Social Evolution, Department of Biology, Universitetsparken 15, University of Copenhagen, 2100 Copenhagen, Denmark.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>jjboomsma@bio.ku.dk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>12</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>340</volume>
<issue>6129</issue>
<fpage>145</fpage>
<lpage>146</lpage>
<product product-type="book"><bold>Nature's Oracle</bold> The Life and Work of W. D. Hamilton <bold><italic>by Ullica Segerstrale</italic></bold> Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2013. 459 pp. S35, &#x00A3;25. ISBN 9780198607274.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2013, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>In this biography of the often controversial evolutionary biologist W. D. Hamilton, Segerstrale argues for the importance of his version of Darwinism.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>In this biography of the often controversial evolutionary biologist W. D. Hamilton, Segerstrale argues for the importance of his version of Darwinism.</p></abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sherman J. Suter</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Cynthia Howe</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>About 50 years ago, William D. Hamilton completed the neo-Darwinian synthesis by extending Fisher's fundamental theorem of natural selection to include social interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). He showed mathematically that to be truly general, Darwinian fitness had to be formulated in terms of gene copies rather than differential survival and progeny. Inclusive fitness (the number of gene copies in future generations passed on through both own offspring and the offspring of relatives) is what organisms are selected to maximize. In <italic>Nature's Oracle</italic>, Ullica Segerstrale offers an authoritative account that relates Hamilton's life and work.</p>
<p>Segerstrale (a sociologist at the Illinois Institute of Technology) takes us on a grand tour through the four decades of Hamilton's scholarship. We become familiar with his inductive reverse engineering of some of nature's most fundamental laws: a remarkable quest to unravel life's coherence and its challenges. Hamilton's insights were fueled by a profound interest in natural history very similar to Darwin's; he grew up just a few miles away from Down House, where Darwin had settled a century earlier. Hamilton endowed abstractions of genes with their own agendas, making it explicit that their interests would often conflict with one another and with the bodies carrying them. This gene's-eye perspective changed evolutionary biology by turning some of its branches into hypothesis-driven disciplines based on testable quantitative predictions of stable adaptive states.</p>
<p>In a single decade, Hamilton not only formulated inclusive fitness theory but also made lasting contributions to other evolutionary topics that were begging for quantitative understanding. Whereas his theories of senescence and extraordinary sex ratios were closely intertwined with the gene's-eye perspective, he also derived a universal geometry for group-living animals chased by predators, demonstrating that herds are ultimately driven by selfish interests. With others, he later developed deep insights into the evolutionary stability of dispersal, decision rules for cooperation among nonrelatives, and the perpetual pressure of pathogens as drivers for maintaining sex and sexually selected ornaments. And he produced a selfish-herd theory for trees beleaguered by sap-sucking insects, which offered honest signaling of resistance as the ultimate explanation for autumn colors.</p>
<p>Segerstrale captures the essence of Hamilton's science and personality remarkably well. She skillfully unravels the intricate connections between his brilliant intellect, fearless engagement, skepticism toward established authority, fondness for Neotropical wasps, and uneasiness with social situations. I was somewhat disappointed by the rather sparse photographic material and in the choice of large <italic>Morpho</italic> butterflies for the dust jacket&#x2014;rather than the giant blue carrion beetles with whom Hamilton had planned to team up for his ultimate graduation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>The book's title is intriguing. It seems to emphasize prophetic mission rather than scientific achievement, but the reason for choosing &#x201C;oracle&#x201D; emerges as we read along. In many chapters we find reminders that Hamilton combined a romantic interest in poetry and history with a rather bleak appreciation of human nature and the long-term perspectives of civilization. He increasingly felt the urge to share his inconvenient truth that our genomes would be no match for rapidly evolving diseases unless we continued to increase our dependence on the permanent surveillance of a global health system&#x2014;which he envisaged would be prone to episodes of disastrous failure and would erode our self-sustained individuality. These convictions were driven by what he considered the true self of nature that few are willing to face, possibly because we discount unimaginable futures even more readily than those we think we can predict.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Forest undertaker.</title>
<p>The bulky and strong Amazonian carrion scarab beetle <italic>Coprophanaeus lancifer</italic>, to which Hamilton wished to commit his remains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="340_145_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: CONRAD GILLET/UNIVERSITY OF EAST ANGLIA</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Although his later derivation showed that inclusive fitness is fully equivalent with selection operating simultaneously at different levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>), Hamilton continued to equate group selection logic in the human domain with totalitarian forces that would ultimately turn people into subdued citizens of a Huxleyan World State. With tribal nepotism and group-selected xenophobia as equally depressive smaller-scale alternatives, he inferred that humanity's future would require careful management of our rare cooperative tendencies rather than trust in a primate heritage that seems hardly benign. Had he lived until now, I think he would have appreciated modern versions of the same idea, emphasizing that large-scale cooperation relies on institution-building rather than human nature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Controversies abounded throughout Hamilton's career, most of them boiling down to being given a hard time by journal editors, reviewers of his manuscripts, and peers discrediting the novelty or general importance of his insights. Similar attitudes can still be found, but they receive little credit in the book. Few would argue that we can dismiss modern particle physics or big-bang theory because that would obviously reverse our state of civilization. Segerstrale makes a strong case for the Hamiltonian version of Darwinism being of the same caliber. Not because we necessarily like it, but because it appears to be the only way to make rational sense of nature's true self. To ultimately weave nature's grand tapestry in humanistic colors, the gene had to be conceptually disconnected from the individual, and that is what Hamilton achieved.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grafen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, in <article-title>Narrow Roads of Gene Land</article-title>, <volume>vol. 3</volume>: <source>Last Words</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ridley</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, Ed. (<publisher-name>Oxford Univ. Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>, <year>2005</year>), pp. <fpage>423</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>458</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>W. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Ethol. Ecol. Evol.</source> <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage> (<year>2000</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>The Price of Altruism: George Price and the Search for the Origins of Kindness</source> (<publisher-name>Bodley Head</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <year>2010</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>The Better Angels of Our Nature: Why Violence Has Declined</source> (<publisher-name>Viking</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <year>2011</year>).</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>