<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ASTRONOMY</subject><subject>ECOLOGY</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Newsmakers</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6094</issue>
<fpage seq="b">507</fpage>
<lpage>507</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>This week's Newsmaker is paleobotanist Kirk Johnson, who was named the new director of the Smithsonian Institution National Museum of Natural History.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>This week's Newsmaker is paleobotanist Kirk Johnson, who was named the new director of the Smithsonian Institution National Museum of Natural History.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec>
<title>Three Q&apos;s</title>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<p>Johnson</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_507b_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: FORREST GIBSON/DENVER MUSEUM OF NATURE &amp; SCIENCE</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Paleobotanist <bold>Kirk Johnson</bold> was named the new director of the Smithsonian Institution National Museum of Natural History last week. Chief curator at the Denver Museum of Nature &amp; Science, Johnson, 51, will start on 29 October, replacing Cristi&#x00E1;n Samper, who on 1 August took over the Wildlife Conservation Society in New York City.</p>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>Q:</bold></speaker>
<p><bold>How do you want to influence the community?</bold></p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker></speaker>
<p>The museum is the urban touchpoint to the natural world. You have all these scientists making all these discoveries one wall away from 7.4 million visitors. I will be exploring ways to use social media, innovative exhibitry, and the Internet to make what happens at the museum more accessible.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>Q:</bold></speaker>
<p><bold>What challenges does the Smithsonian natural history museum face?</bold></p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker></speaker>
<p>There&apos;s a tremendous amount of confusion in this country about what science is and how science accrues knowledge for the betterment of the community. Connecting the content and the joy of science to the public is something that can be done better here than any place else in the country.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>Q:</bold></speaker>
<p><bold>Do you have any innovative ideas for the renovation of the dinosaur hall?</bold></p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker></speaker>
<p> When people go to a museum, they see dusty dinosaurs; they don&apos;t realize that new dinosaurs are being discovered at an incredible rate every year. My thought is: How do you make this exhibit something that demonstrates the vitality of paleontology? It&apos;s also a science that has tremendous information about how the planet has changed through time. To realize that the polar regions have been forested for most of our history, not just covered by ice &#x2026; is a very amazing thing [about which] most people in the street have no idea. But that&apos;s paleontology 101.</p>
</speech>
</sec>
</body>
</article>