<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="review-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1225474</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1225474</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Special Issue Perspective</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>special/perspective</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ASTRONOMY</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Classical Black Holes: The Nonlinear Dynamics of Curved Spacetime</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Black Holes</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>Kip S.</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff>Theoretical Astrophysics, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA 91125, USA. E-mail: <email xlink:href="kip@caltech.edu">kip@caltech.edu</email></aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>03</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6094</issue>
<issue-title content-type="special-issue">Black Holes</issue-title>
<fpage>536</fpage>
<lpage>538</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Numerical simulations have revealed two types of physical structures, made from curved spacetime, that are attached to black holes: tendexes, which stretch or squeeze anything they encounter, and vortexes, which twist adjacent inertial frames relative to each other. When black holes collide, their tendexes and vortexes interact and oscillate (a form of nonlinear dynamics of curved spacetime). These oscillations generate gravitational waves, which can give kicks up to 4000 kilometers per second to the merged black hole. The gravitational waves encode details of the spacetime dynamics and will soon be observed and studied by the Laser Interferometer Gravitational Wave Observatory and its international partners.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Maria Cruz</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Harry Jach</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<boxed-text content-type="sci-custom 6094-blackholes"></boxed-text>
<p>In the 1950s and &#x2019;60s, John Archibald Wheeler speculated that curved, empty spacetime could exhibit rich, nonlinear dynamics&#x2014;which he called geometrodynamics&#x2014;analogous to the writhing surface of the ocean in a storm. Wheeler urged his students and colleagues to seek insight into geometrodynamics by solving Einstein&#x2019;s general relativity equations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Motivated by Wheeler and by the 1963 discovery of quasi-stellar radio sources (quasars), physicists identified black holes as &#x201C;gravitational solitons&#x201D;&#x2014;objects made wholly and solely from curved spacetime, objects whose curvature is generated by the energy stored in the curvature. From general relativity, they deduced that black holes can spin and oscillate; that the evolution of a black hole is governed by a set of physical laws that resemble the laws of thermodynamics; and most famously that, if a black hole is tiny, it can emit Hawking radiation due to quantum effects and thereby gradually evaporate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>At this point (~1976), research on black-hole theory bifurcated into the classical theory for the large black holes that astronomers study, and the quantum theory for tiny, evaporating black holes that can teach us about the laws of quantum gravity. The quantum theory is described in another Perspective in this issue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). I shall describe recent developments in the classical theory.</p>
<p>In the late 1970s, those of us working on the classical theory were stymied. We wanted to learn the details of the &#x201C;stormy behavior&#x201D; of curved spacetime that would be generated, for example, when spinning black holes collide; but we weren&#x2019;t clever enough to dig the answers out of Einstein&#x2019;s equations. We wanted to observe that stormy behavior in the astrophysical universe, but astronomical telescopes looked hopelessly incapable of such observations.</p>
<p>This motivated us to formulate a two-pronged attack on geometrodynamics: numerical simulations of colliding black holes to discover relativity&#x2019;s predictions, and observations of gravitational waves from colliding black holes to test those predictions. The simulations have reached fruition in the past several years, and the observations are near fruition, as I shall describe.</p>
<p>To make sense out of the simulations, we have invented a way to visualize the Riemann curvature tensor, which embodies the curvature of spacetime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>). Just as the electromagnetic field can be split into an electric field and a magnetic field, so the Riemann tensor can be split into a tidal field <inline-formula><mml:math id="m1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> that stretches and squeezes anything it encounters, and a frame-drag field <inline-formula><mml:math id="m2"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> that twists adjacent inertial frames with respect to each other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). Mathematically these fields are second-rank tensors, i.e., 3 by 3 matrices. Just as electric and magnetic fields can be visualized using field lines&#x2014;e.g., the dipolar magnetic field lines that surround Earth&#x2014;so <inline-formula><mml:math id="m3"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="m4"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can each be described by three orthogonal sets of field lines, called (tidal) tendex lines for <inline-formula><mml:math id="m5"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and (frame-drag) vortex lines for <inline-formula><mml:math id="m6"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>The tendex lines come in two varieties: those that stretch (red lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>) and those that squeeze (blue lines). If a person&#x2019;s body is oriented along a red tendex line, then she gets stretched with a relative head-to-foot gravitational acceleration that is the product of her length times the tendex line&#x2019;s tendicity (eigenvalue of <inline-formula><mml:math id="m7"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>), and she gets squeezed transversely by the blue tendex lines that pass transversely through her body. Red tendex lines that stick radially out of the Moon and pass through the Earth raise high tides on the Earth&#x2019;s oceans; the Moon&#x2019;s circumferential (blue) tendex lines, passing through Earth, produce low tides.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) The (tidal) tendex lines around a spherical body, which could be the Earth, Moon, Sun, or a nonspinning black hole. (<bold>B</bold>) The (frame-drag) vortex lines around a black hole that spins at 0.95 of its maximum possible rate. From (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>).</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_536_F1"></graphic></fig>
<p>Vortex lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>) also come in two varieties. If a person&#x2019;s body is oriented along a red vortex line, then gyroscopes at her feet precess (twist) counterclockwise as measured by an inertial frame at her head, and gyroscopes at her head precess in the same counterclockwise direction as measured by an inertial frame at her feet. If her body is oriented along a blue vortex line, then the precessions (twists) are clockwise. The angular velocity of precession is the product of her length times the vortex line&#x2019;s vorticity (eigenvalue of <inline-formula><mml:math id="m8"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). These precessions are similar to wringing a wet towel to remove water: There are two ways for you to twist the towel, clockwise or counterclockwise.</p>
<p>The horizon (surface) of the black hole in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref> is color coded by the vorticity that would be felt by a person falling lengthwise through it (the normal normal component of the frame-drag field, <inline-formula><mml:math id="m9"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub>nn</sub>). The red and blue spots on the horizon have large horizon vorticity, so we call them horizon vortexes. The bundles of vortex lines emerging from those spots also have large vorticity; they are (frame-drag) vortexes.</p>
<p>A dozen research groups are now simulating black-hole collisions, and the simulations are teaching us about geometrodynamics. I shall describe two instructive examples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Lovelace <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>) have simulated the head-on collision of two identical black holes with spin axes perpendicular to the direction of collision and antiparallel to each other (movie S1 and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). When the holes collide, each hole deposits its two vortexes on the merged horizon. The four vortexes, feeling each others&#x2019; presence, interact. Adjacent vortexes slow each other and then exchange vorticity (direction and magnitude of twist). The red horizon vortexes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref> become blue and the blue become red, leading to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>. In the middle of this exchange, when the (color-coded) horizon momentarily turns green everywhere, the vortex lines pop off the horizon, the red lines&#x2019; ends merge to form red closed loops, and the blue lines&#x2019; ends similarly merge; these red and blue loops form a torus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>) that expands outward much like an expanding smoke ring. In the meantime, the hole&#x2019;s oscillation energy, which has been temporarily stored in tendexes (not shown), sloshes back into a new set of vortex lines attached to the hole (center of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>; same as Fig. 2A but different perspective).</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption>
<p>(<bold>A</bold> to <bold>C</bold>) Snapshots of vortex lines and horizon vorticity for a simulation of a head-on collision of two spinning black holes, after the holes have merged. From simulation described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>); figure by F. Zhang, described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>) with dashed tendex lines drawn in by hand.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_536_F2"></graphic></fig>
<p>As the torus of twisting space expands, its time-evolving vortex lines create a set of tendex lines that wrap longitudinally and transversely around the torus (dashed brown and green lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>). The torus has now become a gravitational wave&#x2014;a curved-spacetime structure that contains intertwined vortex lines and tendex lines and propagates outward at the speed of light. As the merged hole oscillates, it emits a sequence of tori that carry away the oscillation energy. The oscillations gradually die out, leaving a final, nonspinning black hole with its vortexes exponentially weakened and disappearing.</p>
<p>My second example is the more astrophysically realistic case of two identical spinning black holes that spiral together in a near-circular orbit, then collide and merge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>). The four vortexes get deposited on the merged horizon (red and blue spots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>); in addition, the orbital angular momentum causes the merged hole to tumble end over end in the plane of the picture, and that rotational tumbling creates two more vortexes on the horizon (not shown): one, red, facing the reader; the other, blue, on the back. The four tumbling vortexes generate spiral arms, much like water splaying out of a rotating sprinkler head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). As the arms spiral outward, their vortex lines generate accompanying tendex lines, producing the intertwined complex that we recognize as a gravitational wave.</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption>
<p>Collision and merger of two spinning black holes in a circularly orbiting binary. (<bold>A</bold>) Merged horizon, colored by its vorticity, and some vortex lines (red and blue) and tendex lines (brown and green) emerging from the horizon (schematic). (<bold>B</bold>) Equatorial plane of the merged black hole, several rotations after merger, showing (i) two families of vortex lines (solid and dashed), and (ii) the vorticity of the strongest lines (blue for solid vortex lines, red for dashed; color intensity proportional to magnitude of vorticity). Drawing (B) was computed by D. Nichols via black-hole perturbation theory for a merged hole with spin 0.7 of its maximum.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_536_F3"></graphic></fig>
<p>The merged horizon not only has attached tumbling vortex lines; it also has attached tumbling tendex lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>) whose tendicity is nearly minus the horizon&#x2019;s scalar curvature. On each of the horizon&#x2019;s sphere-like ends, its scalar curvature is positive so it sprouts a bundle of brown tendex lines, i.e., a stretching tendex. Around the horizon&#x2019;s saddle-shaped middle the scalar curvature is negative, so it sprouts a fan-shaped bundle of green tendex lines, i.e., a squeezing fan-shaped tendex. As the horizon tumbles, its red and green tendexes sweep outward and backward in spiral arms, similar to the vortex spirals of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>, and the outspiraling tendex lines generate accompanying vortex lines, producing thereby a gravitational wave.</p>
<p>There thus are two gravitational waves coming from the merged, tumbling black hole: a vortex-generated wave (which, at late times, has negative parity&#x2014;it changes sign under reflection) and a tendex-generated wave (with positive parity). These two waves superpose on each other constructively in some directions and destructively in others, enabling the waves to carry a large amount of net momentum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>). Correspondingly, the waves can give the merged black hole a large radiation-reaction kick (up to 4000 km/s) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Because the horizon&#x2019;s two-dimensional scalar curvature is (nearly) minus the tendicity of the tendex lines that emerge from it, and as they turn those lines generate half the gravitational waves, there is a strong correlation between the horizon&#x2019;s scalar curvature and the emitted waves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>The gravitational waveforms from a merging black-hole binary carry detailed information about the initial black holes (their masses, spins, and orbit), the final merged black hole (its mass and spin), and the geometrodynamics of the merger. To facilitate extracting this information from observed waves, and to facilitate finding the waves themselves in the noisy output of gravitational-wave detectors, an international collaboration of numerical relativity groups is generating a large catalog of waveforms, and a dictionary of the information in the waveforms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13"><italic>13</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>These waveforms will be observed by the Laser Interferometer Gravitational Wave Observatory (LIGO), with interferometers in Livingston, Louisiana, and Hanford, Washington, and by LIGO&#x2019;s international partners: the Virgo interferometer near Pisa, Italy, and (just recently funded) the Kamioka Gravitational Wave Antenna (KAGRA) in the Kamioka mine in Japan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>). The initial LIGO and Virgo interferometers (with sensitivities at which it is plausible but not likely to see waves) were designed to give the experimental teams enough experience to perfect the techniques and design for advanced interferometers&#x2014;that will have sensitivities at which they are likely to see lots of waves.</p>
<p>Initial LIGO and Virgo exceeded and reached their design sensitivities, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>), and carried out searches for waves in 2006&#x2013;2007 and 2009&#x2013;2010. As was expected, no waves have been seen, though the data are still being analyzed and many interesting results have been obtained (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16"><italic>16</italic></xref>). The advanced LIGO and advanced Virgo interferometers are now being installed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17"><italic>17</italic></xref>) and by 2017 should reach sensitivities at which black-hole mergers are observed. The LIGO/Virgo team will use their merger observations to test numerical relativity&#x2019;s geometrodynamic predictions. This will be just one of many science payoffs from LIGO and its partners, but it is the payoff that excites me the most.</p>
</body>
<back><app-group><app>
<title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/337/6094/536/DC1">www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/337/6094/536/DC1</ext-link></p>
<p>Movie S1</p></supplementary-material></app></app-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="book">J. A. Wheeler, <italic>Geometrodynamics</italic> (Academic Press, New York, 1962).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="book">B. Carter, S. Chandrasekhar, G. W. Gibbons, in <italic>General Relativity, An Einstein Centenary Survey</italic>, S. W. Hawking, W. Israel, Eds. (Cambridge Univ. Press, Cambridge, 1979), chapters 6, 7, and 13.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witten</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Quantum mechanics of black holes</article-title>.<year> </year><source>Science</source> 
<volume>337</volume>, 
<fpage>538</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Frame-dragging vortexes and tidal tendexes attached to colliding black holes: Visualizing the curvature of spacetime</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source> 
<volume>106</volume>, 
<fpage>151101</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.106.151101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21568540</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R5"><note><label>5</label>
<p>If two freely falling particles have a vector separation &#x0394;<bold><italic>x</italic></bold>, then (i) the tidal field gives them a relative acceleration &#x0394;<bold><italic>a</italic> = &#x2212; </bold><inline-formula><mml:math id="m10"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>&#x00B7;&#x0394;<bold><italic>x</italic></bold>, and (ii) gyroscopes carried by the particles precess with respect to each other with angular velocity &#x0394;<bold>&#x03A9; = </bold><inline-formula><mml:math id="m11"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>&#x00B7;&#x0394;<bold><italic>x</italic></bold>.</p></note></ref>
<ref id="R6"><note><label>6</label>
<p>Each tendex line (or vortex line) is the integral curve of an eigenvector field of the tidal field <inline-formula><mml:math id="m12"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (or frame-drag field <inline-formula><mml:math id="m13"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), and the line&#x2019;s tendicity (or vorticity) is that eigenvector&#x2019;s eigenvalue. A knowledge of the tendex and vortex lines and their tendicities and vorticities is equivalent to a full knowledge of the Riemann tensor.</p></note></ref>
<ref id="R7"><note><label>7</label>
<p>For pictures and movies from these and other simulations see, e.g., <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://black-holes.org/explore2.html">http://black-holes.org/explore2.html</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://numrel.aei.mpg.de/images">http://numrel.aei.mpg.de/images</ext-link>.</p></note></ref>
<ref id="R8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lovelace</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Momentum flow in black-hole binaries: II. Numerical simulations of equal-mass, head-on mergers with antiparallel spins</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. D Part. Fields Gravit. Cosmol.</source> 
<volume>82</volume>, 
<fpage>064031</fpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevD.82.064031</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R9"><note><label>9</label>
<p>For example, the simulation by Owen described in figure 5 of (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>).</p></note></ref>
<ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campanelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lousto</surname><given-names>C. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zlochower</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>,
<article-title>Maximum gravitational recoil</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source> 
<volume>98</volume>, 
<fpage>231102</fpage> (<year>2007</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.98.231102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17677894</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x00E1;lez</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sperhake</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x00FC;gmann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Husa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Supermassive recoil velocities for binary black-hole mergers with antialigned spins</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source> 
<volume>98</volume>, 
<fpage>231101</fpage> (<year>2007</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.98.231101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17677893</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaramillo</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moesta</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezzolla</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Black-hole horizons as probes of black hole dynamics. I. Post-merger recoil in head-on collisions</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. D Part. Fields Gravit. Cosmol.</source> 
<volume>85</volume>, 
<fpage>084030</fpage> (<year>2012</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevD.85.084030</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="web">H. P. Pfeiffer, <italic>Class. Quant. Grav</italic>., in press; available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/1203.5166v2">http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/1203.5166v2</ext-link>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ligo.caltech.edu/">www.ligo.caltech.edu/</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://,">, </ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ligo.org/">www.ligo.org/</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://,">, </ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.cascina.virgo.infn.it">www.cascina.virgo.infn.it</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://gwcenter.icrr.u-tokyo.ac.jp/en/">http://gwcenter.icrr.u-tokyo.ac.jp/en/</ext-link></citation></ref>
<ref id="R15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="web">LIGO Scientific Collaboration and Virgo Collaboration, &#x201C;Sensitivity achieved by the LIGO and Virgo gravitational wave detectors during LIGO&#x2019;s sixth and Virgo&#x2019;s second and third science runs,&#x201D; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/1203.2674">http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/1203.2674</ext-link>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="R16"><note><label>16</label>
<p>All published results are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.lsc-group.phys.uwm.edu/ppcomm/Papers.html">https://www.lsc-group.phys.uwm.edu/ppcomm/Papers.html</ext-link>.</p></note></ref>
<ref id="R17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.advancedligo.mit.edu/">https://www.advancedligo.mit.edu/</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cascina.virgo.infn.it/advirgo/">https://www.cascina.virgo.infn.it/advirgo/</ext-link></citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title><p>For insights into the geometrodynamics of black holes, I thank my research collaborators: J. Brink, Y. Chen, J. Kaplan, G. Lovelace, K. Matthews, D. Nichols, R. Owen, M. Scheel, F. Zhang, and A. Zimmerman. My geometrodynamic research is supported by the Sherman Fairchild Foundation, the Brinson Foundation, and NSF grant PHY-1068881.</p>
</ack></back>
</article>