<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ANTHRO</subject><subject>SOCIOLOGY</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Archaeology</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Ice Age Tools Hint at 40,000 Years of Bushman Culture</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balter</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6094</issue>
<fpage>512</fpage>
<lpage>512</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Archaeologists studying a South African cave say they have found 44,000-year-old artifacts&#x2014;including bone tools and poisoned arrowheads&#x2014;nearly identical to those still in use by hunter-gatherers.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Archaeologists studying a South African cave say they have found 44,000-year-old artifacts&#x2014;including bone tools and poisoned arrowheads&#x2014;nearly identical to those still in use by hunter-gatherers. The team calls the finds the oldest known examples of &#x22;modern culture,&#x22; the adaptations that enabled <italic>Homo sapiens </italic>to make it through the last Ice Age and survive to the present day.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Archaeologists studying a South African cave say they have found 44,000-year-old artifacts&#x2014;including bone tools and poisoned arrowheads&#x2014;nearly identical to those still in use by hunter-gatherers. The team calls the finds the oldest known examples of &#x201C;modern culture,&#x201D; the adaptations that enabled <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> to make it through the last Ice Age and survive to the present day.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Ancestral artifacts.</title>
<p>Tools and ornaments found in a South African cave are almost identical to those San hunter-gatherers still use 40 millennia later.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_512_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: COURTESY OF FRANCESCO D&apos;ERRICO AND LUCINDA BACKWELL</attrib>
</fig>
<p>The evidence, from Border Cave in the Lebombo Mountains near the border with Swaziland, adds up to &#x201C;an attractive argument&#x201D; that there was continuity between ancient and modern-day cultures, says Erella Hovers, an archaeologist at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Mount Scopus. Stanley Ambrose, an archaeologist at the University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, agrees: &#x201C;These findings are very important, because Border Cave is a keystone archaeological [site] for this region, and we have waited a long time for the details.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Border Cave was first excavated in the 1930s and 1940s, but the most extensive dig there was conducted in the 1970s by archaeologist Peter Beaumont, now at the McGregor Museum in Kimberley, South Africa. Recent techniques made the new analysis possible, says Francesco d&apos;Errico, an archaeologist at the University of Bordeaux in France and lead author of the new study, published this week in the <italic>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</italic>.</p>
<p>The team, which includes Beaumont and other researchers from South Africa, Europe, and the United States, used scanning electron microscopy, x-ray analysis, gas chromatography, and new mathematical approaches to fine-tune radiocarbon dating. The group concluded that numerous artifacts at Border Cave ranging in age from about 39,000 to 44,000 years old are nearly identical to implements used by the San hunter-gatherers of southern Africa (also known as the Bushmen) during historical times, and in some cases even today.</p>
<p>The artifacts include bone tools shaped into long shafts by scraping, among them one decorated with an incision that spirals around the length of the shaft and is filled with red pigment; beads made of ostrich eggshells; &#x201C;digging sticks&#x201D; like those the San and other hunter-gatherers use to dig up tubers; a stick similar to a tool with which the San apply poison to their arrows, bearing traces of a poisonous compound from the castor bean; and four bones with notches the team interprets as &#x201C;tally sticks&#x201D; used for counting. Previously, the earliest known examples of San-like artifacts came from sites no older than 20,000 years, the team notes&#x2014;leaving a gap, Ambrose says, that may point to a population dip caused by changing climate.</p>
<p>D&apos;Errico maintains that the artifacts &#x201C;strongly point to a continuity in material culture and lifestyle&#x201D; with that of San peoples living today. He concedes that the team &#x201C;cannot [yet] demonstrate a continuity in the more intimate aspects of San culture such as language, religious beliefs, and myths.&#x201D; But with the new research, d&apos;Errico says, &#x201C;such continuity &#x2026; now becomes a viable hypothesis.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Pauline Wiessner, an anthropologist at the University of Utah in Salt Lake City who studies San culture, calls the argument for continuity &#x201C;convincing,&#x201D; although, she says, the modern San don&apos;t use tally sticks. But she cautions that the similar artifacts did not necessarily have the same meaning in the past. For example, in historical times young San women wore ostrich eggshell beads to advertise that they were available for marriage, and marriages cemented social ties over distances of hundreds of kilometers. To test whether beads were used that way in the past, Wiessner says, researchers could conduct isotope analysis to see if the Border Cave eggshells came from local sources or from far away.</p>
<p>In the meantime, Hovers says, the current evidence for continuity at Border Cave &#x201C;is probably as strong as prehistory can offer.&#x201D;</p>
</body>
</article>