<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="article-commentary" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id><journal-title>Science</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1227095</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1227095</article-id><article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Perspective</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>perspective</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Molecular Biology</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>MOLEC BIOL</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Outsourcing Genome Protection</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xiol</surname><given-names>Jordi</given-names></name></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Pillai</surname><given-names>Ramesh S.</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff id="aff1">European Molecular Biology Laboratory, 6 Rue Jules Horowitz, BP 181, 38042 Grenoble, France.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>pillai@embl.fr</email></corresp>
</author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date><volume>337</volume><issue>6094</issue><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>Small RNAs repress transposons by triggering the formation of another class of small RNAs that silence transposon targets.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="excerpt">
<p>Eukaryotic genomes are populated by invading mobile genetic elements called transposons that threaten genome stability as they may cause mutations and chromosomal rearrangements. In animal germ lines, protection against these parasitic elements is conferred by Piwi proteins and their associated &#x223C;20- to 30-nucleotide small RNA guides, called Piwi-interacting RNAs (piRNAs), which actively repress transposons to safeguard the genetic information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). On page 574 of this issue, Bagijn <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>) reveal how piRNAs in the worm <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> identify their transposon targets, triggering local generation of another class of small RNAs, called 22G-RNAs, that carry out silencing. Together with four other reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>), the study by Bagijn <italic>et al.</italic> provides a comprehensive view of worm piRNA targets, mechanism of piRNA action, and pathways that discriminate foreign elements from cellular mRNAs.</p>
</abstract><custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Lisa D. Chong</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Harry Jach</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Eukaryotic genomes are populated by invading mobile genetic elements called transposons that threaten genome stability as they may cause mutations and chromosomal rearrangements. In animal germ lines, protection against these parasitic elements is conferred by Piwi proteins and their associated &#x223C;20- to 30-nucleotide small RNA guides, called Piwi-interacting RNAs (piRNAs), which actively repress transposons to safeguard the genetic information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). On page <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="337" page="574" issue="6094">574</related-article> of this issue, Bagijn <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>) reveal how piRNAs in the worm <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> identify their transposon targets, triggering local generation of another class of small RNAs, called 22G-RNAs, that carry out silencing. Together with four other reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>), the study by Bagijn <italic>et al.</italic> provides a comprehensive view of worm piRNA targets, mechanism of piRNA action, and pathways that discriminate foreign elements from cellular mRNAs.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Recognition of nonself RNA from self.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) In the worm, the complex containing the Piwi protein PRG-1 and piRNA scans all RNAs in germ cells to identify targets via imperfect complementarity. Cellular mRNAs are depleted of high-affinity piRNA binding sites and/or are actively protected by an unknown mechanism. (<bold>B</bold>) piRNAs then trigger the generation of multiple small RNAs called 22G-RNAs (by recruiting an RNA polymerase) that associate with WAGO proteins, amplifying the silencing signal. (<bold>C</bold>) WAGO protein, in turn, represses transposon targets in the cytoplasm and the nucleus for multigenerational silencing by inducing chromatin modifications.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_529_F1" />
<attrib>CREDIT: C. BICKEL/<italic>SCIENCE</italic></attrib>
</fig>
<p>piRNAs function as an immune system that distinguishes transposons from cellular mRNAs and, once they identify a threat, mount an enhanced response. In their simplest mode of action, piRNAs identify target RNAs by base-pairing via sequence complementarity. Some of the Piwi proteins harbor an endonuclease (Slicer) activity, which allows them to cleave target RNAs, resulting in silencing. <italic>C. elegans</italic> piRNAs (also called 21U-RNAs) bind the Piwi protein PRG-1, and the pathway is implicated in the control of the Tc3 DNA transposon. However, piRNAs displaying perfect complementarity to the Tc3 transposons are not detected, raising the question as to how piRNAs function in worms.</p>
<p>Bagijn <italic>et al.</italic> used an in vivo piRNA fluorescent reporter gene to show that a single perfectly complementary binding site for an endogenous worm piRNA is sufficient for silencing. The authors show that silencing does not depend on the slicer activity of PRG-1, thus precluding direct cleavage of the target RNA as a mechanism. Instead, the PRG-1-piRNA complex recruits RNA-dependent RNA polymerases near the piRNA-target interaction site to transcribe 22-nucleotide small RNAs (called 22G-RNAs) using the target RNA as a template (see the figure). The resulting 22G-RNAs are loaded into a set of worm-specific Argonaute (WAGO) proteins, which are the actual effector molecules of the response initiated by piRNAs, because they mediate posttranscriptional and transcriptional silencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>). Given that a single piRNA sequence can give rise to several distinct antisense 22G-RNAs, every targeting event also effectively amplifies the silencing signal.</p>
<p>Point mutations within the fluorescent reporter gene, and genome-wide computational predictions, revealed that worm piRNAs initiate generation of 22G-RNAs on targets that are recognized with imperfect complementarity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). This suggests that <italic>C. elegans</italic> piRNAs could act in a way that is similar to that of most animal microRNAs, where mismatches (up to four) are tolerated, but complementarity via the seed sequence (nucleotides 2 to 8) in the 5&#x2032; end of the small RNA is essential for silencing. However, given the sequence diversity of piRNAs (&#x223C;16,000 sequences), these relaxed targeting rules would also imply that most cellular mRNAs are targeted. Indeed, expression of cellular and transposon mRNAs with imperfect binding sites for piRNAs was increased, while generation of 22G-RNAs from these sites dropped in piRNA mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Increased targeting due to a relaxation of base-pairing rules could be beneficial, but how would cellular mRNAs be protected from runaway silencing? Bagijn <italic>et al.</italic> suggest that piRNAs are evolving to avoid targeting mRNAs, as they observe a depletion of antisense sequences to protein-coding genes in <italic>C. elegans</italic> and the related worm <italic>C. briggsae</italic>, despite an evident lack of conservation of piRNAs and transposons between them. Alternatively, a tantalizing possibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>) is that a small RNA pathway, guided by the Argonaute protein CSR-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>), retains a &#x201C;memory&#x201D; of cellular mRNAs (&#x201C;self&#x201D;) and protects them from piRNAs. Both hypotheses are compatible and could reflect the complexity of achieving &#x201C;self&#x201D; versus &#x201C;nonself&#x201D; recognition.</p>
<p>Once piRNAs have managed the immediate threat of a foreign element, 22G-RNAs establish an epigenetic memory that mediates transgenerational repression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). Although initiated by piRNAs, permanent silencing soon becomes independent of the Piwi pathway and is stable for generations. Consistent with an impact on transcription, the repressed target region becomes packaged with silent histone (heterochromatic) marks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). Genetic screens and candidate approaches identify nuclear WAGOs, chromodomain protein, and putative histone methyltransferases, among others, as key components of the machinery required to maintain this repression over generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). The studies by Bagijn <italic>et al.</italic> and others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>) provide a global view on how foreign elements are silenced&#x2014;from the initial trigger by piRNAs, to a heritable state via 22G-RNAs. Like worm piRNAs, some mammalian Piwi proteins are invested with millions of uniquely mapping piRNAs, but with no known function. It can be envisaged that with relaxed engagement rules, these might also participate in genome surveillance. The relevance of mRNA regulation by piRNAs, however, remains to be clarified and raises questions about the lack of piRNA sequence conservation. It is hoped that the discovery of factors required for permanent silencing in the worm will stimulate research in the mammalian and insect piRNA pathways, where a direct communication with the nuclear compartment is established.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aravin</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brennecke</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Science</source>
<volume>318</volume>, <fpage>761</fpage> (<year>2007</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagijn</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Science</source>
<volume>337</volume>, <fpage>574</fpage> (<year>2012</year>); 10.1126/science.1220952.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1220952</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Cell</source>
<volume>150</volume>, <fpage>78</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Cell</source>
<volume>150</volume>, <fpage>88</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirayama</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Cell</source>
<volume>150</volume>, <fpage>65</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Nature</source>
10.1038/nature11352 (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11352</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yigit</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Cell</source>
<volume>127</volume>, <fpage>747</fpage> (<year>2006</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Claycomb</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Cell</source>
<volume>139</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
