<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id><journal-title>Science</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>MEDICINE</subject><subject>VIROLOGY</subject><subject>SCI COMMUN</subject><subject>SCI POLICY</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>HIV/AIDS</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Dreams Meet Realities At AIDS Conference</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>Jon</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date><volume>337</volume><issue>6094</issue><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>The 19th International AIDS Conference, held in Washington, D.C., from 22 to 27 July, marked the meeting's return to the United States for the first time in 22 years.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>The 19th International AIDS Conference, held in Washington, D.C., from 22 to 27 July, marked the meeting's return to the United States for the first time in 22 years because President Barack Obama lifted an immigration ban on HIV-infected people in 2010. The U.S. government is leading the effort to provide lifesaving antiretroviral drugs to everyone in need and also articulating a bold agenda to take advantage of the breakthrough finding last year that people on treatment who fully suppress HIV rarely transmit the virus to others.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Return engagement.</title>
<p>Secretary of State Hillary Clinton welcomed delegates to the United States after a 22-year hiatus.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_509_F1"/>
<attrib>CREDIT: &#x00A9; IAS/RYAN <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://RAYBURN-COMMERCIALIMAGE.NET">RAYBURN-COMMERCIALIMAGE.NET</ext-link></attrib>
</fig>
<p><bold>WASHINGTON, D.C.</bold>&#x2014;In a sharp break from the past, the top U.S. government official to speak at the International AIDS Conference held here last week, U.S. Secretary of State Hillary Clinton, heard roars of appreciation rather than jeers of outrage. &#x201C;Let me say five words we have not been able to say for too long,&#x201D; Clinton told the 24,000 delegates, who gathered here from 22 to 27 July. &#x201C;Welcome to the United States!&#x201D;</p>
<p>The 19th International AIDS Conference marked the meeting&apos;s return to the United States for the first time in 22 years because President Barack Obama lifted an immigration ban on HIV-infected people in 2010. But that&apos;s not the main reason the crowd repeatedly jumped to its feet with applause during Clinton&apos;s speech. The U.S. government is leading the effort to provide lifesaving anti-retroviral (ARV) drugs to everyone in need and also articulating a bold agenda to take advantage of the breakthrough finding last year that people on treatment who fully suppress HIV rarely transmit the virus to others (<italic>Science</italic>, 13 July, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-publication" vol="337" page="168" issue="6091">168</related-article>). &#x201C;I am here today to make it absolutely clear: The United States is committed and will remain committed to achieving an AIDS-free generation,&#x201D; said Secretary Clinton. &#x201C;We will not back down; we will fight for the resources necessary to achieve this historic milestone.&#x201D;</p>
<p>The battle against HIV is having more success than ever. In 2011, 8 million people in low- and middle-income countries were receiving ARVs&#x2014;a 20% jump from the year before. Of the $16.8 billion now spent combating the disease, more than half of it comes from these countries, which reflects a growing commitment from low- and middle-income countries to dealing with their own epidemics. In developed countries, which have more experience with ARVs, it&apos;s clear that the drugs can extend lives by 50 years and all but stop mother-to-child transmission. As a sign of how much progress researchers have made in treatment and prevention, attempts to find a cure&#x2014;long viewed as a fantasy&#x2014;now lead the scientific agenda.</p>
<p>But several presentations made clear that a gulf separates aspirations from reality when it comes to &#x201C;ending AIDS,&#x201D; which Clinton and many other prominent speakers at the conference emphasized was now possible. The vast majority of the 34 million HIV-infected people in the world do not take ARVs, many receiving treatment have trouble staying on the medication, and new infection rates continue to climb in key populations. No AIDS vaccine is on the horizon. And funding shortfalls loom for global programs.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Poor no more.</title>
<p>Low-income countries with heavy HIV burdens increasingly are moving to middle-income status.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_509_F2"/>
<attrib>CREDIT: BERNHARD SCHW&#x00C4;RTLANDER/UNAIDS</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Peter Piot, who formerly headed the Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS) and now runs the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, supports the aspirational goals but worries that &#x201C;overpromising&#x201D; may lead to complacency. &#x201C;We have made significant progress, but it is not clear that we have the tools to end this epidemic,&#x201D; says Piot, who suspects the endgame will require a vaccine. &#x201C;What is missing today is a recognition that we need to sustain and intensify efforts for decades to come, and that the end of HIV/AIDS is not in sight.&#x201D;</p>
<p>The theme of the meeting was &#x201C;Turning the Tide Together,&#x201D; and UNAIDS epidemiologist Bernhard Schwartl&#x00E4;nder spelled out how it will require a massive financial infusion to accomplish the goals now on the table. At a U.N. General Assembly AIDS summit last year, member countries agreed to have 15 million people on ARVs by 2015, which Schwartl&#x00E4;nder said will require an additional $7 billion per year. He urged countries receiving aid to contribute more of their own budgets. &#x201C;The days when we had a simple world of rich countries and poor ones is gone, and with it we should abandon the concept of dependency and charity,&#x201D; Schwartl&#x00E4;nder said.</p>
<p>According to his calculations, if funding levels remain flat, the number of new infections will not budge. An infusion of $7 billion per year he said would cut new infections by more than 50% in 5 years. &#x201C;This certainly does look like a good investment to me,&#x201D; he said. &#x201C;And for me, the choice is clear: Let us pay now and not forever.&#x201D;</p>
<p>On the treatment front, Timothy Schacker of the University of Minnesota Medical Center, Fairview, reported that HIV-infected people in eastern Africa may have environmental disadvantages that limit the benefit of ARVs. Schacker and co-workers examined lymph nodes&#x2014;which are home to most of the CD4 cells that orchestrate the immune response&#x2014;of Ugandans. As HIV disease progresses, the lymph nodes become junked up with collagen, a fibrotic process that prevents CD4s from communicating with each other. They analyzed 30 HIV-uninfected Ugandans and discovered collagen levels that matched what they have seen in HIV-infected Minnesotans on ARVs. &#x201C;They look for all the world histologically &#x2026; like individuals who have early, chronic HIV infection,&#x201D; Schacker said. He suggests this occurs because the immune systems of the Ugandans faced many more assaults from diseases such as tuberculosis, malaria, and helminthic infections. &#x201C;When the patients become infected, in a sense they&apos;re already behind the eight ball.&#x201D;</p>
<p>A growing cadre of HIV researchers now working on a cure presented some of the most intriguing&#x2014;if early stage&#x2014;results. The only cured person, Timothy Brown, had his immune system destroyed to combat leukemia and then replaced with bone marrow transplants from a donor who had blood cells that were naturally resistant to the virus. Brown stopped taking ARVs more than 5 years ago, and the virus&#x2014;if it&apos;s even in his body&#x2014;remains at bay. Timothy Henrich of Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center in Boston reported two patients who could mimic Brown but for now fall short of being cured.</p>
<p>Henrich&apos;s patients both had Hodgkin&apos;s lymphoma and received bone marrow transplants from donors. Unlike Brown, the donors did not have HIV-resistant immune systems, but since the transplants, neither patient has had detectable levels of HIV on the most sensitive blood tests available. Henrich cautioned that the patients are still on ARVs and that they have not had their tissues analyzed for the virus, which often can harbor HIV when it&apos;s undetectable in blood. Transplants are not a widely applicable intervention, but they bolster the field because they prove that cures are possible.</p>
<p>At the closing ceremony, former U.S. President Bill Clinton stressed that many difficult questions remain, but he encouraged those in the field to keep their aspirations high. &#x201C;All of you have created the possibility that we could have an AIDS-free generation,&#x201D; Clinton said. &#x201C;You may think this is na&#x00EF;ve, but I&apos;ve seen it over and over again: If you build it, they will come. If you scale it up and it works, the money will be there to fund it.&#x201D;</p>
</body>
</article>
