<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1222565</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1222565</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Books <italic>et al.</italic></subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>books</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>PSYCHOLOGY</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Social Psychology</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Left and Right, Right and Wrong</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Jost</surname><given-names>John T.</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff id="aff1">The reviewer is at the Department of Psychology, New York University, 6 Washington Place, New York, NY 10003, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>john.jost@nyu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6094</issue>
<fpage>525</fpage>
<lpage>526</lpage>
<product product-type="book"><bold>The Righteous Mind</bold> Why Good People Are Divided by Politics and Religion <bold><italic>by Jonathan Haidt</italic></bold> Pantheon, New York, 2012. 441 pp. $28.95, C$33. ISBN 9780307377906. Allen Lane, London. &#x00A3;20. ISBN 9781846141812.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Haidt offers a provocative account of the psychological foundations of morality and how they lead to political conflicts.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Haidt offers a provocative account of the psychological foundations of morality and how they lead to political conflicts.</p></abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sherman J. Suter</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Harry Jach</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Jonathan Haidt is as ubiquitous as a social psychologist can be. When not giving TED talks or writing op-eds, he's showing up at the American Enterprise Institute, appearing on Bill Moyers's PBS program, warning the Dalai Lama about the evils of socialism, or taking a ribbing from Stephen Colbert. An energetic, self-confident, charismatic speaker, he is also a gifted storyteller who weaves together personal and historical anecdotes, biological metaphors, and even spiritual aphorisms.</p>
<p>In <italic>The Righteous Mind</italic>, Haidt attempts to explain the psychological foundations of morality and how they lead to political conflicts. The book's three parts are not as compatible or settled as Haidt's ingenious prose makes them seem. The first revisits the intriguing arguments of an earlier, influential paper (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>) in which he argued that moral reasoning is nothing but post hoc rationalizing of gut-level intuitions. The second introduces an evolutionarily inspired framework that specifies five or six &#x201C;moral foundations&#x201D; and applies this framework to an analysis of liberal-conservative differences in moral judgments. In the third part, Haidt speculates that patriotism, religiosity, and &#x201C;hive psychology&#x201D; in humans evolved rapidly through group-level selection.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_525_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDITS: RICHARDMASONER/WIKIMEDIA COMMONS; BROWNPAU/WIKIMEDIA COMMONS</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Early on, Haidt spurns as ideologically biased attempts by Lawrence Kohlberg, Elliot Turiel, and others to develop rational, objective psychological standards for moral development (or progression). He claims &#x201C;it was inevitable that [their] research would support worldviews that were secular, questioning, and egalitarian.&#x201D; But by redefining morality in subjective, culturally relative terms, Haidt does not correct the alleged error in research on developmental psychology so much as supplant it with his own worldview. Erasing any distinction between being moral and being moralistic, his purely subjectivist approach risks replacing what he perceives as a liberal bias in the psychological study of moral behavior with a conservative one.</p>
<p>How does he get there? A prominent theory of human reasoning holds that there are two cognitive systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>): System 1 is quick, intuitive, low-effort, and association-based. System 2 is slow, deliberate, high-effort, and logical. In Haidt's view, system 2 is really just a bullshitter&#x2014;a dissembler, a post hoc rationalizer. He asserts that humans make lousy scientists and logicians but excellent lawyers and press secretaries (people who consider only one side of an issue and defend it to the end). Haidt then proceeds to make a virtue of necessity: Because we are so emotionally driven and so bad at thinking rationally about morality, it must be that morality itself is and can only be based on gut-level (often emotional) intuitions. He discounts the possibility that, as Max Bazerman put it, &#x201C;System 2, our more deliberative thought processes, can be used to dampen the negative effects of our intuitive judgments&#x201D; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). However, research shows that diminishing the emotional intensity of situations through reappraisal leads people to abandon gutlevel intuitions and engage in more deliberative moral reasoning [e.g., (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>)].</p>
<p>After arguing that &#x201C;moral reasoning&#x201D; is nothing more than a post hoc rationalization of intuitive, emotional reactions, Haidt risks contradiction when claiming that liberals should embrace conservative moral intuitions about the importance of obeying authority, being loyal to the ingroup, and enforcing purity standards. If one were to accept Haidt's post hoc rationalization premise and his findings about differences in the moral judgments of liberals and conservatives, a more parsimonious (and empirically supportable) conjunction would be: For a variety of psychological reasons, conservatives do more rationalizing of gut-level reactions, and this makes them more moralistic (i.e., judgmental) than liberals. It does not, however, make them more moral in any meaningful sense of the word, nor does it provide a legitimate basis for criticizing liberal moral judgment the way Haidt does.</p>
<p>Haidt argues that the liberal moral code is deficient, because it is not based on all of his &#x201C;moral foundations.&#x201D; The liberal, he maintains, is like the idiot restaurateur who thought he could make a complete cuisine out of just one taste, however sweet. This illustrates the biggest flaw in Haidt's book: he swings back and forth between an allegedly value-neutral sense of &#x201C;moral&#x201D; (anything that an individual or a group believes is moral and serves to suppress selfishness) and a more prescriptive sense that he uses mainly to jab liberals. Ultimately, Haidt's own rhetorical choices render his claim to being unbiased unconvincing. If descriptive morality is based on whatever people believe, then both liberals and conservatives would seem to have equal claim to it. Does it really make sense, philosophically or psychologically or politically, to try to keep score, let alone to assert that &#x201C;more is better&#x201D; when it comes to moral judgment?</p>
<p>Haidt relies on data from an online survey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>) to support his critical evaluation of liberal &#x201C;narrowness.&#x201D; When asked about the extent to which it is good to be &#x201C;a team player,&#x201D; bad to &#x201C;hurt a defenseless animal,&#x201D; and so on, liberals are more concerned than conservatives about achieving fairness and avoiding harm, whereas conservatives are more concerned than liberals about obeying authority, favoring the ingroup, and enforcing norms of sanctity. Haidt misleadingly characterizes these results as suggesting that liberal morality is a partial subset of conservative morality&#x2014;indeed, he calls liberals &#x201C;moral monists.&#x201D; A simpler explanation is that liberal judgments are more differentiated than conservative judgments. Indeed, if respondents were to agree modestly with every question (exhibiting what survey researchers refer to as an acquiescence bias), their scores on the moral foundations questionnaire would look like the &#x201C;very conservative&#x201D; respondents whom Haidt admires for their balanced diet.</p>
<p>Beautifully written, Haidt's book shines a new and creative light on moral psychology and presents a provocative message. From a scientific perspective, however, his theory raises more questions than it answers. Why do some individuals feel that it is morally good (or necessary) to obey authority, favor the ingroup, and maintain purity, whereas others are skeptical? Why do some think it is morally acceptable to judge or mistreat others (such as gay or lesbian couples or, only a generation ago, interracial couples) because they dislike or feel disgusted by them, whereas others do not? Why do we &#x201C;care about violence toward many more classes of victims today than our grandparents did in their time&#x201D;? Haidt dismisses the possibility that this aspect of liberalism, which prizes universal over parochial considerations (the justice principle of impartiality), is in fact a tremendous cultural achievement&#x2014;a shared victory over the limitations of our more primitive ancestral legacy.</p>
<p>Before drawing sweeping, profound conclusions about the politics of morality, Haidt needs to address a more basic question: What are the specific, empirically falsifiable criteria for designating something as an evolutionarily grounded moral foundation? Haidt sets the bar pretty low&#x2014;anything that suppresses individual selfishness in favor of group interests. By this definition, the decision to plunder (and perhaps even murder) members of another tribe would count as a moral adaptation. Recent research suggests that Machiavellianism, authoritarianism, social dominance, and prejudice are positively associated with the moral valuation of ingroup, authority, and purity themes [e.g., (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>)]. If these are to be ushered into the ever-broadening tent of group morality, one wonders what it would take to be refused admission.</p>
<p>I see no compelling reason to assume that morality is&#x2014;let alone should be&#x2014;whatever comes first, easiest, or even most forcefully to mind (because of our evolutionary heritage or otherwise). In many situations behaving morally may require us to do what is difficult, perhaps even &#x201C;unnatural&#x201D; in some sense. Or, as John Stuart Mill put it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>), &#x201C;&#x2026; Nature cannot be a proper model for us to imitate. Either it is right that we should kill because nature kills; torture because nature tortures; ruin and devastate because nature does the like; or we ought not to consider what nature does, but what it is good to do.&#x201D;</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haidt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Psychol. Rev.</source> <volume>108</volume>, <fpage>814</fpage> (<year>2001</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kahneman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Thinking, Fast and Slow</source> (<publisher-name>Farrar</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Straus, and Giroux, New York</publisher-loc>, <year>2011</year>); reviewed in (9).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.psychologicalscience.org/index.php/publications/observer/obsonline/thinking-fast-and-slow.html">www.psychologicalscience.org/index.php/publications/observer/obsonline/thinking-fast-and-slow.html</ext-link>.</comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feinberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonenko</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>O. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Psychol. Sci.</source> <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>788</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.yourmorals.org">www.yourmorals.org</ext-link>.</comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arvan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Neuroethics</source> 10.1007/s12152-011-9140-6 (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12152-011-9140-6</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isherwood</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>J. Soc. Psychol.</source> <volume>151</volume>, <fpage>391</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mill</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Nature, the Utility of Religion, and Theism</source> (<publisher-name>Longmans</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Green, Reader, and Dyer, London</publisher-loc>, <year>1874</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Science</source> <volume>334</volume>, <fpage>1062</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>