<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI COMMUN</subject><subject>ASTRONOMY</subject><subject>SCI POLICY</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Newsmaker Interview: John Grunsfeld</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>NASA's Spacefaring Science Chief Sets a New Course for Mars</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname><given-names>Yudhijit</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6094</issue>
<fpage>511</fpage>
<lpage>512</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p><italic>Science </italic>spoke to John Grunsfeld, head of NASA's Science Mission Directorate, days before what he calls the science event of the decade: the 5 August (PDT) landing of Curiosity on the martian surface.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>When John Grunsfeld took over as head of NASA's Science Mission Directorate, he knew that he would soon have to answer to planetary scientists for the Administration's decision to pull NASA out of ExoMars and also face congressional ire over mismanagement of the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) project. Now, 7 months into the job, Grunsfeld says that JWST is on track for completion by 2018 and NASA is developing ideas for a new Mars program. <italic>Science </italic>spoke to Grunsfeld days before what he describes as the science event of the decade: the 5 August (PDT) landing of Curiosity on the martian surface.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Looking up.</title>
<p>Grunsfeld says NASA is pursuing an ambitious space science agenda for the next decade.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_511_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: WILL KIRK/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HOMEWOODPHOTO.JHU.EDU">HOMEWOODPHOTO.JHU.EDU</ext-link></attrib>
</fig>
<p>When John Grunsfeld took over as head of NASA&apos;s Science Mission Directorate in January, he knew his mission was at least as challenging as the shuttle flights he had flown as an astronaut. The directorate&apos;s $5 billion annual budget makes it one of the biggest science agencies in the world. Grunsfeld knew that he would soon have to answer to planetary scientists for the Administration&apos;s decision to pull NASA out of ExoMars, a European-led program to explore Mars through joint missions planned for 2016 and 2018. He would also face congressional ire over mismanagement of the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) project, whose new price tag of $8.7 billion exceeds an earlier cost estimate by more than $1.5 billion.</p>
<p>Now, 7 months into the job, Grunsfeld says that JWST is on track for completion by 2018 and that the lessons learned from earlier lapses in management will prevent further cost increases and delays. And NASA is developing ideas for a new Mars program, which Grunsfeld believes will set the course for human exploration of the planet within the next few decades. <italic>Science</italic> spoke to Grunsfeld days before what he describes as the science event of the decade: the 5 August (PDT) landing of Curiosity on the martian surface. His remarks have been edited for clarity and brevity.</p>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>Q:</bold></speaker>
<p><bold>You&apos;ve had some time now to settle into your job. How is it going?</bold></p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>J.G.:</bold></speaker>
<p>I decided to come back to NASA to work in the Science Mission Directorate because I love science, and NASA science is the greatest thing there is. From that perspective, it&apos;s been going well. From the [standpoint] of the education of a science director, it has been tough, and I knew it would be, because there are so many constraints and challenges. We are over subscribed: We have more that we would like to do than we have the funding or the ability to do. So it&apos;s challenging, it&apos;s a human power issue, a brainpower issue, and a funding issue.</p>
<p>[However], if you step back, we have nearly a $5 billion science budget, and we leverage the rest of NASA to accomplish our mission. That&apos;s the sign of a great nation, that we can invest at that level in space science, so I have no complaints.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>Q:</bold></speaker>
<p><bold>Since we&apos;re in a time of budget constraints, what are you doing to make NASA science dollars go farther?</bold></p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>J.G.:</bold></speaker>
<p>First, I have a strong commitment in reinforcing the culture within the Science Mission Directorate to have extremely sound science systems engineering. That&apos;s a combination of systems engineering and science to accomplish our goals, to make sure that when we sign up to do a mission on a certain cost and schedule, we do our best to maintain that. That&apos;s the key to having budget stability. And budget stability is what allows you to actually launch missions, to get the science out, to get the most science per unit dollar. At the top of our list is the James Webb Space Telescope. We have to maintain the budget, the schedule, the milestone accomplishments, and deliver what will be Hubble 2.0, the world&apos;s greatest telescope. It will be amazing. But we have to deliver it.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>Q:</bold></speaker>
<p><bold>The agency has had some time to process the errors that were made in the fiscal planning and management of JWST. What lessons have you learned from it?</bold></p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>J.G.:</bold></speaker>
<p>From a project management standpoint, it&apos;s about communication, communication, communication. All throughout the project, we need our team members to feel comfortable &#x2026; that if they are worried about something, if there&apos;s an issue that can&apos;t be solved easily in the normal process of doing business, elevate it so it can be discussed and solved as soon as possible. Don&apos;t delay things and say, &#x201C;We&apos;ll get to that later.&#x201D; Because that&apos;s what accumulates and drives your budget and schedule.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>Q:</bold></speaker>
<p><bold>Is that what went wrong?</bold></p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>J.G.:</bold></speaker>
<p>It was a combination of things. But the project management&#x2014;I don&apos;t know how deliberate it was&#x2014;ended up in a posture where engineers and technicians were afraid to bring problems forward because they knew that the answer would be &#x201C;We don&apos;t have the funds to solve it. Go away.&#x201D; So a lot of stuff was accumulating that had to be solved but wasn&apos;t budgeted. And because it wasn&apos;t budgeted, it wasn&apos;t scheduled, and because it wasn&apos;t scheduled, it was put off, and by definition it was delayed. &#x2026;</p>
<p>A critical lesson that we have learned is that you have to have clear lines of communication. The full spectrum of team members have to be comfortable raising problems, without any fear.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>Q:</bold></speaker>
<p><bold>Is JWST on track now? Are all the milestones being met?</bold></p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>J.G.:</bold></speaker>
<p>All the milestones are being met, except two that have been rescheduled [but won&apos;t impact the final delivery date].</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>Q:</bold></speaker>
<p><bold>Have you come up with the outlines of a new Mars program? What would it look like?</bold></p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>J.G.:</bold></speaker>
<p>As a result of our withdrawal from the ExoMars mission, we have decided to look forward &#x2026; and ask the question: What would the next generation of Mars programs look like? After the failure of two Mars missions in the late &apos;90s, NASA restructured the whole program, but the emphasis was still the same: Follow the water, look for signs of extant or past life. That has been a very successful strategy. Now, we have an opportunity to try and develop a Mars Exploratory Framework to plan the next several decades. [NASA Administrator Charles] Bolden asked me to lead a team to go do that. I really wanted the team to be a science and exploration team. We are engaging the community; we have a Web site where people can submit ideas. The goal is to come up with an option for a U.S.-led mission that we could fly in 2018 within the budget that we do have for future Mars missions.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>Q:</bold></speaker>
<p><bold>What&apos;s your philosophy on extending current missions beyond their projected lifetime?</bold></p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>J.G.:</bold></speaker>
<p>We are blessed with missions that last much longer than their requirement lifetime. The Hubble Space Telescope is a good example. It&apos;s continuing to return great science. Fermi, Chandra, Spitzer&#x2014;they all are. If the goal is science, which it is, getting science from operating missions is a high priority, because you don&apos;t know what&apos;s going to happen with future missions.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>Q:</bold></speaker>
<p><bold>Five decades from now, will U.S. astronauts still have jobs?</bold></p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker><bold>J.G.:</bold></speaker>
<p>Absolutely, and I think they will be out exploring Mars, probably exploring the moon, building our future in space and inspiring the nation. I see our country as an exploring nation. That&apos;s why we do so well. We are curious, we innovate, we explore, we invent. It should be obvious that I feel this way, but space is a really exciting and intriguing frontier. We are born explorers. That&apos;s part of our ability to generate the tremendous success that we have had on this planet.</p>
</speech>
</body>
</article>