<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>MEDICINE</subject><subject>ASIA/PACIFIC NEWS</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Polio Campaign</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Closing a Deadly Refuge</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>Leslie</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6094</issue>
<fpage>520</fpage>
<lpage>521</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>On 17 July in the town of Gadap in Karachi, Pakistan, two gunmen shot at two men who were participating in a national polio vaccination campaign&#x2014;sadly, a not uncommon occurrence.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>On 17 July in the town of Gadap in Karachi, Pakistan, two gunmen shot at a Ghanaian doctor and his Pakistani driver, who were participating in a national polio vaccination campaign. Three days later, another WHO polio worker was shot and killed outside a Gadap clinic. The attacks, sadly, are not uncommon. Polio workers in Pakistan have received death threats. Two doctors on WHO duty and their driver were killed in a roadside bombing in Afghanistan in September 2008. And just last year 23 people were killed when the jihadist terrorist organization Boko Haram bombed U.N. House in Abuja, Nigeria. The attack in Gadap came just as the town was, for the first time, showing signs of progress in its fight against polio.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>On the morning of 17 July in the town of Gadap in Karachi, Pakistan, two gunmen pulled alongside a white Nissan pickup truck belonging to the World Health Organization (WHO) and opened fire, shooting a Ghanaian doctor in the abdomen; his Pakistani driver suffered a grazing wound on his shoulder. Both men, who were participating in a national polio vaccination campaign, are recovering. As investigations began, WHO suspended its activities in Gadap. Three days later, on 20 July, another WHO polio worker, Muhammad Ishaq, was shot and killed outside a Gadap clinic.</p>
<p>The attacks, sadly, are not uncommon. Polio workers in Pakistan have received death threats. Two doctors on WHO duty and their driver were killed in a roadside bombing in Afghanistan in September 2008. And just last year 23 people, including five WHO and two UNICEF staff members, were killed when the jihadist terrorist organization Boko Haram bombed U.N. House in Abuja, Nigeria. The attack in Gadap came just as the town was, for the first time, showing signs of progress in its fight against polio.</p>
<p>Gadap is a squalid, festering slum that many have long feared would be the undoing of the country's, and the world's, fight to eradicate polio. It is one of just 10 so-called sanctuaries for the poliovirus worldwide&#x2014;places where the virus has been impossible to dislodge.</p>
<p>Gadap, and especially one area known as Union Council 4, has everything working against it, says Chris Maher, who runs country operations from WHO headquarters in Geneva. It is a receiving ground for migrants from across the country, especially those fleeing the violence in the tribal areas and Balochistan. Many are Pashtun, an underserved minority in this part of the country. In Pakistan overall, 8% of the population is Pashto-speaking; in Union Council 4, that number climbs to 73%.</p>
<p>The migrants crowd into multifamily dwellings where they have no basic services such as clean water or sanitation, much less routine childhood immunizations or other medical care. Literacy rates are low. Many Pashtun don't know what polio is or that a vaccine can prevent it. Suspicions run high. The population is understandably skeptical of a government that provides them with nothing and then comes around repeatedly offering drops of polio vaccine, says Tariq Masood of WHO's Karachi office. &#x201C;In their minds, often the government and the U.S. are bombing their children in [the tribal areas], so why is there so much concern for our kids here?&#x201D; he says.</p>
<p>Polio-vaccination campaigns in Gadap have been consistently lousy. The often unpaid vaccinators, whose job is to go house to house and give drops of oral polio vaccine to every child under age 5, have little incentive to work. In March, for instance, the campaign was delayed for 2 days because the vaccinators, unpaid for the past 9 months, went on strike. Some 80% of the teams don't speak Pashto, and child vaccinators are common. It's not surprising that mothers turn away vaccinators who come to their doors, saying their children are asleep, or refuse outright because they have been told that the vaccine is made of monkey kidneys and other nonhalal materials and will make their children weak and sterile. Since 2006, 80% of the polio cases in Gadap have been from Union Council 4. Samples of sewage water in Gadap have consistently tested positive for the virus, indicating rampant circulation.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Casualty.</title>
<p>Muhammad Ishaq, a polio worker in Gadap, Karachi, was shot and killed in July.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_520_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: WHO</attrib>
</fig>
<p>After another disappointing performance during the March vaccination rounds, Elias Durry, who runs the Pakistan program for WHO, and his colleague Salah Tumsah, who runs the Sindh province operation, decided to shake things up. Instead of bringing in vaccinators for a few days during each campaign, the program has hired women from the community to work full-time since April, providing not just polio drops but also other services such as newborn follow-up. &#x201C;It has made a huge, huge difference,&#x201D; Durry says.</p>
<p>Rotary International and the U.N. Children's Fund have also been focusing their efforts there. In April, the two organizations, in collaboration with Coca-Cola, conducted a massive cleanup of Union Council 4, carting out an estimated 160 tons of garbage. It is one of the ways Rotary is trying to &#x201C;give the message that we are there not just for polio but for everything else,&#x201D; says Aziz Memon, national chair for Rotary's PolioPlus program in Pakistan.</p>
<p>Rotary conducted a major survey in Gadap in June. Of 7000 children they checked for the finger marking that indicates they were vaccinated, only four hadn't been&#x2014;and they were quickly vaccinated, too, Memon says.</p>
<p>Most encouraging of all, Durry says, is that for more than 4 months, the environmental samples from Gadap have tested negative, suggesting the virus is in retreat.</p>
<p>WHO's Bruce Aylward, who leads the Global Polio Eradication Initiative from Geneva, says it is unclear whether the two shootings were related and whether they specifically targeted polio workers. Until they get more evidence, he says, &#x201C;Our operating assumption is that [the shootings] may be related, and that affects how we approach security.&#x201D; WHO insists the attacks will not distract from the job of wiping out polio in Pakistan. But the shootings make uncomfortably clear just how much is out of the program's control.</p>
</body>
</article>