<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="book-review" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1225634</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1225634</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Books <italic>et al.</italic></subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>books</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ANTHRO</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Anthropology</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>On Our Biocultural Nature</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>Antoinette</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff id="aff1">The reviewer is at the Department of Human and Organizational Learning, George Washington University, 2134 G Street NW, Washington, DC 20052, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>jenkinsa@gwmail.gwu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6094</issue>
<fpage seq="a">526</fpage>
<lpage>526</lpage>
<product product-type="book"><bold>Race, Monogamy, and Other Lies They Told You</bold> Busting Myths About Human Nature <bold><italic>by Agust&#x00ED;n Fuentes</italic></bold> University of California Press, Berkeley, 2012. 290 pp. $27.50, &#x00A3;19.95. ISBN 9780520269712.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Fuentes dissects various widely held but scientifically unsupported beliefs about human sex, aggression, and race.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Fuentes dissects various widely held but scientifically unsupported beliefs about human sex, aggression, and race.</p></abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Sherman J. Suter</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Barbara Ordway</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><bold>I</bold> do not ask for directions. I yell at football games. I must be a man, right? Wrong. The range of skin colors in my immediate family is so diverse that awestruck onlookers often ask, &#x201C;Are you all together?&#x201D; (To which my husband quips, &#x201C;Are you all together?&#x201D;) Surely people from different populations cannot be a family, right? Wrong. It is not my intent to drive people mad by going against the grain on these and other societal expectations. I am just living my life&#x2014;a life that, according to Agust&#x00ED;n Fuentes, is scrutinized through a lens of normality formed by false assumptions about human nature. That is not to say that I don't conform to or perpetuate such normative standards myself. Sadly, I do. However, after reading the compelling arguments presented by Fuentes in <italic>Race, Monogamy, and Other Lies They Told You</italic>, I will think twice before doing so again.</p>
<p>Fuentes, an anthropologist at the University of Notre Dame, developed the book to debunk myths on race, aggression, and sex &#x201C;because of the way they constrain our thinking about, and being with, each other.&#x201D; From the preface to the appendix, he engages readers in a complex but well-mapped journey that challenges commonly accepted assumptions about the nature of race, aggression, and fundamental differences in the desires and behaviors of men and women. To support his endeavor, Fuentes offers data distilled from his own research and the copious literature on these topics. Readers for whom biology, anthropology, and psychology are not disciplines of practice or interest need not fret. The author masterly conveys his knowledge in an informative way.</p>
<p>In presenting arguments against the myths, Fuentes takes care not to minimize the social importance of these supposed characteristics of human nature. Humans may not fall into biological races, but racist attitudes and behaviors are alive and well. Although men and women may not be so different after all, the definition and perpetuation of normative gender roles remains standard practice. Whereas we may not have a natural propensity toward aggression, we fear others anyway. Such contradictions illustrate Fuentes's point: &#x201C;Being human is messy. We are simultaneously biological and cultural beings with complex schemata and social lives that shape and populate our perceptions and philosophies.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Fuentes suggests that if we are to progress toward understanding what it really means to be human, we need to challenge ourselves to not see only what we already believe. If you are willing to enhance your worldview by sleuthing to discover &#x201C;who we are and why we do what we do,&#x201D; <italic>Race, Monogamy, and Other Lies They Told You</italic> is for you. Whether you agree with Fuentes or not, it will at least engage your critical thinking skills and encourage you to be a more active and discerning consumer of information.</p>
</body>
</article>