<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1220952</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1220952</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Report</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Reports</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>reports</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>MOLEC BIOL</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Function, Targets, and Evolution of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> piRNAs</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bagijn</surname><given-names>Marloes P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1">*</xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>Leonard D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1">*</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn2"><sup>&#x2020;</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sapetschnig</surname><given-names>Alexandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1">*</xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weick</surname><given-names>Eva-Maria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bouasker</surname><given-names>Samir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lehrbach</surname><given-names>Nicolas J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Simard</surname><given-names>Martin J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Miska</surname><given-names>Eric A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x2021;</sup></xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Gurdon Institute and Department of Biochemistry, University of Cambridge, The Henry Wellcome Building of Cancer and Developmental Biology, Tennis Court Road, Cambridge CB2 1QN, UK.</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Laval University Cancer Research Centre, H&#x00F4;tel-Dieu de Qu&#x00E9;bec (CHUQ), Quebec City, Qu&#x00E9;bec G1R 2J6, Canada.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn id="afn1" fn-type="equal"><label>*</label>
<p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn>
<fn id="afn2" fn-type="present-address"><label>&#x2020;</label>
<p>Present address: Department of Bioinformatics and Computational Biology, Genentech Inc., 1 DNA Way, South San Francisco, CA 94080, USA.</p></fn>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x2021;</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:href="e.miska@gurdon.cam.ac.uk">e.miska@gurdon.cam.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>03</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6094</issue>
<fpage>574</fpage>
<lpage>578</lpage>
<history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>02</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>06</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>06</month><year>2012</year></date></history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="editor"><title>Secondary Endogenous Small and Interfering</title><p>In many eukaryotes, Piwi proteins bind small noncoding Piwi-interacting RNAs (piRNAs) that function to silence transposons in the germ line and protect the germ line from transposable element&#x2013;driven recombination and mutation. <bold>Bagijn <italic>et al.</italic></bold> (p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="337" page="574">574</related-article>, published online 14 June; see the Perspective by <bold><related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="337" page="529" issue="6094"><bold>Xiol and Pillai</bold></related-article></bold>) show that in the nematode, <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>, a messenger RNA (mRNA) that contains a piRNA target sequence gives rise to a second, downstream class of small RNAs known as secondary endogenous small interfering RNAs, or endo siRNAs. These endo siRNAs map to the vicinity of the piRNA complementary sequence in the mRNA target and depend on both Piwi and on factors involved in the related RNA interference pathway for their genesis, but not on the Piwi slicer activity. Mapping the endo siRNAs reveals that piRNAs can target imperfectly matched targets and that piRNAs target a subset of both transposons and endogenous genes for silencing.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Piwi-bound piwi-interacting RNAs recruit endogenous small interfering RNAs to silence mobile genetic elements.</p></abstract>
<abstract>
<p>Piwi-interacting RNAs (piRNAs) are small RNAs required to maintain germline integrity and fertility, but their mechanism of action is poorly understood. Here we demonstrate that <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> piRNAs silence transcripts in trans through imperfectly complementary sites. Target silencing is independent of Piwi endonuclease activity or &#x201C;slicing.&#x201D; Instead, piRNAs initiate a localized secondary endogenous small interfering RNA (endo-siRNA) response. Endogenous protein-coding gene and transposon transcripts exhibit Piwi-dependent endo-siRNAs at sites complementary to piRNAs and are derepressed in Piwi mutants. Genomic loci of piRNA biogenesis are depleted of protein-coding genes and tend to overlap the start and end of transposons in sense and antisense, respectively. Our data suggest that nematode piRNA clusters are evolving to generate piRNAs against active mobile elements. Thus, piRNAs provide heritable, sequence-specific triggers for RNA interference in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Guy Riddihough</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Harry Jach</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The Piwi-piRNA pathway has an evolutionarily conserved role in germline transposon silencing in animals. <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> encodes two Piwi family proteins, PRG-1 and PRG-2, although PRG-2 has likely little or no function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). PRG-1 and piRNA expression is restricted to the male and female germ line. The piRNAs of <italic>C. elegans</italic> are 21 nucleotides in length with a 5&#x2032; uracil (21U-RNAs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>). In <italic>C. elegans</italic> piRNAs have a sequence motif, situated ~40 base pairs (bp) upstream of each piRNA locus, that is thought to be required for piRNA biogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). A challenge in the field is to understand the mechanism(s) by which piRNAs act on their targets. Proposed functions for Piwi-piRNA complexes include the RNA interference (RNAi)&#x2013;like slicing of RNA transcripts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>), transcript deadenylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>), and de novo DNA methylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>). Here we identify the targeting mechanism and the endogenous targets of <italic>C. elegans</italic> piRNAs.</p>
<p>We generated <italic>C. elegans</italic> strains carrying green fluorescent protein (GFP)&#x2013;histone H2B fusion transgenes into which we inserted a short sequence complementary to that of an endogenous piRNA (21UR-1) or its reverse complement, hereafter referred to as the piRNA sensor and control sensor, respectively (see fig. S1 and supplementary text) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>). Whereas the control sensor expressed nuclear, chromatin-associated GFP throughout germline development, GFP expression was silenced in animals carrying the piRNA sensor transgene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1, A and B</xref>). piRNA sensor silencing was dependent on <italic>prg-1</italic>. In contrast, <italic>prg-2</italic> did not show an effect (fig. S2 and supplementary text). An independent sensor for the unrelated endogenous piRNA 21UR-1349 confirmed these results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1, C and D</xref>).</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption>
<p>A single antisense piRNA site is sufficient for target silencing in vivo. (<bold>A</bold>) Fluorescence microscopy (GFP-H2B) and differential interference contrast (DIC) images of adult hermaphrodites. Scale bar, 20 &#x03BC;m. (<bold>B</bold>) Flow cytometry analysis of control sensor strain (green) and piRNA sensor strain in wild-type (red) or <italic>prg-1</italic> (<italic>n4357</italic>) mutant background (blue) as in (A). (<bold>C</bold>) Germline GFP-H2B expression of the 21UR-1349 piRNA sensor. (<bold>D</bold>) Flow cytometry analysis of the 21UR-1349 piRNA sensor strain in wild-type (red) and <italic>prg-1</italic> mutant (blue). (<bold>E</bold>) Profiles of small RNA high-throughput sequencing reads with unique match to the sensor relative to the target site (indicated in gray). Colors correspond to 5&#x2032; nucleotides as indicated in the color key in (F). Positive and negative <italic>y</italic> axes correspond to antisense and sense reads, respectively. (<bold>F</bold>) Length and 5&#x2032; nucleotide identity of small RNAs antisense to the piRNA sensor in wild type. (<bold>G</bold>) Northern blot of total RNA. Probes were against piRNA 21UR-1, a piRNA sensor-specific 22G-RNA, and the PRG-1&#x2013;independent endo-siRNA siR26-263. (<bold>H</bold>) Quantitative reverse transcription (qRT)&#x2013;PCR of primary piRNA sensor transcript and mRNA. Data were normalized to wild-type transcript levels. Error bars are SEMs.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_574_F1"></graphic></fig>
<p>We analyzed small RNA populations in the sensor strains by high-throughput sequencing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>). We detected a set of small RNAs that map unambiguously to the piRNA sensor mRNA in antisense orientation, mostly within ~20 bp of the piRNA target site. These small RNAs were predominantly 22 nucleotides in length with a 5&#x2032; guanosine, characteristic features of secondary endo-siRNAs, also referred to as 22G-RNAs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref>). 22G-RNAs represent the most abundant class of endogenous small RNAs in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, are RNA-dependent RNA polymerase products, and have a 5&#x2032; triphosphate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>). The set of 22G-RNAs that map in close proximity to the piRNA target site was dependent on <italic>prg-1</italic> and absent in the control sensor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>). We validated the high-throughput sequencing data using Northern blotting for an abundant 22G-RNA mapping to the piRNA sensor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1G</xref>). As endo-siRNA silencing can involve posttranscriptional regulation of mRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>) or cotranscriptional gene regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16"><italic>16</italic></xref>), we tested whether the piRNA sensor was regulated at either level. We find that both primary transcript and mRNA are up-regulated in <italic>prg-1</italic> mutants, consistent with cotranscriptional or a combination of post- and cotranscriptional regulation of the piRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1H</xref>).</p>
<p>To investigate the role of endo-siRNAs in piRNA-mediated gene silencing, we screened a set of 24 siRNA pathway genes. Mutants were crossed into the piRNA sensor and assayed for transgene GFP expression through fluorescent microscopy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref> and fig. S3, A and B), flow cytometry (fig. S3, C and D), Northern blotting (fig. S4), or high-throughput sequencing (fig. S5). We found that a specific subset of siRNA pathway genes is required for piRNA-mediated silencing and encodes pathway components, including three putative helicases (MUT-7, DRH-3, MUT-14), two RNA-dependent RNA polymerases (EGO-1 and RRF-1), the enzymes that generate secondary siRNAs, and several &#x201C;worm&#x201D;-specific Argonaute proteins (WAGOs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17"><italic>17</italic></xref>) (fig. S6, A and B). Although several strains with mutations in multiple WAGOs are defective in piRNA sensor silencing, <italic>hrde-1/wago-9</italic> is the only single-mutant WAGO strain defective in piRNA sensor silencing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref> and fig. S3). PRG-1 is necessary for both piRNA expression and sensor-specific 22G-RNA expression. In contrast, the identified siRNA pathway genes act downstream of piRNA expression and are required only for the expression of piRNA sensor-derived 22G-RNAs (figs. S4 and S5). We conclude that a specific endo-siRNA pathway acts as a downstream effector of the piRNA pathway.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption>
<p>A specific endo-siRNA pathway acts downstream of and is required for piRNA-mediated silencing. (<bold>A</bold>) piRNA sensor expression in siRNA pathway mutants as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) A second 21UR-1 piRNA sensor strain (cherrysensor) expressing mCherry-H2B in <italic>prg-1 (n4357)</italic>.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_574_F2"></graphic></fig>
<p>The Ping-Pong piRNA amplification loop in insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18"><italic>18</italic></xref>) and vertebrates requires endonuclease or slicing activity for biogenesis of at least a subset of piRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19"><italic>19</italic></xref>). PRG-1 contains an evolutionarily conserved DDH motif (catalytic triad) that confers endonuclease or slicing activity to some Argonaute superfamily proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20"><italic>20</italic></xref>), and recombinant PRG-1 appears to have some slicing activity in vitro (figs. S7 and S8 and supplementary text). To test the requirement for PRG-1 catalytic activity in vivo, we generated two transgenes expressing wild-type GFP&#x2013;PRG-1 or GFP&#x2013;PRG-1 DAH mutant fusion proteins (fig. S9). In <italic>prg-1</italic> mutants, both wild-type and DAH mutant GFP&#x2013;PRG-1 were sufficient to rescue piRNA expression (fig. S4). To address whether the catalytic triad of PRG-1 is required for piRNA-mediated silencing of targets, we generated a second 21UR-1 piRNA sensor strain (cherrysensor) expressing mCherry-H2B. Although the cherrysensor was desilenced in a <italic>prg-1</italic> mutant background, both wild-type GFP&#x2013;PRG-1 and GFP&#x2013;PRG-1 DAH restored silencing of the cherrysensor to the same extent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). This was also true in the <italic>prg-1;prg-2</italic> double mutants (fig. S10). In addition, both wild-type and DAH mutant GFP&#x2013;PRG-1 rescued the fertility defects of <italic>prg-1</italic> mutants (fig. S11). Finally, we generated a panel of mutated piRNA sensors and find that two mismatches are tolerated throughout the target sequence for PRG-1&#x2013;dependent sensor silencing, including mismatches at positions 10 and 11 that are required for slicing (fig. S12). We conclude that PRG-1 slicing is not required in vivo.</p>
<p>To investigate whether piRNAs target endogenous transcripts, we considered piRNA matches in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> genome, allowing for up to three mismatches. For 16,003 piRNAs, we identified a total of 681,746 sites (additional data tables S1 and S2). We found that PRG-1&#x2013;dependent 22G-RNAs localize in close proximity to imperfect piRNA matches, recapitulating our observations for the piRNA sensor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref> and fig. S13). To assess how many of these represent functional target sites, we compared genomic matches of piRNAs to those of matched control sequences. In wild-type animals, approximately 4.2, 2.6, 2.0, and 1.7% of the 0, 1, 2, and 3 mismatch sites exhibit unambiguously mapping 22G-RNAs, corresponding to an enrichment of 1.6, 1.4, 1.5, and 1.2 compared to control sites, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). In <italic>prg-1</italic> mutants, the percentage of genomic piRNA matches with 22G-RNAs was comparable to that of control sites. The distribution of piRNA matches (and those with 22G-RNAs) across the genome resembled that of controls, except for an enrichment of perfect piRNA matches in the two piRNA clusters on chromosome IV (figs. S14 and S15).</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption>
<p>piRNAs initiate a localized secondary siRNA response against endogenous transcripts. (<bold>A</bold>) Average profiles of collapsed small RNAs mapping uniquely to imperfect genomic piRNA matches (one to three mismatches) in wild-type (left) and <italic>prg-1</italic> mutant (right). Top and bottom panels to the right of each profile illustrate characteristics of antisense and sense small RNAs, respectively. (<bold>B</bold>) Number of genomic piRNA matches (left) and percentage of matches with uniquely mapping 22G-RNAs in wild type (middle) and <italic>prg-1</italic> (right). Black and white bars correspond to piRNAs and matched controls, respectively. Bars for control sequences indicate medians, error bars the range of values obtained for 20 cohorts of control sequences. Numbers above bars indicate the fold-difference between piRNAs and controls. (<bold>C</bold>) Difference in 22G-RNAs mapping uniquely within 20 bp of genomic piRNA matches between <italic>prg-1</italic> and wild type. Shown are boxplots of the difference in 22G-RNA reads after square root transformation (box indicates interquartile range, plot extends from 5th to 95th percentile). Asterisks indicate statistical significance (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, two-sided Wilcoxon rank-sum test). (<bold>D</bold>) As in (C) with genomic piRNA matches grouped according to motif score of complementary piRNA (as proxy for abundance).</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_574_F3"></graphic></fig>
<p>To further investigate mismatch tolerance of piRNA targeting, we considered genomic piRNA matches with up to five mismatches. We observed that levels of PRG-1&#x2013;dependent 22G-RNAs decreased with an increasing number of mismatches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). Levels of PRG-1&#x2013;dependent 22G-RNAs were greater at sites with four compared to five mismatches, suggesting that in some cases, sites with up to four mismatches can be sufficient for the synthesis of 22G-RNAs. We also observed that levels of 22G-RNAs depend on piRNA abundance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>).</p>
<p>We identified candidate endogenous targets by searching for antisense piRNA matches in annotated protein-coding genes, pseudogenes, and transposons, allowing for up to three mismatches (additional data tables S3 to S5). We found that in <italic>prg-1</italic> mutant animals, 22G-RNAs antisense to candidate targets showed a stronger reduction at target sites (within 20 nucleotides) compared to regions distant from target sites (fig. S16). Microarray analysis showed that mRNA expression differences between <italic>prg-1; prg-2</italic> mutant and wild-type animals were more strongly correlated with changes in 22G-RNAs at target sites compared to the whole transcript (fig. S16).</p>
<p>We ranked transposons and protein-coding genes by the decrease in target-site&#x2013;associated 22G-RNA density in <italic>prg-1</italic> mutant compared to wild-type animals and examined individual candidate targets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4, A and B</xref>). Transposase mRNA from Tc3 is desilenced in <italic>prg-1</italic> mutants, and Tc3 exhibits PRG-1&#x2013;dependent 22G-RNAs against its terminal inverted repeats (TIRs) but no matching piRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). We identified three piRNAs with imperfect complementarity to the consensus sequence of Tc3, all of which map to the TIRs, suggesting that these piRNAs target Tc3 elements in trans. We chose five transposable elements (CEREP1A, MARINCE1, TURMOIL1, Chapaev-2_CE, and LINE2H_CE) and six protein-coding genes (<italic>bath-45</italic>, <italic>zfp-1</italic>, C18H2.2, <italic>nfm-1</italic>, Y75B8A.19, and <italic>pan-1</italic>) with a strong reduction in target-site&#x2013;associated 22G-RNAs for analysis by quantitative reverse transcription&#x2013;polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4, C to E</xref>). Six of these candidates showed statistically significant increased expression in <italic>prg-1</italic> mutants (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test). We tested the requirement of an intact catalytic triad and found that both wild-type and DAH mutant GFP&#x2013;PRG-1 restored silencing of <italic>zfp-1</italic> (F54F2.2b) in <italic>prg-1</italic> mutants, whereas an independent isoform lacking target-site&#x2013;associated 22G-RNAs (F54F2.2a) showed no change in expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4E</xref>). In addition, expression of a PRG-1&#x2013;dependent 22G-RNA against <italic>zfp-1</italic> (F54F2.2b) was restored by both wild-type and DAH mutant GFP&#x2013;PRG-1 (fig. S4). Thus, piRNAs target endogenous transcripts in trans for silencing, independently of slicing activity.</p>
<fig id="F4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption>
<p>Endogenous piRNA targets and piRNA evolution. (<bold>A</bold>) Candidate transposon targets ranked by change in 22G-RNA density at target sites between <italic>prg-1</italic> and wild type. Transposons selected for qRT-PCR validation are in red. Antisense 22G-RNA profiles are shown for selected elements with target sites indicated above each profile as explained in the color key. (<bold>B</bold>) Candidate protein-coding targets as in (A). (<bold>C</bold>) qRT-PCR analysis of candidate transposon targets with fold-changes normalized to actin. Error bars are SEMs, asterisks denote <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 (two-sided <italic>t</italic> test). (<bold>D</bold>) qRT-PCR analysis of candidate protein-coding targets. (<bold>E</bold>) qRT-PCR analysis of targeted (F54F2.2b) and nontargeted (F54F2.2a) transcripts from the <italic>zfp-1</italic> locus. Data were normalized to wild type. (<bold>F</bold>) Enrichment and depletion of genomic piRNA matches overlapping features of interest. Red and blue indicate increased or reduced number of matches for piRNAs compared to control sequences, respectively. Asterisks indicate statistical significance (adjusted empirical <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Start and end refer to the first and last 50 bp of the annotated feature, respectively. Pseudogene annotation was only available for <italic>C. elegans.</italic> (<bold>G</bold>) piRNA matches against start (left) and end (right) of DNA transposons. Profiles indicate the number of transposon subfamilies with a perfect piRNA match in at least one full-length genomic copy. Positive (blue) and negative (red) <italic>y</italic> axes correspond to sense and antisense matches, respectively. Dashed lines correspond to maximal allowed distance between an upstream sequence motif and piRNA 3&#x2032; end.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_574_F4"></graphic></fig>
<p>Our findings raise the question of how piRNAs and target sites arise during evolution. The majority of the 16,003 <italic>C. elegans</italic> piRNAs (96%) map to unique locations in the genome and are depleted of protein-coding genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). We confirmed that piRNA loci are depleted of protein-coding genes in both <italic>C. elegans</italic> and the related nematode species <italic>C. briggsae</italic> when compared to loci of matched control sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4F</xref>). However, we did not observe a depletion of pseudogenes or transposons. piRNA loci showed a trend for depletion at the start and end of full-length DNA transposons in antisense and sense, respectively, and an inverse trend for enrichment at the start and end in sense and antisense, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4F</xref>). This signature suggests recent DNA transposon integrations downstream of instances of the sequence motif thought to be required for piRNA biogenesis. Such integrations may result in the birth of a piRNA either sense to the 5&#x2032; end or antisense to the 3&#x2032; end of the transposon. In the latter case, the new piRNA has the potential to target and silence the mobile element. Indeed, the observed distances between piRNA locus and start or end of the transposon are consistent with transposon insertions downstream of existing sequence motifs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4G</xref> and fig. S17). A similar signature was observed in <italic>C. briggsae</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4G</xref> and fig. S18) even though neither piRNAs nor transposable elements are conserved between the two species. When considering imperfect piRNA matches, we observed a depletion antisense to protein-coding genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4F</xref> and fig. S19), suggesting that mRNA targeting is often detrimental and piRNAs and sites with potential for mRNA silencing undergo negative selection.</p>
<p>Our data demonstrate that <italic>C. elegans</italic> piRNAs silence endogenous transcripts by triggering a secondary siRNA response (fig. S20). Although we find that individual mRNAs are piRNA targets, the physiological roles of piRNA-mediated gene regulation remain to be explored. RNA interference pathways can silence repetitive elements regardless of their sequence content but rely on the formation of double-stranded RNA. The piRNA pathway may provide an alternative defense mechanism that is heritable and sequence-specific based on the evolution of new piRNAs against active mobile elements. Secondary siRNA amplification ensures effective silencing of abundant targets, resembling the Ping-Pong piRNA amplification cycle in other species.</p>
</body>
<back><app-group><app>
<title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/science.1220952/DC1">www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/science.1220952/DC1</ext-link></p>
<p>Materials and Methods</p>
<p>Supplementary Text</p>
<p>Figs. S1 to S21</p>
<p>Tables S1 to S3</p>
<p>References (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21"><italic>21</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30"><italic>30</italic></xref>)</p>
<p>Additional Data Tables S1 to S5</p></supplementary-material></app></app-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>P. P.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Piwi and piRNAs act upstream of an endogenous siRNA pathway to suppress Tc3 transposon mobility in the Caenorhabditis elegans germline</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source> 
<volume>31</volume>, 
<fpage>79</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2008.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18571451</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Batista</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>PRG-1 and 21U-RNAs interact to form the piRNA complex required for fertility in C. elegans</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source> 
<volume>31</volume>, 
<fpage>67</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2008.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18571452</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruby</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Large-scale sequencing reveals 21U-RNAs and additional microRNAs and endogenous siRNAs in C. elegans</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> 
<volume>127</volume>, 
<fpage>1193</fpage> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2006.10.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17174894</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinke</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A C. elegans Piwi, PRG-1, regulates 21U-RNAs during spermatogenesis</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source> 
<volume>18</volume>, 
<fpage>861</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2008.05.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18501605</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brennecke</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Discrete small RNA-generating loci as master regulators of transposon activity in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> 
<volume>128</volume>, 
<fpage>1089</fpage> (<year>2007</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2007.01.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17346786</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunawardane</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>A slicer-mediated mechanism for repeat-associated siRNA 5&#x2032; end formation in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>315</volume>, 
<fpage>1587</fpage> (<year>2007</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1140494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17322028</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Miwi catalysis is required for piRNA amplification-independent LINE1 transposon silencing</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>480</volume>, 
<fpage>264</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22121019</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rouget</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Maternal mRNA deadenylation and decay by the piRNA pathway in the early Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>467</volume>, 
<fpage>1128</fpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20953170</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aravin</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>A piRNA pathway primed by individual transposons is linked to de novo DNA methylation in mice</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source> 
<volume>31</volume>, 
<fpage>785</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2008.09.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18922463</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuramochi-Miyagawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>DNA methylation of retrotransposon genes is regulated by Piwi family members MILI and MIWI2 in murine fetal testes</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source> 
<volume>22</volume>, 
<fpage>908</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1640708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18381894</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R11"><note><label>11</label>
<p>Materials and methods are available as supplementary materials on <italic>Science</italic> Online.</p></note></ref>
<ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Distinct argonaute-mediated 22G-RNA pathways direct genome surveillance in the C. elegans germline</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source> 
<volume>36</volume>, 
<fpage>231</fpage> (<year>2009</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2009.09.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19800275</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fire</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Distinct populations of primary and secondary effectors during RNAi in C. elegans</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>315</volume>, 
<fpage>241</fpage> (<year>2007</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1132839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17124291</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sijen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thijssen</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plasterk</surname><given-names>R. H. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Secondary siRNAs result from unprimed RNA synthesis and form a distinct class</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>315</volume>, 
<fpage>244</fpage> (<year>2007</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1136699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17158288</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fire</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Potent and specific genetic interference by double-stranded RNA in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>391</volume>, 
<fpage>806</fpage> (<year>1998</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9486653</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Small regulatory RNAs inhibit RNA polymerase II during the elongation phase of transcription</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>465</volume>, 
<fpage>1097</fpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20543824</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yigit</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Analysis of the C. elegans Argonaute family reveals that distinct Argonautes act sequentially during RNAi</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> 
<volume>127</volume>, 
<fpage>747</fpage> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2006.09.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17110334</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>A regulatory circuit for piwi by the large Maf gene traffic jam in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>461</volume>, 
<fpage>1296</fpage> (<year>2009</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19812547</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Fazio</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>The endonuclease activity of Mili fuels piRNA amplification that silences LINE1 elements</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>480</volume>, 
<fpage>259</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22020280</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshua-Tor</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Crystal structure of Argonaute and its implications for RISC slicer activity</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>305</volume>, 
<fpage>1434</fpage> (<year>2004</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1102514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15284453</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="book">W. Wood, <italic>The Nematode Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> (Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, 1988).</citation></ref>
<ref id="R22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fr&#x00F8;kj</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>&#x00E6;<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>r-Jensen</surname></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Single-copy insertion of transgenes in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet.</source> 
<volume>40</volume>, 
<fpage>1375</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18953339</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fr&#x00F8;kj&#x00E6;r-Jensen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ailion</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Improved Mos1-mediated transgenesis in C. elegans</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source> 
<volume>9</volume>, 
<fpage>117</fpage> (<year>2012</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22290181</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horvitz</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulston</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Isolation and genetic characterization of cell-lineage mutants of the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> 
<volume>96</volume>, 
<fpage>435</fpage> (<year>1980</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7262539</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pall</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Improved northern blot method for enhanced detection of small RNA</article-title>. <source>Nat. Protoc.</source> 
<volume>3</volume>, 
<fpage>1077</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2008.67</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18536652</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamore</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>In vitro analysis of RNA interference in Drosophila melanogaster</article-title>. <source>Methods</source> 
<volume>30</volume>, 
<fpage>330</fpage> (<year>2003</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1046-2023(03)00052-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12828947</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsukumo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagami</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siomi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siomi</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Slicer function of Drosophila Argonautes and its involvement in RISC formation</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source> 
<volume>19</volume>, 
<fpage>2837</fpage> (<year>2005</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1370605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16287716</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source> 
<volume>10</volume>, 
<fpage>R25</fpage> (<year>2009</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2009-10-3-r25</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19261174</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source> 
<volume>11</volume>, 
<fpage>R106</fpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979621</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Bioconductor: open software development for computational biology and bioinformatics</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source> 
<volume>5</volume>, 
<fpage>R80</fpage> (<year>2004</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2004-5-10-r80</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15461798</pub-id></citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We are grateful to J. Ahringer and E. Jorgensen for providing reagents. A.S. was supported by the Human Frontier Science Program and the Herchel-Smith Fund. N.J.L. was supported by a Ph.D. studentship from the Wellcome Trust (UK). E.-M.W. was supported by a Ph.D. studentship from the Herchel-Smith Fund. S.B. and M.J.S. were funded by the Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR). M.J.S. is a New Investigator from CIHR. This work was supported by Cancer Research UK and the Wellcome Trust. Small RNA sequence data and Affymetrix gene expression data were submitted to the Gene Expression Omnibus under accession no. GSE37433. Detailed methods can be found in the supplementary materials.</p>
</ack></back>
</article>