<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>MEDICINE</subject><subject>CELL BIOL</subject><subject>ECOLOGY</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Around the World</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6094</issue>
<fpage seq="b">506</fpage>
<lpage>507</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>In science news around the world this week, a dengue vaccine shows promise, a U.S. court says stem cells are drugs, a fracking report is under scrutiny, Germany's National Academy of Sciences Leopoldina has come down firmly against the use of crops for energy, and a Senate panel last week approved a bill that would ban invasive research on great apes in the United States.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>In science news around the world this week, a dengue vaccine shows promise, a U.S. court says stem cells are drugs, a fracking report is under scrutiny, Germany's National Academy of Sciences Leopoldina has come down firmly against the use of crops for energy, and a Senate panel last week approved a bill that would ban invasive research on great apes in the United States.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_506b_F1"></graphic>
</fig>
<boxed-text content-type="story_index">
<def-list>
<def-item><term>1 - Ratchaburi Province, Thailand</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec1">Dengue Vaccine Shows Promise</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>2 - Washington, D.C.</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2">U.S. Court Says Stem Cells Are Drugs</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>3 - Washington, D.C.</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3">Fracking Report Under Scrutiny</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>4 - Halle, Germany</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec4">Poor Review for Biofuels</xref></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>5 - Washington, D.C.</term><def><p><xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec5">Ape Research Ban Moves Forward in Senate</xref></p></def></def-item>
</def-list>
</boxed-text>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec1">
<title>Ratchaburi Province, Thailand</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Dengue Vaccine Shows Promise</title>
<p>A vaccine against dengue&#x2014;a debilitating and sometimes fatal viral disease that&apos;s widespread in the world&apos;s tropical regions&#x2014;has shown promise in its first phase III trial, although it hasn&apos;t entirely fulfilled the hopes of its producer, French vaccine manufacturer Sanofi. In a trial among 4002 children aged 4 to 11 years in Ratchaburi Province in Thailand, the vaccine proved safe and effective against three of the four circulating dengue strains, the company said in a press release on 25 July. The vaccine was designed to protect against all four strains, which dengue experts say is the ideal.</p>
<p>Sanofi declined to issue details of the study; they will be submitted for publication soon, a spokesperson says. A vaccine that protects against only three strains &#x201C;might slow down licensure a bit,&#x201D; says Duane Gubler, a dengue expert at the Duke University&#x2013;National University of Singapore Graduate Medical School Singapore, but would still &#x201C;be very important from a public health point of view.&#x201D; Because of cross-protection from the other strains, vaccinated people would be unlikely to develop the most severe&#x2014;and often fatal form&#x2014;of the disease, called dengue hemorrhagic fever, Gubler says. At least five other dengue vaccines are in clinical trials.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Spray-off.</title>
<p>A Thai Disease Control officer sprays a chemical to kill dengue-spreading mosquitoes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_506b_F2"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: PORNCHAI KITTIWONGSAKUL/AFP/GETTY IMAGES</attrib>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec2">
<title>Washington, D.C.</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>U.S. Court Says Stem Cells Are Drugs</title>
<p>A U.S. federal court has found that a stem cell therapy offered by a Colorado clinic is a regulated drug. The ruling could spur a U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) crackdown on other clinics offering untested adult stem cell treatments.</p>
<p>Regenerative Sciences Inc. in Broomfield, Colorado, uses stem cells extracted from a patient&apos;s own bone marrow to treat bone and joint injuries. The company calls its treatment a medical procedure. But in a 2010 suit, FDA argued that because the stem cells are more than &#x201C;minimally manipulated&#x201D; and the procedure uses reagents that cross state lines, the cells are an FDA-regulated biological drug. On 23 July, the U.S. District Court for the District of Columbia in Washington, D.C., granted FDA an injunction, agreeing that &#x201C;the cultured cell product is a drug&#x201D; according to federal law.</p>
<p>University of Minnesota bioethicist Leigh Turner says the ruling &#x201C;is particularly important given &#x2026; the proliferation of [U.S.] clinics marketing stem cell procedures,&#x201D; many of which &#x201C;appear to be pushing stem cell quackery.&#x201D; Regenerative Sciences plans to appeal.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec3">
<title>Washington, D.C.</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Fracking Report Under Scrutiny</title>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<caption>
<p>Groat</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_506b_F3"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: &#x00A9; LES STONE/CORBIS; (INSET) USGS</attrib>
</fig>
<p>A controversial study of hydraulic fracking released in February will be reviewed by an independent panel of experts. The study was criticized last week when an advocacy group highlighted the financial ties of geologist Charles &#x201C;Chip&#x201D; Groat, the lead author of the study, to an energy company.</p>
<p>The report analyzed the risks and benefits of hydraulic fracturing, or fracking, a type of drilling used to extract natural gas from shale. It found that fracking hasn&apos;t contaminated ground water.</p>
<p>But Groat, former head of the U.S. Geological Survey and now associate director of the Energy Institute at the University of Texas, Austin, didn&apos;t disclose a potential conflict of interest: He serves on the board of Plains Exploration &amp; Production Co., which conducts fracking in the United States.</p>
<p>Groat says he thought his board membership wasn&apos;t relevant to the project and he didn&apos;t have an actual conflict of interest. In a statement released on 24 July, Steven Leslie, provost and executive vice president of the University of Texas, Austin, said he hoped to have the independent review of the study completed in a few weeks. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scim.ag/Groatfrack"><bold>http://scim.ag/Groatfrack</bold></ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec4">
<title>Halle, Germany</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Poor Review for Biofuels</title>
<p>Germany&apos;s National Academy of Sciences Leopoldina has come down firmly against the use of crops for energy. In a report issued on 26 July from a panel of more than 20 experts who have been working together since 2010, the academy concludes that biofuels should play only a small part in the move toward sustainable sources of energy.</p>
<p>Biofuels use more land area, generate more greenhouse gas emissions, and have a greater impact on the environment than other alternative energy sources such as photovoltaic solar energy, solar thermal energy, or wind power. Biofuel crops may also find themselves competing with food crops for valuable land.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="story_container" id="sec5">
<title>Washington, D.C.</title>
<sec sec-type="story">
<title>Ape Research Ban Moves Forward in Senate</title>
<p>A Senate panel last week approved a bill that would ban invasive research on great apes in the United States. The Great Ape Protection and Cost Savings Act of 2011, sponsored by Senator Maria Cantwell (D&#x2013;WA), would ban research that may kill, injure, or cause fear, pain, distress, or trauma to a great ape&#x2014;defined as a chimpanzee, bonobo, gorilla, orangutan, or gibbon. It would also require that the more than 900 chimpanzees now being used in invasive research in the United States be retired. An amendment adopted during markup by the Senate Committee on Environment and Public Works would set up a federal task force to approve exemptions after consulting with the public.</p>
<p>Research advocacy groups say the bill conflicts with a 2011 Institute of Medicine report recommending that chimp research continue under specific circumstances. The Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology protested that the bill would make it difficult to start a research program quickly to study an emerging disease. A House of Representatives version of the bill is awaiting action by the House Energy and Commerce Committee health subcommittee; some onlookers say a final bill is unlikely to be approved by the full House and Senate this year.</p>
<fig id="F4" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_506b_F4"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ISTOCKPHOTO.COM">ISTOCKPHOTO.COM</ext-link></attrib>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
</article>