<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id><journal-title>Science</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News of the Week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-week</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI COMMUN</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Random Sample</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date><volume>337</volume><issue>6094</issue><fpage seq="a">507</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>The world's largest telescope to observe the highest energy photons from space saw its first light in Namibia last week. An orchid called <italic>Acampe rigida </italic>seems to be the first discovered that depends on rain to pollinate its flowers. And this week's numbers quantify HIV-infected U.S. men who have sex with men, low-income countries that will become middle-income by 2020, and the speed of cheetahs and ducks.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>The world's largest telescope to observe the highest energy photons from space saw its first light in Namibia last week. An orchid called <italic>Acampe rigida </italic>seems to be the first discovered that depends on rain to pollinate its flowers. And this week's numbers quantify HIV-infected U.S. men who have sex with men, low-income countries that will become middle-income by 2020, and the speed of cheetahs and ducks.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec>
<title>First Light for HESS II</title>
<fig id="F1" position="float"><graphic xlink:href="337_507a_F1"/>
<attrib>CREDIT: H.E.S.S. COLLABORATION, STEFAN SCHWARZBURG</attrib>
</fig>
<p>The world&apos;s largest telescope to observe the highest energy photons from space saw its first light in Namibia last week. Paradoxically, the HESS II telescope&#x2014;with a dish the size of two tennis courts&#x2014;does not direct its gaze out into space, but inside Earth&apos;s atmosphere.</p>
<p>High-energy gamma rays are immune to conventional optics and don&apos;t penetrate the atmosphere. So HESS II looks out for flashes of blue light, known as Cherenkov radiation, emitted by the cascade of particles that ensue when a gamma ray hits the upper atmosphere. Its ultrafast snapshots can tell astronomers the incoming particle&apos;s energy and direction. HESS II &#x201C;resolves the cascade images at unprecedented detail, with four times more pixels per sky area compared to the smaller telescopes,&#x201D; says Pascal Vincent of France&apos;s National Institute for Nuclear and Particle Physics.</p>
<p>Astrophysicists think the gamma rays come from cosmic particle accelerators such as supermassive black holes, supernovae, and pulsars. HESS II, an addition to the four smaller dishes of HESS I that have operated at the site since 2004 (<italic>Science</italic>, 3 September 2004, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-publication" vol="305" page="1393" issue="5689">1393</related-article>), will give them unrivaled information about such objects.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Raindrops Keep Falling on My &#x2026;</title>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><graphic xlink:href="337_507a_F2"/>
<attrib>CREDIT: JIANG-YUN GAO</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Birds do it. Bees do it. Even raindrops do it&#x2014;pollinate flowers, that is. In China, researchers were puzzled by the high reproductive rates of an orchid called <italic>Acampe rigida</italic>. As flowers go, <italic>A. rigida</italic> doesn&apos;t have much going for it: It has an attractive odor but offers no nectar reward to would-be pollinators, and such &#x201C;deceptive&#x201D; species tend to produce few fruits. Furthermore, it flowers during the rainy season, when visits by insects tend be rare. Nor do its flowers seem designed for self-pollination. So plant reproductive biologist Jiang-Yun Gao from the Chinese Academy of Sciences Xishuangbanna Tropical Botanical Garden and his colleagues spent 4 years studying this orchid in the wild and in the lab.</p>
<p>The researchers filmed the flowers during a rain shower (as well as under an actual showerhead), and discovered a curious effect: When rain splashes on the orchid&apos;s male sexual organs, it flicks a tethered, pollen-laden bundle upward. As the bundle bounces back on the tether, it lands exactly where it needs to be to pollinate the flower. Plants shielded from rain, on the other hand, produce no fruit, Gao&apos;s team reports this week in <italic>Annals of Botany</italic>.</p>
<p>A few other plants can be pollinated in the rain, but <italic>A. rigida</italic> seems to be the first discovered that really depends on rain to do this job. &#x201C;I think it is likely to make plant reproductive biologists appreciate that rain is not always detrimental for flowers, causing damage, but in some cases can actually aid in promoting reproductive success,&#x201D; says co-author Spencer Barrett, a botanist at the University of Toronto, St. George, in Canada.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>By the Numbers</title>
<p><bold>15.4</bold> Percentage of men who have sex with men in the United States who are infected with HIV, according to a study published online 20 July in <italic>The Lancet</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>53</bold> Number of low-income countries that are projected to move to middle-income status by 2020, according to Bernhard Schwartl&#x00E4;nder, director for evidence, strategy, and results at UNAIDS.</p>
<p><bold>104</bold> Kilometers per hour that a cheetah can run, or a duck can fly&#x2014;still almost twice as fast as even the fastest Olympic athlete can run, notes a study published 28 July in <italic>Veterinary Record</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Science Live</title>
<p><italic>Science</italic>LIVE is on hiatus. We will return at 3 p.m. EDT on Thursday, 6 September, with a chat on <bold>head trauma in soldiers</bold>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>
