<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id><journal-title>Science</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>MEDICINE</subject><subject>ASIA/PACIFIC NEWS</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Polio Campaign</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Polio Emergency</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>Leslie</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date><volume>337</volume><issue>6094</issue><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Can a tough new taskmaster and ramped-up program finally push the global eradication initiative over the finish line?</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>In an October 2011 report, the Independent Monitoring Board (IMB), an oversight body for the Global Polio Eradication Initiative, said that GPEI may never eradicate polio without fundamental changes in a culture and management style the board characterized as insular, stuck in old habits, averse to criticism, and resistant to innovation. The report jolted a program that for 2 decades has struggled to rid the world of poliovirus. Most agree that the report was instrumental in reinvigorating a program that was years behind schedule and billions of dollars over budget. In June 2012, with polio cases at an all-time low, IMB said &#x22;the Programme has broken free of its decade-long stagnation.&#x22; But, the board warned, these gains were fragile, and failure was still possible.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>The last child.</title>
<p>Rukshar Khatoon was the last child to contract polio in India, in January 2011.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_514_F1" />
<attrib>CREDIT: UNICEF/ROD CURTIS; SOURCE: IMB</attrib>
</fig>
<p>&#x201C;We are convinced that polio can&#x2014;and must&#x2014;be eradicated. We are equally convinced that it will not be eradicated on the current trajectory.&#x201D; So declared the Independent Monitoring Board (IMB), an oversight body recently constituted to ride herd on the Global Polio Eradication Initiative (GPEI), in a pivotal October 2011 report with blunt language that broke the mold of bland bureaucratic white papers. Using words such as &#x201C;dysfunctional&#x201D; and &#x201C;diseased,&#x201D; the report said that GPEI&#x2014;the biggest, most expensive, and longest running public health program in history&#x2014;may never eradicate polio without fundamental changes in a culture and management style the board generally characterized as insular, stuck in old habits, averse to criticism, and resistant to innovation.</p>
<p>The eight-member IMB did have some kind words, noting the program's early success in knocking down cases by 99%, its increasing agility in stamping out new outbreaks, and its decisive progress in India&#x2014;that country, long considered the hardest of the hardest places, would soon go 1 year without a case, erasing any lingering doubts that polio eradication was feasible. Overall, the board said, the program is good and its staff members dedicated. But &#x201C;good&#x201D; was not enough to pull off what has been done only once before in human history&#x2014;the eradication of a human disease, smallpox, in 1979. For that, GPEI had to be &#x201C;great,&#x201D; and the initiative was falling considerably short, IMB said. As it starkly warned in its next report: &#x201C;[GPEI] will succeed spectacularly, or fail monumentally.&#x201D;</p>
    <p>The report jolted a program that for 2 decades has struggled to rid the world of the crippling poliovirus&#x2014;a task that proved far more difficult than anyone ever anticipated but was now tantalizingly close. GPEI had weathered plenty of criticism, but no one had challenged program leadership like this and questioned its fundamental ethos (<italic>Science</italic>, 12 May 2006, p. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/312/5775/832.full">832</ext-link>).</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><graphic xlink:href="337_514_F2" />
<attrib>CREDIT: UNICEF/ROD CURTIS; SOURCE: IMB</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Some in the global program&#x2014;a partnership of the World Health Organization (WHO), Rotary International, the U.N. Children's Fund (UNICEF), the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), and most recently, the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation&#x2014;embraced the report, calling it refreshingly frank. Others say it felt like a punch in the gut, sapping the morale of some and offending others. It was especially tough for the staff members on the front lines, who had been working for years in the roughest spots on earth, such as Afghanistan, Somalia, and the Democratic Republic of the Congo, to be told their efforts weren't up to snuff, says Chris Maher, an Australian epidemiologist who oversees all the troops on the ground and easily matches IMB in bluntness. However valid IMB's criticisms, he says, &#x201C;My guys are pretty damn good.&#x201D;</p>
<p>But most agree that the report was instrumental in reinvigorating a program that was years behind schedule and billions of dollars over budget&#x2014;and bone-tired from chasing the poliovirus across the globe for the past 24 years. &#x201C;Do I like it? When you get medicine that tastes bad, do you like it?,&#x201D; says WHO's Bruce Aylward, a Canadian epidemiologist and physician and longtime leader of GPEI who was recently promoted to assistant director-general for polio, emergencies, and country collaboration at WHO. &#x201C;But do you need it? &#x2026; I wouldn't have turned around the whole program if I didn't think it needed it.&#x201D;</p>
<p>And turn it around they did, with a raft of changes, an infusion of new resources, and a new sense of urgency, all of which seem to be producing results. In June 2012, with polio cases at an all-time low, GPEI earned rare words of praise from IMB: &#x201C;In recent months, the Programme has broken free of its decade-long stagnation.&#x201D; But, the board warned, these gains were fragile, and failure was still a very real possibility.</p>
<sec>
<title>Stalemate</title>
    <p>When the program started in 1988, 125 countries were infected with poliovirus and an estimated 350,000 children were paralyzed each year. By 2006, there were just four countries where the disease was endemic&#x2014;India, Nigeria, Afghanistan, and Pakistan&#x2014;where poliovirus transmission had never been interrupted. Globally, cases of polio had dropped by 99%, thanks to massive campaigns conducted multiple times a year in infected and at-risk countries to immunize every child under age 5 with two drops of oral polio vaccine. Then the program got stuck, unable to vaccinate all children and eliminate the last 1% of cases. Since 2000, cases have fluctuated between 500 and 2000 a year, concentrated in the poorest, most marginalized children in the world (<italic>Science</italic>, 26 March 2004, p. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/303/5666/1960.full">1960</ext-link>).</p>
<p>Periodically, the virus bursts out of those reservoirs and reinfects countries that had rid themselves of the disease. &#x201C;That's why for the past 10 years, GPEI has been playing whack-a-mole all over Africa and Asia,&#x201D; says Thomas Frieden, head of CDC, knocking the virus out in one spot only to have it pop up in another. As the deadline slipped from 2000 to 2005 and now 2012, the program kept spending more and more money each year&#x2014;the annual tab has risen to about $1 billon&#x2014;just to stay in place.</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Straight shooter.</title>
<p>IMB's Liam Donaldson &#x201C;tells it like it is.&#x201D;</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_514_F3" />
<attrib>CREDIT: LONDON TELEGRAPH</attrib>
</fig>
<p>With the global supply of money and patience running low, in 2008 the World Health Assembly asked GPEI to come up with a new strategy. The result was the &#x201C;intensified&#x201D; 2010&#x2013;12 strategic plan that called for stopping transmission of wild poliovirus by the end of 2012. At the same time, the World Health Assembly created IMB to oversee the plan's implementation. WHO Director-General Margaret Chan asked Liam Donaldson, the United Kingdom's chief medical officer from 1998 to 2010, to chair it. Controversial and outspoken, Donaldson has become the distinctive voice of the board, writing each pithy report himself, with the help of an assistant, within a fortnight of each quarterly meeting.</p>
<p>&#x201C;I put great stock in the power of the written word,&#x201D; Donaldson says. &#x201C;We are one of the few parties in polio eradication that can talk frankly, without fear or favor.&#x201D; And that they do.</p>
<p>IMB's first report, in April 2011, was mild enough. There was already reason for concern, IMB said, noting that the program had missed some of its milestones. Time was running out, the board said, and no one was treating eradication as the emergency it was. IMB's July report was tougher in tone, warning for the first time that the &#x201C;GPEI is not on track to interrupt polio transmission as it planned to do by the end of 2012.&#x201D; &#x201C;More of the same will not deliver the polio eradication goal,&#x201D; it said.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>The indictment</title>
    <p>In its October 2011 report, IMB took off its gloves. By then, the situation had deteriorated further. Five of the then-seven countries with persistent polio transmission (the four endemic countries plus three where the virus had become reestablished) had more cases in 2011 than they had had by that point the previous year. Of the four endemic countries, only India was on track to stop transmission by the end of 2011. Afghanistan was making steady progress. Nigeria had knocked cases down by 95% in 2010 but had slipped badly since. Its performance was &#x201C;embarrassing and unacceptable.&#x201D; As for Pakistan, the &#x201C;programme is failing,&#x201D; they wrote, calling its governance &#x201C;deeply dysfunctional&#x201D; (see p. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/337/6094/517.full">517</ext-link>).</p>
<fig id="F4" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Crusader.</title>
<p>Bruce Aylward of WHO has led the charge against polio.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_514_F4" />
<attrib>CREDIT: JAMES DUNCAN DAVIDSON/TED CONFERENCES</attrib>
</fig>
<p>The report ticked off a litany of problems. GPEI's management was in a rut, immersed in a &#x201C;narrative of positivity&#x2014;a pervading sense of &#x2018;nearly there.&#x2019;&#x201D; There are many reasons to project a positive spin, Donaldson concedes, but &#x201C;then probably, maybe they are not as honest with themselves as possible.&#x201D;</p>
<p>At a time when the program desperately needs new ideas, the report added, &#x201C;the relative paucity of innovation is striking,&#x201D; with new ideas &#x201C;too readily condemned to death-by-bureaucracy.&#x201D; There was a lack of what the board calls &#x201C;accountability,&#x201D; a culture in which underperformance is tolerated. It was not too late to stop global transmission by the end of 2012, IMB said. But for that to happen, &#x201C;important changes in style, commitment, and accountability are essential.&#x201D;</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>The shakeup</title>
<p>However tough IMB's criticisms were, they were generally on the mark, people throughout the program say. IMB said what &#x201C;many of us have been saying for some time,&#x201D; CDC's Frieden says. &#x201C;That for too many people, polio eradication had become a lifestyle rather than a mission.&#x201D; Many contend that the report, and the success in India, changed the whole game: India showed them what was possible; IMB told them what was wrong.</p>
<p>Although India had not hit the 1-year mark without a case when IMB issued its indictment, it was clearly headed that way. (On 25 February 2012, India was removed from the list of endemic countries.) That feat laid to rest any arguments about technical barriers to eradication, Aylward says. What turned the tide, says Hamid Jafari, who led the effort in India and is now the director of GPEI at WHO, was the government's commitment&#x2014;it has spent more than $2 billion so far on this gargantuan effort (see table, p. 514)&#x2014;and what he calls &#x201C;inescapable accountability.&#x201D; Each vaccinator knew how many houses to visit; each supervisor was held responsible if they didn't. In places where the virus was most entrenched, such as Uttar Pradesh, vaccination rounds were conducted almost every month. When it became clear that mobile populations were one of the last reservoirs of the virus, the program devised ways to reach them, vaccinating 5 million children at train stations and other transit points in each immunization round in Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, and Mumbai alone. The Kosi River basin in Bihar is flooded for 2 or 3 months after the monsoons; polio teams reached the children by boat. Jafari calls it &#x201C;the relentless pursuit&#x201D; of every last child.</p>
<p>By January 2012, still smarting from IMB's last report, the heads of the five partner organizations had declared polio eradication their top priority. (It was always a priority for Rotary&#x2014;with 1.2 million members, it is one of the world's largest service organizations&#x2014;and Gates, IMB noted; both organizations have each contributed about $1 billion to the effort.)</p>
<p>Frieden was the first to move. On 2 December, he activated CDC's Emergency Operations Center for polio, the war room from which the agency coordinated the national response to emergencies such as bird flu and Hurricane Katrina. This freed up resources like never before. The polio group has tens of additional experts at its disposal and this year is hiring 15 to 20 &#x201C;very high level&#x201D; public health experts, says Greg Armstrong, who leads CDC's effort. The teams of volunteers on the ground are bigger and stay there longer.</p>
<p>WHO and UNICEF soon followed suit. In the past few months, the organizations have recruited thousands of new people in the three endemic countries. The management structure of the initiative has undergone a &#x201C;step change,&#x201D; Aylward says. WHO no longer dominates the effort. For instance, the internal meetings WHO used to hold each Tuesday to review the situation are gone, replaced with a Wednesday conference call attended, virtually, by all the partner agencies.</p>
<fig id="F5" position="float"><graphic xlink:href="337_514_F5" />
<attrib>CREDITS: WHO HEADQUARTERS JULY 2012</attrib>
</fig>
<p>And in late May, IMB finally got what it had asked for all along: The World Health Assembly declared the persistence of polio a &#x201C;programmatic emergency for global public health,&#x201D; in essence, warning infected countries to clean up their acts or face the world's wrath. At the same time, GPEI released its new Polio Global Emergency Action Plan for 2012&#x2013;2013 to replace the failed strategic plan for 2010&#x2013;12. Its subhead: &#x201C;Action to stop polio now in Nigeria, Pakistan and Afghanistan.&#x201D;</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Fragile gains</title>
<p>It's too soon to say whether the reinvigorated program will finally stop polio transmission. &#x201C;We are trying to help the last endemic countries do what India did in 10 years and do it in 12 months,&#x201D; Aylward says. But the early signs are encouraging. As IMB notes in its June 2012 report, case numbers are at a historic low: &#x201C;Compared to the same period last year, there have been: substantially fewer cases (52, down from 123) in fewer districts (39, down from 72), in fewer countries (four, down from 12).&#x201D; (As of 26 July, there have been 100 polio cases, down from 286 this time last year.)</p>
<p>Success, however, is &#x201C;far from inevitable,&#x201D; Donaldson warns. After its dismal performance in 2011, Pakistan has made real strides. But in an all-too-familiar pattern, gains in one country are offset by problems in another. Cases are soaring in Nigeria, setting the stage for an &#x201C;explosive return&#x201D; of polio across Africa. Afghanistan is now on the &#x201C;critical list.&#x201D; And overall, IMB said, a startling 2.7 million children in the six countries where polio now persists have never received a single drop of polio vaccine.</p>
<p>The greatest threat is GPEI's precarious financial position, said IMB. The program is nearly $1 billion short of its roughly $2 billion budget for 2012&#x2013;13, and it has had to cancel or scale back vaccination campaigns in 24 at-risk countries. The world may have gotten weary of repeated alerts about the initiative's funding shortfalls, but this one is qualitatively different, Donaldson says&#x2014;because of the amount of money at stake, and because &#x201C;of the opportunity that stands to be lost.&#x201D;</p>
<p>No one thinks it can be done in 2012, and the new emergency plan doesn't set a date. Its goal is to &#x201C;ensure that the coverage levels needed to stop transmission of all polioviruses are reached by end 2012.&#x201D; Presumably, transmission would be interrupted soon after.</p>
<p>IMB won't venture a guess. Its role, Donaldson says, is to monitor progress for each quarter, and right now, the program is still not on track to stop poliovirus transmission in 2012. As for the board's unflinching criticism, Donaldson says he has no regrets. &#x201C;It has not been our intention to offend anyone, but certainly the criticisms in our reports have not been easy for some to hear.&#x201D; But, he adds, &#x201C;We take seriously our responsibility to &#x2018;tell it like it is.&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>
