<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="article-commentary" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1218616</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1218616</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Perspective</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>perspective</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Systems Biology</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>NEUROSCIENCE</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Modular Biological Complexity</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>Christof</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff id="aff1">Allen Institute for Brain Science, Seattle, WA 98103, USA, and Division of Biology, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA 91125, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>christofk@alleninstitute.org</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6094</issue>
<fpage>531</fpage>
<lpage>532</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>Understanding how vast numbers of heterogeneous components behave in biological systems requires consideration of their interactions as modules.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="excerpt">
<p>It has been argued that the technological capability to fully simulate the human brain on digital computers will exist within a decade. This is taken to imply that we will comprehend its functioning, eliminate all diseases, and &#x201C;upload&#x201D; ourselves to computers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Although such predictions excite the imagination, they are not based on a sound assessment of the complexity of living systems. Such systems are characterized by large numbers of highly heterogeneous components, be they genes, proteins, or cells. These components interact causally in myriad ways across a very large spectrum of space-time, from nanometers to meters and from microseconds to years. A complete understanding of these systems demands that a large fraction of these interactions be experimentally or computationally probed. This is very difficult.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Lisa D. Chong</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Jeff Cook</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>It has been argued that the technological capability to fully simulate the human brain on digital computers will exist within a decade. This is taken to imply that we will comprehend its functioning, eliminate all diseases, and &#x201C;upload&#x201D; ourselves to computers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Although such predictions excite the imagination, they are not based on a sound assessment of the complexity of living systems. Such systems are characterized by large numbers of highly heterogeneous components, be they genes, proteins, or cells. These components interact causally in myriad ways across a very large spectrum of space-time, from nanometers to meters and from microseconds to years. A complete understanding of these systems demands that a large fraction of these interactions be experimentally or computationally probed. This is very difficult.</p>
<p>One can estimate the upper bound on the number of such interactions. The extent to which a system of <italic>n</italic> discrete components integrates information in a synergistic manner can be quantified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>), such that the system acts as more than the union of its parts. This requires evaluating the causal interactions among all possible partitions of the system. Considering all the distinct ways in which the system can be decomposed into parts cannot be done on a statistical basis (as, for example, with an ideal gas) because each interaction is particular; genomes, proteins, and cells interact in specific ways. It is therefore necessary to evaluate all bipartitions, all ways in which the system can be divided into three parts, and so on. The number of ways a system can be partitioned is known as Bell's number <italic>B<sub>n</sub></italic>. For three elements, there are <italic>B</italic><sub>3</sub> = 5 such partitions; three genes, proteins, or cells may not interact at all, or any two of them can interact, or all three, for a total of five possibilities. Understanding the system requires measuring the probability and magnitude of each of these five.</p>
<p>In general, on the order of <italic>B<sub>n</sub></italic> empirical or computational measurements have to be carried out to exhaustively describe the system. Collectively, the sum total of all interactions is referred to as the interactome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). Unfortunately, Bell's number scales faster than exponentially. Thus, <italic>B</italic><sub>10</sub> is already 115,975. The standard asymptotic approximation of <italic>B<sub>n</sub></italic> for large numbers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) is log(<italic>B<sub>n</sub></italic>) &#x2248; <italic>n</italic>[log(<italic>n</italic>) &#x2212; 1].</p>
<p>To appreciate the colossal times necessary to analyze complex organisms in this comprehensive manner, one can presuppose optimistically that the technologies needed to quantify and analyze interactions among the components keep on improving exponentially and indefinitely into the future. Moore predicted that the number of transistors per chip doubles every 18 to 24 months, an observation known as Moore's law. Suppose also that such a law of accelerating returns keeps improving by a factor of 10 each year. And suppose furthermore that in the first year, 10<sup>12</sup> such interactions can be evaluated. In the second year, it will be 10<sup>13</sup>, for a total of 1.1 &#x00D7; 10<sup>13</sup> over the 2 years. This geometric series sums, after <italic>t</italic> years, to 10<sup>12</sup>(10<sup><italic>t</italic></sup> &#x2212; 1)/(10 &#x2212; 1). Setting this equation to <italic>B<sub>n</sub></italic> by exploiting the asymptotic expansion for <italic>B<sub>n</sub></italic>, with 10<sup><italic>t</italic></sup> &gt;&gt; 1 and neglecting the small 12 &#x2212; log(9) term, yields the number of years to fully characterize the complete system: <italic>t<sub>n</sub> &#x2248; n</italic>[log(<italic>n</italic>) &#x2212; 1].</p>
<p>This is bad news. Consider a neuronal synapse&#x2014;the presynaptic terminal has an estimated 1000 distinct proteins. Fully analyzing their possible interactions would take about 2000 years. Or consider the task of fully characterizing the visual cortex of the mouse&#x2014;about 2 million neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). Under the extreme assumption that the neurons in these systems can all interact with each other, analyzing the various combinations will take about 10 million years (see the figure), even though it is assumed that the underlying technology speeds up by an order of magnitude each year. This conclusion is not substantially affected if only a fixed fraction (e.g., 0.001%) of all interactions need to be characterized, if the initial technology is better and could analyze 100 times as many interactions, or if the technology scales annually by two orders of magnitude instead of one. We know from proteomics that not all proteins interact with each other. Likewise, we know from neuroanatomy that brains are not fully interconnected but primarily make local synapses. However, the number of possible interactions in both cases is still on the order of 10<sup>5</sup> or more, which implies an interactome that is astronomically large.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>How long will it take?</title>
<p>The logarithm of Bell's number (left axis) and the upper bound on the time it takes to fully analyze all possible partitions of the system (right axis) are shown as a function of the number of components (proteins or cells).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_531_F1"></graphic>
</fig>
<p>Given the large number of components that cannot be averaged away, any possible technological advance is overwhelmed by the relentless growth of interactions among all components of the system. It is not feasible to understand evolved organisms by exhaustively cataloging all interactions in a comprehensive, bottom-up manner. More is needed.</p>
<p>Allen and Greaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>) recently introduced the metaphor of a &#x201C;complexity brake&#x201D; for the observation that fields as diverse as neuroscience and cancer biology have proven resistant to facile predictions about imminent practical applications. Improved technologies for observing and probing biological systems has only led to discoveries of further levels of complexity that need to be dealt with. This process has not yet run its course. We are far away from understanding cell biology, genomes, or brains, and turning this understanding into practical knowledge. The complexity break is very apparent in the figure.</p>
<p>Engineered systems can contain millions (airplanes) or billions (microprocessors) of components. Yet these are purposefully built in such a manner to limit the interactions among the parts to a small number. For instance, design rules for the a layout of integrated electronic circuits impose a minimum distance between wires and other components to eliminate coupling, and separate power supply from computing, and computing from memory. None of this is true for nervous systems. It is this reduction in the interactome that allows engineers to build large and robust systems where the complexity brake does not apply.</p>
<p>The complexity brake could be loosened if a supra-individual level of components were discovered. If groups of components behave as a single module, the effective number of interactions that need to be analyzed would drop precipitously. If a minicolumn of about 1000 cortical neurons proves to be the relevant module to understand the cerebral cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>), <italic>t<sub>n</sub></italic> for the mouse visual cortex reduces from millions of years to five millennia. If the interactions among minicolumns could be further causally reduced to interactions among cortical columns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>), where each column consists of about 10 &#x00D7; 10 minicolumns, the goal to fully understand the visual cortex could be reached within 6 years (assuming technologies increase by a factor of 10 each year).</p>
<p>The discovery of modular, hierarchical structures that capture the behavior of complex systems in a causal manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>) is essential to speed up solving these challenging problems. This emphasizes the need to develop heuristic methods to discover modules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>). For if appropriate modules cannot be found, understanding of life will escape us.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>I thank N. Joshi for the plot. Supported by the Paul G. Allen Family Foundation.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurzweil</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>The Singularity Is Near</source> (<publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <year>2005</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balduzzi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tononi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source> <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>e1000091</fpage> (<year>2008</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source> <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage> (<year>1999</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Bruijin</surname><given-names>N. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Asymptotic Methods in Analysis</source> (<publisher-name>North-Holland</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>, <year>1958</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Nature</source> <volume>483</volume>, <fpage>397</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Technol. Rev.</source> <volume>12</volume>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.technologyreview.com/view/425733/paul-allen-the-singularity-isnt-near">www.technologyreview.com/view/425733/paul-allen-the-singularity-isnt-near</ext-link> (<year>2011</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buxhoeveden</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casanova</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Brain</source> <volume>125</volume>, <fpage>935</fpage> (<year>2002</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mountcastle</surname><given-names>V. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Brain</source> <volume>120</volume>, <fpage>701</fpage> (<year>1997</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartwel</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Nature</source> <volume>402</volume> (<issue>suppl.</issue>), <fpage>C47</fpage> (<year>1999</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e17013</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>