<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="other" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>New Products</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Products &amp; Materials</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>products</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>New Products</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>03</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6094</issue>
<fpage seq="a">603</fpage>
<lpage>603</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>A weekly roundup of information on newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of potential interest to researchers.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary">
<p>A weekly roundup of information on newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of potential interest to researchers.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>PCR WORKSTATIONS </title>
<fig id="F1" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="337_603a_F1"><alt-text>Figure 1</alt-text></graphic></fig>
<p>AirClean Systems AC600 Series PCR workstations are designed as application solutions for the manipulation and amplification of DNA and RNA. These polymerase chain reaction (PCR) workstations are available in 24", 32", and 48" widths. Additional features include built-in 254 nm ultraviolet (UV) lights for irradiation and HEPA filtration for a clean work area. Standard on 32" and 48" wide models, the UVTect Microprocessor Controller maintains airflow to provide a clean Class 100 work area during PCR preparation. UVTect<sup> </sup>provides audible and visible alarms to alert the end user of insufficient airflow, UV bulb changes, and HEPA filter changes. UVTect also allows the operator to vary blower speed and digitally set irradiation timer and lab event timer to current application requirements. In addition, each workstation features an interlocking sash with a safety switch that automatically turns off the UV light and activates blower and fluorescent light when the sash is raised.  </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>AirClean Systems</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-849-0472     </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aircleansystems.com">www.aircleansystems.com</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>MINI VIEWING CABINET </title>
<p>The compact, lightweight CM-10MP mini viewing cabinet is perfect for any type of life science application requiring high-contrast fluorescence analysis. It is also excellent for viewing TLC plates and for quality control inspection of PC boards. Weighing only 4 lbs. (1.8 kg), it can be conveniently carried from place to place. With its compact dimensions of 8.75" W x 10" L x 4.5" H (22.2 cm W x 25.4 cm L x 11.4 cm H), this space-saving unit can fit easily in cramped areas. The CM-10MP is made of molded, high-impact plastic for rugged durability. It features a contoured eyepiece with a built-in ultraviolet (UV)-absorbing window for safe viewing. Openings on top of the cabinet accommodate one or two MiniMAX Series UV lamps. MiniMAX lamps are available in three models&#x2014;UV-5A for long-wave UV (365 nm), UV-5F for short-wave UV (254 nm), and UV-5NF for a combination of both long- and short-wave UV emissions.</p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Spectroline</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-274-8888      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.spectroline.com">www.spectroline.com</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>FT-IR SPECTROMETER </title>
<p>The Nicolet iS50 FT-IR spectrometer, the first research-grade FT-IR with one-touch operation, features purpose-built accessories and integrated analytical software capabilities to provide a truly all-in-one materials analysis platform that helps laboratories solve analytical challenges with unprecedented ease. The highly flexible system can be upgraded from a simple FT-IR bench to a fully automated multi-spectral range system that can acquire spectra from the far- to the near-infrared. Users can initiate novel ATR, Raman, and NIR modules at the touch of a button, enabling access to these techniques without manually changing system components. The flexible system architecture of the Nicolet iS50 is designed to improve the speed of analysis while eliminating the possibility of operational errors that can occur while changing instrument components. The instrument's integrated diamond ATR allows users to obtain IR spectra in seconds, and a novel in-sample-compartment FT-Raman feature includes a video microstage for point-and-shoot Raman spectroscopy with no fluorescence. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Thermo Fisher Scientific</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-532-4752      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.thermoscientific.com/iS50">www.thermoscientific.com/iS50</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>MINIPREP SYSTEMS</title>
<p>The ReliaPrep 96 gDNA MiniPrep HT System has been launched to complement the recently released ReliaPrep RNA Cell MiniPrep System, for the extraction and isolation of gDNA and RNA respectively. The range of ReliaPrep Systems is designed to isolate pure nucleic acid from very small sample volumes, from blood, tissue, FFPE, or cell samples, in a simple and reliable process. ReliaPrep 96 gDNA MiniPrep HT System provides a robust method for purifying gDNA from blood and Oragene-DNA sample collection devices in a multiwell format. DNA is captured using paramagnetic particles and without the need for an organic solvent, eliminating the need for centrifugation or vacuum manifolds and making the system safe, convenient, and suitable for full automation. The ReliaPrep RNA Cell MiniPrep System enables isolation of RNA from samples of very small numbers of cells. Eluted in small volumes (less than 15 &#x03BC;L), the isolated RNA is free of contaminants and inhibitors. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>Promega</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-356-9526      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.promega.com">www.promega.com</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="product-information">
<title>CHROMATOGRAPHY MEDIUM </title>
<p>Capto L affinity chromatography medium (resin) is designed for the purification of antibody fragments. It combines a rigid, high-flow agarose matrix with the immunoglobulin-binding recombinant protein L ligand, which has strong affinity for the variable region of antibody's kappa light chain. Capto L is therefore suitable for purification of a range of antibody fragments such as Fabs, single-chain variable fragments and domain antibodies. With its high dynamic binding capacity and high selectivity, Capto L increases process economy and process design flexibility. Capto L is a BioProcess medium supported for commercial manufacturing and enables a high-productivity platform approach to antibody fragment purification. Availability of flexible formats such as PreDictor plates and PreDictor RoboColumn units speeds up the screening and optimization of binding and elution conditions. HiTrap and HiScreen prepacked columns can be utilized for confirming screening and optimization results in packed bed conditions as well as for convenient small-scale purification. </p>
<list list-type="simple" list-content="company-information">
<list-item><p><bold>GE Healthcare</bold></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>For info: 800-526-3593      </p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gelifesciences.com/captol">www.gelifesciences.com/captol</ext-link></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="product-submission-instructions"><p>Electronically submit your new product description or product literature information! Go to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/products/newproducts.dtl">www.sciencemag.org/products/newproducts.dtl</ext-link> for more information.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="disclaimer"><p><italic>Newly offered instrumentation, apparatus, and laboratory materials of interest to researchers in all disciplines in academic, industrial, and governmental organizations are featured in this space. Emphasis is given to purpose, chief characteristics, and availabilty of products and materials. Endorsement by </italic>Science<italic> or AAAS of any products or materials mentioned is not implied. Additional information may be obtained from the manufacturer or supplier.</italic></p></fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
