<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id><journal-title>Science</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>MEDICINE</subject><subject>ASIA/PACIFIC NEWS</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Polio Campaign</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Fighting Polio in Pakistan</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>Leslie</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date><volume>337</volume><issue>6094</issue><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Pakistan's 18-year struggle shows why it is so hard to eradicate polio from its last few strongholds.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>In 2011, Pakistan became the global epicenter of polio, with more cases than any country in the world. The Global Polio Eradication Initiative, with help from the Edhi Foundation, Pakistan's largest and best-known charity, has since been pulling out all the stops, and the government is on board as never before. As a result, polio cases are down, and Nigeria has eclipsed Pakistan as the gravest threat to polio eradication. But the recent success is too fragile to say that Pakistan has turned the corner. Because the virus is so contagious and spreads so stealthily, as long as it lingers anywhere, the world is at risk. And that means if eradication fails in Pakistan, the 24-year, nearly $10 billion initiative fails everywhere.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>On the move.</title>
<p>A boy receives a dose of oral polio vaccine at a train station in Karachi.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_517_F1" />
<attrib>CREDIT: &#x00A9; UNICEF/NYHQ2011-0195/ZAIDI</attrib>
</fig>
<p><bold>KARACHI AND ISLAMABAD, PAKISTAN</bold>&#x2014;In early spring, just as the heat was beginning to take hold, a handful of men incongruously dressed in suits and ties made their way down a dusty street in one of Karachi's chaotic market districts. Carefully sidestepping the freshly slaughtered cow that was being skinned outside the door, they entered the modest two-room office of the Edhi Foundation, Pakistan's largest and best-known charity.</p>
<p>The visitors, who included some of the top brass from the World Health Organization (WHO), were there to see Abdul Sattar Edhi&#x2014;a philanthropist who has dedicated his life to helping the poor&#x2014;to ask for his help in turning around the polio eradication program in Pakistan, which was failing badly.</p>
<p>Edhi, 84, who has a weathered face and long, white beard and was dressed as always in a simple homespun cotton tunic, vowed to do all he could to help vaccinate those children the eradication program has not been able to reach&#x2014;those who live in the tribal areas that are so dangerous that no health workers can go there, for example, or in places where mothers, suspicious of anything that smacks of the government or the West, won't open their doors.</p>
<p>He offered his fleet of 1800 ambulances to serve as mobile vaccination units; families could also bring their children to his 300-plus health centers across the country to receive polio drops. To counter pervasive rumors, he would broadcast the message that the polio vaccine is safe. &#x201C;People believe in me. I will be helpful to you,&#x201D; he said.</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Ally.</title>
<p>Known as Pakistan's Mother Teresa, Abdul Sattar Edhi has joined the fight against polio.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_517_F2" />
<attrib>CREDIT: WHO PAKISTAN</attrib>
</fig>
<p>And with that, and a profusion of thanks, photos, and handshakes all around, the visitors were off, back to their waiting drivers and on to their next mission. Elias Durry, who leads WHO's polio eradication team in Pakistan, was elated. &#x201C;Edhi is able to go where the Taliban fights. They trust his motives. It is marvelous to have him,&#x201D; he said as the car inched down the clogged street.</p>
<p>The Edhi Foundation won't solve Pakistan's polio problem. But the fact that the people at the front of the Global Polio Eradication Initiative (GPEI) have come to this corner of the world to knock on his door illustrates just how critical this country is to the effort to defeat this stubborn virus, which has been chased out of almost every country, including Pakistan's neighbor and rival India, just this year.</p>
<p>GPEI, a partnership of WHO, the U.N. Children's Fund (UNICEF), the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Rotary International, and more recently, the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, has good reason to worry. In 2011, Pakistan became the global epicenter of the disease, with more cases than any country in the world. An October report from the influential Independent Monitoring Board (IMB) (see p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="337" page="514" issue="6094">514</related-article>) minced no words: &#x201C;Pakistan's progress now lags far behind every other country in the world. Without urgent and fundamental change, it is a safe bet that it will be the last country on earth to host polio.&#x201D;</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float"><graphic xlink:href="337_517_F3" />
<attrib>CREDIT: JAKE NOWAKOWSKI/NEWSPIX; WHO HEADQUARTERS JULY 2012</attrib>
</fig>
<p>In an effort to turn that around, GPEI has been pulling out all the stops&#x2014;bringing in high-powered talent like Durry, deploying a surge of more than 1000 additional staff on the ground, reaching out to Edhi and other community leaders, and devising new tactics for the most recalcitrant strongholds of the virus. After years of indifference, the government is on board as never before. It's still early, but the efforts seem to be paying off. Polio cases are down so far this year, and Nigeria has eclipsed Pakistan as the gravest threat to polio eradication.</p>
<p>But the recent success is too fragile to say that Pakistan has turned the corner. Because the virus is so contagious and spreads so stealthily, as long as it lingers anywhere, the entire world is at risk. And that means if eradication fails in Pakistan, the 24-year, nearly $10 billion initiative fails everywhere.</p>
<sec>
<title>Thirty-five million times six</title>
<p>Messy and complicated, Pakistan is the perfect case study for why it is so hard to eradicate poliovirus from its last few strongholds&#x2014;and what it might take to pull it off. Wiping a human disease off the face of the earth, which has only been done once before, for smallpox, requires synchronized vaccination campaigns executed with near-military precision multiple times a year to reach all the children under age 5 with two drops of oral polio vaccine. In Pakistan, that means immunizing some 35 million kids about six times a year. But in Pakistan, nothing much works as it should, and certainly not with precision.</p>
<p>For a while, Pakistan seemed to be on track. Sure, it was always a trouble spot&#x2014;one of the few countries where transmission of the poliovirus has never been stopped. But since the program began in earnest there in 1994, cases dropped more or less steadily, reaching an all-time low of 28 in 2005.</p>
<p>Even when cases began to climb in 2008, there wasn't much alarm; GPEI was focused on India and Nigeria, then considered the biggest threats to success. In Pakistan, the mantra was, once vaccinators could get into the tribal areas along the troubled border with Afghanistan, polio would disappear. And if Pakistan went, Afghanistan would follow.</p>
<fig id="F4" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Strategist.</title>
<p>Chris Maher is overseeing the &#x201C;surge&#x201D; of new WHO staff in the polio-infected countries.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_517_F4" />
<attrib>CREDIT: JAKE NOWAKOWSKI/NEWSPIX; WHO HEADQUARTERS JULY 2012</attrib>
</fig>
<p>&#x201C;After Pakistan cases [dropped] in 2005, it looked extremely good. The focus and pressure changed before the job was done,&#x201D; says Dennis King, who heads UNICEF's polio eradication program in Pakistan and is coordinating that agency's influx of new workers. &#x201C;When cases were going down, it looked like what we were doing was working, and it largely was,&#x201D; says Chris Maher, WHO's top operations man, who for the past 20 years has combated polio in the toughest spots in the world and now splits his time roughly between Pakistan, Afghanistan, and Nigeria, the last three endemic countries.</p>
<p>Then in 2011, cases shot up &#x201C;in a very scary way,&#x201D; Maher says, in sharp contrast with India, which soon went a year without a case and has now been removed from the list of endemic countries. Pakistan's case count topped out at 198 by the end of 2011. That may not sound like a lot, but for every child paralyzed, 100 or 200 others are infected asymptomatically and are silently spreading the virus.</p>
<p>What's more, cases were not just clustered in the tribal areas but had spread to previously polio-free places across the country, such as Punjab, where there were no apparent obstacles to reaching the children. And in 2011 for the first time, poliovirus from Pakistan jumped the border into China, sparking a large outbreak.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>A perfect storm</title>
<p>Maher and others attribute the explosion of cases last year to a perfect storm of all the problems that are Pakistan: poverty and illiteracy; a health system in tatters; ethnic and sectarian violence; a government struggling to deal with corruption and dysfunction; huge population movements; and, especially since 9/11, rising extremism and anti-Western views&#x2014;not to mention the natural attrition that accompanies any program that has dragged on for so long. Equally important, he says, is the nature of the beast that they are fighting&#x2014;the poliovirus&#x2014;which, after all these years, still manages to surprise. &#x201C;I think there are some years when conditions are more favorable&#x201D; for widespread polio transmission, Maher says. &#x201C;To some extent it is cyclical as with any infectious disease&#x2014;something we don't give enough weight to especially as far as polio is concerned.&#x201D;</p>
<p>What's clear, Maher says, is that &#x201C;if you knock the virus down to fairly low levels, it is not going to stay there. That is not the nature of the disease. Unless you can take it one step further from knocking down the virus to knocking it out, you will be punished.&#x201D; And that's what happened in Pakistan.</p>
<fig id="F5" position="float">
<caption>
<title>The fixer.</title>
<p>WHO's Elias Durry was brought in to clear up polio in Pakistan.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_517_F5" />
<attrib>PHOTO CREDIT: WHO/SALAH TUMSAH</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Sometime in the mid-2000s, it became apparent that poliovirus circulated in three distinct transmission zones in Pakistan, each with its own unique genetic signature: the Federally Administered Tribal Areas (FATA) and adjoining Khyber Pakhtunkhwa (KP), formerly known as the Northwest Frontier Province, in the northwest along the border with Afghanistan; Balochistan, which is south of FATA and also shares a porous border with Afghanistan; and Karachi at the southern tip of the country on the Arabian Sea, with 14 million people, the only megacity in the world to have polio. And within these zones, polio is concentrated in 33 high-risk districts where, for various reasons, it has been impossible to vaccinate all the children. Not coincidentally, these holdouts tend to be the most badly broken of all the broken places in Pakistan, Maher says.</p>
<p>In 2011, 73% of all cases were genetically linked to these three areas. &#x201C;They drive the agenda,&#x201D; Maher says. &#x201C;You can do a brilliant job in 80% of the country, but it makes no difference if you do a lousy job in the rest.&#x201D; FATA and KP are home base to the Taliban and al-Qaeda and a training ground for jihadists. There, myriad tribes and clans are at war with each other, the federal government, and the West. Female literacy is a mere 3%. The area has been pounded by U.S. drone strikes, which have killed an estimated 1900 to 2900 people since 2004, according to the New America Foundation. Abbottabad, where U.S. Navy SEALs killed Osama bin Laden in May 2011, is in KP, and the CIA's fake vaccination campaign there to try to identify his family has only inflamed animosity to and suspicion about polio vaccination, which is rumored to be a Western plot to sterilize or otherwise harm Muslim children. In parts of the tribal areas, no polio campaigns have been conducted in the last 3 years; in January 2011, 38% of the children in Khyber Agency, FATA, were inaccessible, according to WHO data. (That number, which fluctuates, dropped to 20% in January 2012.)</p>
<fig id="F6" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Barriers to Polio Vaccination in Pakistan</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_517_F6" />
<attrib>CREDIT: WHO GRAPH SOURCES: UNICEF/INDEPENDENT MONITORING DATA JAN. 2012; UNICEF/INDEPENDENT MONITORING DATA; UNICEF/2012 KAP STUDY</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Balochistan borders Kandahar and Helmand in Afghanistan, where poliovirus circulation is unchecked and people and the virus move freely across the border. It's a dangerous place, where kidnappings and other crimes are rampant, and a climate of fear keeps vaccinators out. Recently, the Taliban has extended its reach in Balochistan. Like FATA and KP, the province is a hotbed of religious extremism and anti-American views. In the first few months of 2012 in Quetta Block, the hottest polio hot spot in Balochistan, the proportion of parents who refused to let their children be vaccinated increased dramatically. Of all the missed children there, about 50% were &#x201C;active refusals,&#x201D; according to UNICEF (see graphic).</p>
<p>And then there is Karachi, &#x201C;which has all the problems in the world,&#x201D; says WHO's Tariq Masood, who is an area coordinator in Karachi. That city has a large minority and migrant population that settles in the squalid periurban slums that stretch for miles. With so many people traveling in and out of the city, Karachi serves as the hub and amplifier of the virus&#x2014;it was virus from Karachi that sparked the outbreak in China. Most of the migrants are Pashtun, the dominant ethnic group in Afghanistan and tribal areas but an unwelcome minority in Karachi. In 2011, 77% of all polio cases in Pakistan occurred in Pashto-speaking people, although they account for just 8% of the population. Across the country, huge numbers of people are on the move, often between the three transmission zones, fleeing the violence of the tribal areas, in search of seasonal jobs, or displaced by the historic floods of the past 2 years. And when they travel, the poliovirus often goes with them.</p>
<fig id="F7" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Spreading the word.</title>
<p>One of UNICEF's health promoters goes door to door in Karachi to brief families about polio.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_517_F7" />
<attrib>CREDIT: UNICEF/ASAD ZAIDI</attrib>
</fig>
<p>In all three transmission zones, the federal government has little control; instead, power is concentrated at the local levels, where corruption and nepotism are rife. Over the years, Durry says, polio eradication became something of a full-employment act. Polio money lined the pockets of corrupt officials, who dispensed jobs as favors, turning over vaccination posts to their brother or their cousin, who might in turn pass it on to their kids, who would work for nothing but did nothing, either. &#x201C;We created a monster,&#x201D; Durry concedes.</p>
<p>In many places, unmotivated and unpaid vaccinators showed up late and stopped early. Sometimes the campaigns didn't take place at all: ghost campaigns, Durry calls them. All too often teams didn't inspire trust&#x2014;say, if they were children, or they didn't speak Pashto, or if the only vaccinators were men. The battle is won or lost &#x201C;in those 30 seconds when the mother opens the door and decides,&#x201D; Durry says. And at the end of the day, data were falsified.</p>
<p>In its October 2011 report, with cases soaring, IMB labeled Pakistan's program &#x201C;deeply dysfunctional,&#x201D; citing its &#x201C;diseased core&#x201D; and calling the government on the carpet and urging it to &#x201C;fundamentally re-think&#x201D; its program.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>The surge</title>
<p>Even before then, alarmed at the rise in cases, GPEI began to intensify its operations in Pakistan. In May 2011, WHO brought in Durry, an Ethiopian-born epidemiologist who had delivered some of the toughest countries on time, such as Somalia and South Sudan. If anyone could turn around Pakistan, the reasoning went, he could. &#x201C;They do this to me all the time,&#x201D; he says somewhat ruefully.</p>
<p>By December, the Pakistani government, with help from WHO and the other GPEI partners, had crafted its &#x201C;augmented&#x201D; emergency action plan for polio eradication in 2012. The new plan declares polio eradication a national emergency and puts in place strict new measures to ensure what officials call &#x201C;accountability&#x201D; at all levels. To see that this plan actually did something this time, the government appointed Shahnaz Wazir Ali to a new position as the country's &#x201C;focal person&#x201D; for polio eradication. Smart, driven, exacting, and with the ear of the prime minister, Wazir Ali has made a huge difference, program leaders say. In May, she led a delegation to India to learn from the experts firsthand.</p>
<p>Borrowing a leaf or two from India's playbook, the ramped-up efforts are concentrating on the country's 33 high-risk districts&#x2014;and within those, specific towns or subdistricts like Pishin in Balochistan's Quetta Block and Gadap in Karachi&#x2014;where large numbers of children are missed in each campaign. Those 33 districts are where all the &#x201C;surge&#x201D; personnel have been deployed&#x2014;some 1000 from UNICEF and 350 from WHO. The WHO teams assist with technical issues such as training, surveillance, and monitoring; UNICEF works with the community to try to increase acceptance of, and generate demand for, the polio vaccine. Data from a January 2012 survey show the magnitude of what the organization is up against.</p>
<p>One of the biggest changes is at the grassroots level, where the old network of ineffectual supervisors has been booted out, replaced by the higher-level district commissioners, who are like mayors in the United States. The plan spells out exactly who must do what, including the composition of the vaccination team, the number of meetings to hold, and who must attend to prepare for each campaign. If a union council, or town, is not prepared, the round is canceled; workers' salaries are docked, or they are put on probation, or sometimes fired.</p>
<p>In the high-risk districts, efforts are focused on the highest-risk populations, mainly the Pashtun, migrants, and nomadic populations. Mobile populations will be the Achilles' heel in Pakistan, Durry says, because so many travel in and out of the tribal areas where virus circulation is unchecked. The key, he says, is to anticipate their movements and make special arrangements to vaccinate them wherever they are.</p>
<p>In the past few months, the program has set up tens of permanent transit posts that offer polio drops 24/7 at common entry and exit points from FATA/KP, Balochistan, and Karachi. At one toll booth alone in Karachi, 13,688 children were vaccinated between 23 April and 9 May, according to WHO. Efforts are also under way to negotiate access to the tribal areas. In the meantime, Durry's team is trying to figure out how best to take advantage of any opportunity to get in and out of conflict zones quickly. One strategy is to deliver multiple doses of vaccine at very short intervals&#x2014;a few days apart instead of the usual 4 to 6 weeks. No empirical studies have proved that this strategy works, but it seemed to help quickly boost immunity in Somalia, where Durry first introduced it, and it's worth a try, he says.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Off the critical list</title>
<p>In June 2012, with cases down significantly from the previous year (so far to date there have been 23 cases compared with 60 this time last year), IMB took Pakistan off the critical list, commending the government for significantly improving its game&#x2014;while still warning that tough challenges remain.</p>
<p>What's most encouraging to Durry is that environmental sampling, the testing of sewage water for poliovirus, is clearing up in some places&#x2014;most surprisingly in Gadap town in Karachi, where samples have been positive for years (see sidebar, p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="337" page="520" issue="6094">520</related-article>). But just as Gadap improved, positive samples have cropped up in Lahore, Punjab, where everyone assumed the program was working fine. That means redoubling efforts on that front, Durry says: &#x201C;We have to put more resources into central Pakistan without losing our focus on places like Karachi.&#x201D;</p>
<p>There are plenty of other caveats. Pakistan has yet to bear the full brunt of the high season when cases rise along with the rains. There's been little progress in Pishin, where Durry says &#x201C;we are still trying to make things happen without intimidation and sometimes sabotage&#x201D; and where, as in much of Balochistan, vaccination is still done by children as young as 8. Parts of FATA remain inaccessible, and a June letter from a Taliban leader in North Waziristan saying the Taliban will block vaccination until U.S. drone strikes stop certainly didn't help, although it is unclear how much it hurt, says Aziz Memon, the national chair of Rotary's PolioPlus program in Pakistan, noting that in many places, &#x201C;We didn't have access anyway.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Even so, Durry says, &#x201C;Pakistan is in the best position ever to finish the job,&#x201D; and he thinks the country can&#x2014;if the program can sustain momentum and somehow get access to the children in FATA. &#x201C;If we had denied that there is corruption and a problem in management and just tried to go around it, we never would have reached anywhere,&#x201D; Durry says. &#x201C;But once you know the problems, the solutions are not that tough.&#x201D;</p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>
