<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="obituary" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1226088</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1226088</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Retrospective</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>perspective</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Retrospective</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>ECOLOGY</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>F. Herbert Bormann (1922&#x2013;2012)</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hedin</surname><given-names>Lars O.</given-names></name></contrib>
<aff id="aff1">Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, Princeton University, Princeton, NJ 08544, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp>E-mail: <email>lhedin@princeton.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>03</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6094</issue>
<fpage>534</fpage>
<lpage>534</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser">
<p>An ecologist's relentless focus on large-scale studies of watersheds played a key role in identifying human impacts on forests.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="excerpt">
<p>F. Herbert Bormann was a leading architect of our modern view of land ecosystems. At a time when ecology was largely concerned with individual species in local environments, Bormann and his collaborators proposed that nature can be rigorously understood as an integrated whole by measuring how entire ecosystems of interacting species cycle nutrients and minerals at the scale of forested watersheds. The result&#x2014;the small watershed ecosystem approach&#x2014;has since grown into a leading tool for understanding how complex land ecosystems function in the biosphere and how these systems are affected by stresses such as air pollution or climate change.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Julia Fahrenkamp-Uppenbrink</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Cynthia Howe</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>F. Herbert Bormann was a leading architect of our modern view of land ecosystems. At a time when ecology was largely concerned with individual species in local environments, Bormann and his collaborators proposed that nature can be rigorously understood as an integrated whole by measuring how entire ecosystems of interacting species cycle nutrients and minerals at the scale of forested watersheds. The result&#x2014;the small watershed ecosystem approach&#x2014;has since grown into a leading tool for understanding how complex land ecosystems function in the biosphere and how these systems are affected by stresses such as air pollution or climate change.</p>
<p>Central to the development of the small watershed idea, and to what became the Hubbard Brook Ecosystem Study in the White Mountains of New Hampshire, was a meeting of four young minds in the early 1960s. Bormann, then a botany professor at Dartmouth College, had been exposed to the idea that forest hydrology could be measured at scales of entire watersheds and held a long-standing interest in how biological communities and their physical environment are best abstracted in nature. Gene E. Likens, just arrived at Dartmouth, shared Bormann's fascination with complex ecosystems and brought deep understanding of biogeochemistry and of whole-ecosystem experimentation. Robert S. Pierce, a scientific leader at the U.S. Forest Service, had just begun hydrological studies of gauged watersheds at the Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest. Finally, Noye M. Johnson was a young Dartmouth geochemist with keen understanding of weathering in coupled plant-soil-water systems.</p>
<p>What evolved was a new technique for studying and quantifying land ecosystems that has since revolutionized ecology, biogeochemistry, and environmental biology. In their seminal 1967 article in <italic>Science</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>), Bormann and Likens offered a conceptual justification for their new approach: &#x201C;The small watershed, with its measured parameters of hydrologic and chemical input, output, and net change, is an excellent vehicle for the study of interrelationships within a single ecosystem.&#x201D; By carefully measuring the dynamics of nutrients and pollutants at the vast scale of watersheds, Bormann and his colleagues drew new connections between the biosphere, atmosphere, geosphere, and hydrosphere.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<graphic xlink:href="337_534_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: JOYCE H. DOPKEEN/THE NEW YORK TIMES/REDUX PICTURES</attrib>
</fig>
<p>A series of influential findings followed. Perhaps most eye-catching was the experimental deforestation of an entire watershed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>), aimed at understanding how the internal plant-soil cycle of nutrients and water acts to sustain forests. Today, we accept the value of large-scale experiments (witness recent iron fertilizations of large swaths of ocean), but at that time, watershed manipulations had never before sought to disentangle the biogeochemistry of a forested ecosystem. In 1979, Bormann and Likens presented a conceptual model of the Hubbard Brook forest ecosystem that was grounded in more than 20 years of research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>The scientific value of the Hubbard Brook small watershed approach has only increased over time, and the model has been replicated worldwide. During the often intense debate about acid rain in the 1980s and 1990s, measurements and experiments from the Hubbard Brook watersheds were crucial for identifying acid rain in North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) and for elucidating the serious and complex ways by which human-produced sulfuric and nitric acids affect forest plants, soils, and waters.</p>
<p>Today, the long-term records of careful measurements collected since 1963 are offering invaluable clues about how ecosystems respond to climate change and other human perturbations. Central to these insights is the accumulation of the longest, most complete, and most integrated record of nutrient cycling, hydrology, forest growth, and climate change available anywhere: a half-century-long national treasure of environmental understanding.</p>
<p>Bormann's unique perspective may have arisen from early influences in his life. Born in 1922 in an apartment above Riverside Drive in New York City, he was affected by his mother's love of nature and his father's interest in social issues of the day. As an undergraduate student with Murray Buell at Rutgers University and as a Ph.D. student with Henry Oosting at Duke University, he was exposed to Frederic Clements' ideas on how plant communities interact with their environments. But perhaps most influential throughout his career was Bormann's close relationship with his colleague, Gene Likens, whose point of view he once referred to as &#x201C;a complement to my own.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Bormann was the Oastler Professor of Forest Ecology at Yale University from 1966 to his retirement in 1992. He was a member of the National Academy of Sciences and received numerous honors, including the prestigious Blue Planet Prize. As he addressed his fellow colleagues in celebration of his retirement at the yearly meeting of collaborating scientists at Hubbard Brook&#x2014;back then, held in a crowded and much-too-hot barn on U.S. Forest Service property&#x2014;he could not resist the temptation of showing newly produced graphs illustrating how the small watershed approach might be applied to ecosystem sustainability. His late-career interest in environmental sustainability is evocatively illustrated in a book on the American lawn, published with a group of students near his retirement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>Herb Bormann's passing leaves a void for many. Those of us who knew Herb experienced a mind dedicated to seeing the whole as well as the parts, to understanding top-down causation as well as bottom-up. Students who took his classes were inspired to think independently, question conventions, integrate across disciplines, and link ecological knowledge to the most urgent environmental issues of the day.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bormann</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Likens</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Science</source> <volume>155</volume>, <fpage>424</fpage> (<year>1967</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Likens</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>., <source>Science</source> <volume>163</volume>, <fpage>1205</fpage> (<year>1969</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bormann</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Likens</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Pattern and Process in a Forested Ecosystem</source> (<publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <year>1979</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Likens</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bormann</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Science</source> <volume>184</volume>, <fpage>1176</fpage> (<year>1974</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bormann</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balmori</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geballe</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Redesigning the American Lawn: A Search for Environmental Harmony</source> (<publisher-name>Yale Univ. Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>, <year>1993</year>).</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
