<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id><journal-title>Science</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI POLICY</subject><subject>NEUROSCIENCE</subject><subject>PSYCHOLOGY</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Science and the Courts</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>In Mock Case, Biological Evidence Reduces Sentences</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Greg</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>17</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date><volume>337</volume><issue>6096</issue><fpage>788</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>In a fictional case, judges presented with biological evidence of psychopathy handed out reduced sentences, researchers report in this week's issue.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>In a recent study, U.S. trial judges reviewed a case involving a fictional violent crime, including psychiatric testimony that the perpetrator had been diagnosed as a psychopath. Some of them also read testimony from a neurobiologist who testified that the perpetrator possessed a specific genetic variant linked to violent behavior and that research with other psychopaths has identified abnormalities in brain function that may undermine the normal human aversion to inflicting harm on others. When asked how they would sentence the criminal, the judges who read this biological explanation handed out modestly reduced prison sentences. That judges would be swayed by biological evidence in such a violent case surprised the study researchers, who report their findings on page <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/337/6096/846">846</ext-link> of this week's issue.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Jonathan Donahue is a textbook psychopath. In 2008, he beat the manager of a Burger King restaurant, leaving the man with permanent brain damage. When apprehended, he showed no remorse. He&apos;d kept bashing the manager on the back of the head with a pistol, he said, because &#x201C;that fat son-of-a-bitch wouldn&apos;t stop crying.&#x201D; He bragged about the beating to other prisoners and had a crown&#x2014;a reference to the fast-food restaurant&apos;s cartoon king mascot&#x2014;tattooed on his back.</p>
<p>In a recent Web-based study, 181 state trial judges from across the United States reviewed the details of Donahue&apos;s case, which is fictional but loosely based on a real crime. All of the judges read testimony from a psychiatrist who testified that Donahue had been diagnosed as a psychopath. Some of them also read testimony from a neurobiologist, who presented results of a genetic test showing that Donahue possessed a specific genetic variant linked to violent behavior. The neurobiologist also testified that research with other psychopaths has identified abnormalities in brain function that may undermine the normal human aversion to inflicting harm on others. When asked to imagine how they would rule in a sentencing hearing, the judges who read this biological explanation cited more mitigating factors (such as mental illness) and handed out modestly reduced prison sentences&#x2014;13 years, on average, compared with 14 years for judges who did not see this testimony.</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Biology goes to court.</title>
<p>A new study looks at whether judges are swayed by testimony about the biological basis of criminal behavior.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_788_F1"/>
<attrib>CREDIT: ISTOCKPHOTO.COM</attrib>
</fig>
<p>That judges would be swayed by biological evidence in such a violent case surprised James Tabery, a philosophy professor at the University of Utah in Salt Lake City, who conducted the study with two Utah colleagues: social psychologist Lisa Aspinwall and law professor Teneille Brown. The trio reports its findings on page <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/337/6096/846.full">846</ext-link>. Biological explanations of behavior are potentially a double-edged sword in the courtroom, Tabery explains: They could be seen as aggravating evidence that a defendant is &#x201C;hard-wired&#x201D; for bad behavior and destined to reoffend, or they could be seen as mitigating evidence that a defendant&apos;s behavior was outside his control. Tabery says the new findings suggest the sword may cut more sharply for the defense in such cases.</p>
<p>And the cases are not just hypothetical. To the consternation of some of his colleagues, neuroscientist Kent Kiehl of the University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, testified for the defense in the 2009 sentencing phase of a trial for Brian Dugan, who was convicted for the rape and murder of a 10-year-old girl in Illinois (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scim.ag/BrianDugan">http://scim.ag/BrianDugan</ext-link>). Kiehl testified that brain scans his team performed on Dugan showed abnormalities in brain activity consistent with psychopathy. &#x201C;Without the brain imaging stuff the jury would have been back in an hour,&#x201D; Dugan&apos;s defense attorney, Steve Greenberg, told <italic>Science</italic> at the time. As it was, they deliberated for 10 hours before returning a death sentence. Neuroscience evidence may have spared another convicted murderer from the death penalty in a 2010 case (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scim.ag/GradyNelson">http://scim.ag/GradyNelson</ext-link>).</p>
<p>It&apos;s very difficult to track how often biological explanations of behavior are introduced in court and how judges and juries weigh them against other types of evidence, says Owen Jones, a law professor at Vanderbilt University in Nashville and director of the MacArthur Foundation Research Network on Law and Neuroscience. &#x201C;What&apos;s pathbreaking about this paper is that it isolates, as well as one can, both the effects of biological testimony on outcomes and it also does this within a sample of the real-world decision-makers, the judges themselves.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Psychopathy has long been viewed as an aggravating factor in criminal cases, partly because its characteristic traits&#x2014;including callousness, arrogance, and lack of remorse&#x2014;aren&apos;t sympathetic, and partly because it&apos;s one of the best predictors of recidivism. Some researchers consider it a mental illness even though it&apos;s not listed in the primary diagnostic manual, and work by Kiehl and others has linked psychopathy to abnormalities in brain regions involved in regulating emotion and behavior (<italic>Science</italic>, 5 September 2008, p. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/321/5894/1284.full">1284</ext-link>). &#x201C;Understanding psychopathy as a mental-health disorder changes people&apos;s ideas about sentencing,&#x201D; Kiehl says. Developing effective treatments would change them even more, he adds.</p>
<p>But there&apos;s a danger in applying published studies showing that the brains of psychopaths differ <italic>on average</italic> from the brains of nonpsychopaths to individual cases, says James Blair, a cognitive neuroscientist who studies psychopathy at the National Institute of Mental Health in Bethesda, Maryland. &#x201C;I don&apos;t think the data are there to do this on an individual basis,&#x201D; he says.</p>
<p>Among the questions the new findings raise for future research is how sentencing might be influenced by biological evidence of other conditions that might be viewed more sympathetically than psychopathy, such as intellectual disability or posttraumatic stress disorder, Brown says. &#x201C;If you could show some biological risk factor for those disorders, it might reduce sentencing even more,&#x201D; she says.</p>
<p>If judges are, in fact, giving extra weight to biological evidence in real-life cases, the next obvious question is whether they should, says Stephen J. Morse, a legal scholar specializing in criminal law and neuroscience at the University of Pennsylvania. &#x201C;I think the answer there has to be no,&#x201D; Morse says. For example, he says, if the law deems poor impulse control to be relevant in sentencing, &#x201C;why should it matter whether that poor impulse control is a product of a biomechanical cause, a psychological cause, a sociological cause, an astrological cause, or any other cause for which the defendant is not responsible?&#x201D;</p>
</body>
</article>
