<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id><journal-title>Science</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News Focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-focus</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>MEDICINE</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Alzheimer's Research</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>How to Talk About Alzheimer's Risk</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Greg</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>17</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date><volume>337</volume><issue>6096</issue><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>792</lpage><permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Most people do not want to know if Alzheimer's disease is written in their genes, say researchers leading two trials that will try to prevent Alzheimer's in people with gene mutations that cause it.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>If Alzheimer's disease were written in your genes, would you want to know? Most people do not, say researchers leading two upcoming clinical trials that will try to prevent Alzheimer's in people with gene mutations that cause an early-onset form of the disease (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/summary/337/6096/790">see main text</ext-link>). To accommodate the participants' wishes, those trials will not reveal genetic testing results. But what about less certain risks?</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>If Alzheimer's disease were written in your genes, would you want to know? Most people do not, say researchers leading two upcoming clinical trials that will try to prevent Alzheimer's in people with gene mutations that cause an early-onset form of the disease (see main text, p. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/337/6096/790.full">790</ext-link>). To accommodate the participants' wishes, those trials will not reveal genetic testing results. But what about less certain risks?</p>
<p>Many people do want to know if they have the so-called <italic>ApoE4</italic> genetic variant, which triples the risk of developing Alzheimer's disease in old age, says Robert Green, a medical geneticist at Harvard University and principal investigator of the Risk Evaluation and Education for Alzheimer's Disease study. Over the past decade, Green and his colleagues have looked at the impact of telling people their <italic>ApoE</italic> status. When people who are psychologically healthy find out they're <italic>ApoE4</italic>-positive, they handle the information fairly well, Green says. &#x201C;Whether they can do something medically about it isn't as important as you might think,&#x201D; he adds. People who find out they are positive often take other measures, such as buying long-term care insurance or joining an advocacy group, Green says.</p>
<p>A third upcoming trial, the Anti-Amyloid Treatment of Asymptomatic Alzheimer's (A4), will enroll people with a different risk factor: evidence of &#x03B2; amyloid accumulation in the brain, widely thought to be an indicator of the disease. In contrast with genetic testing, however, the predictive value of a &#x03B2; amyloid&#x2013;positive brain scan is not well understood, says Jason Karlawish, a professor of ethics and health policy at the University of Pennsylvania, who will lead an ethics arm of the A4 trial. To enroll in the trial, participants must agree to find out their amyloid status, and Karlawish says he and colleagues are working on how to explain the scans and convey the uncertainty. Researchers will monitor participants for mood and lifestyle changes and examine how &#x03B2; amyloid test results affect their perceptions of their cognitive abilities and future risks.</p>
<p>With the approval earlier this year of florbetapir, a radioactive compound that binds to &#x03B2; amyloid in the brain and makes it visible on a positron emission tomography scan, more and more doctors will start ordering these tests, Karlawish says. He hopes his study will provide guidance for doctors on how to deliver the news, and on how patients are likely to take it.</p>
</body>
</article>
