<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="brief-report" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1222901</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1222901</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Brevia</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brevia</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>brevia</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>CELL BIOL</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Type 6 Secretion Dynamics Within and Between Bacterial Cells</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Basler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Mekalanos</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib>
<aff>Department of Microbiology and Immunobiology, Harvard Medical School, 200 Longwood Avenue, Boston, MA 02115, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:href="john_mekalanos@hms.harvard.edu">john_mekalanos@hms.harvard.edu</email></corresp></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>17</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6096</issue>
<fpage>815</fpage>
<lpage>815</lpage>
<history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>04</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>06</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>07</month><year>2012</year></date></history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Time-lapse video records a bacterial protein transportation machine in action.</p></abstract>
<abstract>
<p>The bacterial type 6 secretion system (T6SS) functions as a virulence factor capable of attacking both eukaryotic and prokaryotic target cells by a process that involves protein transport through a contractile bacteriophage tail-like structure. The T6SS apparatus is composed, in part, of an exterior sheath wrapped around an interior tube. Here, we report that in living cells the cytoplasmic adenosine triphosphatase called ClpV specifically recognizes the contracted T6SS sheath structure, causing its disassembly within seconds. ClpV imaging allowed spatial and temporal documentation of cell-cell interactions (termed T6SS dueling) that likely mark the location of repeated T6SS-mediated protein translocation events between bacterial cells.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Stella Hurtley</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Trista Wagoner</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The bacterial type 6 secretion system (T6SS) is a dynamic apparatus that translocates proteins between cells by a mechanism analogous to phage tail contraction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). In <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic>, two proteins (VipA and VipB) build a phage tail sheathlike tubular structure in the cytosol of &#x201C;predator&#x201D; cells that is either extended or contracted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). Contraction of the extended VipA/VipB sheath is thought to drive the T6SS spike and inner tube complex out of the effector or predator cell and into an adjacent target or &#x201C;prey&#x201D; cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). Disassembly of the cytoplasmic contracted sheath requires ClpV in vivo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>), a AAA+ adenosine triphosphatase (ATPase) that binds VipA/VipB tubules in vitro and can remodel these structures in the presence of ATP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). In <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, ClpV1&#x2013;green fluorescent protein (GFP) localizes to discrete foci that depend on T6SS function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>We used time-lapse fluorescence microscopy to follow ClpV localization in live <italic>V. cholerae</italic> 2740-80 cells. Functional ClpV&#x2013;super folder GFP (sfGFP) and mCherry2 fusion proteins assembled at random times into short structures that disappeared in tens of seconds. In the &#x2206;VipA background, ClpV was evenly distributed in cytosol, suggesting that the short ClpV structures were dependent on T6SS sheaths (fig. S1 and movie S1). We used functional VipA-sfGFP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>) and ClpV-mCherry2 fusions to image ClpV and T6SS sheaths simultaneously. Extended VipA-sfGFP&#x2013;containing sheaths were not colocalized with ClpV-mCherry2, whereas contraction of a sheath led to immediate colocalization of ClpV-mCherry2 with the whole contracted sheath (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> and movies S2 and S3). Half of the ClpV associated with the contracted sheath between 683 and 1273 ms (average = 952 ms, SD = 164 ms, <italic>n</italic> = 10; fig. S2 and movie S4). The disassembly of the contracted sheath required between 22 and 46 s (average = 32.5 s, SD = 6.1 s, <italic>n</italic> = 40), measured from the moment of contraction to the moment when both ClpV and VipA signals were no longer colocalized to one spot (movies S2 and S3).</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption>
<p>ClpV colocalizes with contracted sheath (arrows). A 3-&#x03BC;m-by-3-&#x03BC;m field of cells is shown. Scale bar in (A) is 1 &#x03BC;m and applies to (A) to (D). (A to C) <italic>V. cholerae</italic> ClpV-mCherry2 + pBAD24-VipA-sfGFP. (<bold>A</bold>) Merge of ClpV-mCherry2 and VipA-sfGFP signals. (<bold>B</bold>) ClpV-mCherry2 signal. (<bold>C</bold>) VipA-sfGFP signal. Additional frames and cells are shown in movies S2 and S3. (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> &#x0394;<italic>retS</italic>/ClpV1-GFP; additional frames and cells are shown in movies S6 and S7.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_815_F1"></graphic></fig>
<p>The Tyr<sup>664</sup>&#x2192;Ala<sup>664</sup> (Y664A) mutation in the pore of ClpV blocks VipA/VipB disassembly but still allows binding of ClpV to VipB in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>) whereas the Phe<sup>87</sup>&#x2192;Arg<sup>87</sup> (F87R) mutation of N-terminal domain of ClpV blocks VipB recognition in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). In vivo, ClpV-Y664A-mCherry2 was colocalized with VipA-sfGFP to short nondynamic structures that were likely contracted T6SS sheaths (fig. S3 and movie S5). In contrast, ClpV-F87R-mCherry2 was distributed uniformly in the cytosol with only VipA-sfGFP localized into contracted nondynamic sheaths (fig. S3 and movie S5). Localization of these ClpV mutants and the change in the dynamics of VipA-containing structures are consistent with published data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>) and suggest that, in vivo, the N terminus of VipB is exposed on the surface of the contracted sheath just before its disassembly.</p>
<p>In <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, mutation of the regulatory gene <italic>retS</italic> allows expression of one of its T6SS loci (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). To assess the dynamics of T6SS in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, we imaged a ClpV1-GFP fusion protein in a <italic>retS</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>) by time-lapse fluorescence microscopy. In contrast to <italic>V. cholerae</italic>, only a subset of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> cells actively formed and disassembled ClpV1-GFP&#x2013;containing complexes during the observation period; the formation and dynamics of these structures required the VipA homolog PA0083 (fig. S1 and movies S6 and S7). ClpV1-GFP structures often assembled and disassembled repeatedly in apparently the same subcellular location (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref> and movie S7) indicating that, in contrast to <italic>V. cholerae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>), multiple T6SS apparatuses assemble in close proximity or, more likely, T6SS &#x201C;base plate&#x201D; components (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>) are recycled by <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>.</p>
<p><italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> cells responded to T6SS activity occurring in a neighboring sister cell with an increase in their own T6SS dynamics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref> and movies S6 and S7). Over time, the coincidence of T6SS activity between pairs of sister cells (termed T6SS dueling) became the dominant category of T6SS activity observable in the <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> population (table S1 and fig. S4). Spatially concurrent T6SS activity could not be documented between <italic>V. cholerae</italic> sister cells because this species exhibited much higher levels of T6SS activity in nearly all cells (fig. S4). The spatial and temporal coincidence of T6SS activity in adjacent <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> cells strongly suggests that a signal was being transferred between cells precisely at the position of the initial T6SS activity. The <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> T6SS is thought to transfer peptidoglycan-hydrolyzing T6SS substrates into sister cells that express immunity proteins to their action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>). Perhaps cellular attack by a T6SS apparatus mediated by translocation of T6SS components (e.g., the spike/inner tube complex or effector proteins) into nearby adjacent sister cells induces local cell-envelope alterations [e.g., membrane perturbation, mild peptidoglycan hydrolysis, or protein phosphorylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>)] that trigger the formation of a T6SS apparatus in the vicinity of such alterations (fig. S5).</p>
<p>ClpV imaging provides evidence that <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> likely recycles T6SS membrane base plate components and can sense T6SS activity in nearby cells. Because T6SS dueling events were spatially and temporally linked, they likely mark the exact location of T6SS translocation of protein components (e.g., VgrG and/or effector proteins) between cells. T6SS dueling may reflect social interactions between heterologous T6SS<sup>+</sup> species that coexist in the same niche.</p>
</body>
<back><app-group><app>
<title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/science.1222901/DC1">www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/science.1222901/DC1</ext-link></p>
<p>Materials and Methods</p>
<p>Figs. S1 to S5</p>
<p>Table S1</p>
<p>References (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>)</p>
<p>Movies S1 to S7</p></supplementary-material></app></app-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pukatzki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Identification of a conserved bacterial protein secretion system in <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> using the <italic>Dictyostelium</italic> host model system</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>103</volume>, 
<fpage>1528</fpage> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0510322103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16432199</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leiman</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Type VI secretion apparatus and phage tail-associated protein complexes share a common evolutionary origin</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>106</volume>, 
<fpage>4154</fpage> (<year>2009</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0813360106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19251641</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilhofer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekalanos</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Type VI secretion requires a dynamic contractile phage tail-like structure</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>483</volume>, 
<fpage>182</fpage> (<year>2012</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22367545</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x00F6;nemann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietrosiuk</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diemand</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zentgraf</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogk</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Remodelling of VipA/VipB tubules by ClpV-mediated threading is crucial for type VI protein secretion</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source> 
<volume>28</volume>, 
<fpage>315</fpage> (<year>2009</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2008.269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19131969</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pietrosiuk</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Molecular basis for the unique role of the AAA+ chaperone ClpV in type VI protein secretion</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>286</volume>, 
<fpage>30010</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.253377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21733841</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mougous</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>A virulence locus of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> encodes a protein secretion apparatus</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>312</volume>, 
<fpage>1526</fpage> (<year>2006</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1128393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16763151</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Type VI secretion delivers bacteriolytic effectors to target cells</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>475</volume>, 
<fpage>343</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21776080</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Separate inputs modulate phosphorylation-dependent and -independent type VI secretion activation</article-title>. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source> 
<volume>82</volume>, 
<fpage>1277</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2011.07889.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22017253</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bina</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekalanos</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title><italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> tolC is required for bile resistance and colonization</article-title>. <source>Infect. Immun.</source> 
<volume>69</volume>, 
<fpage>4681</fpage> (<year>2001</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.69.7.4681-4685.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402016</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metcalf</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Conditionally replicative and conjugative plasmids carrying lacZ alpha for cloning, mutagenesis, and allele replacement in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Plasmid</source> 
<volume>35</volume>, 
<fpage>1</fpage> (<year>1996</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/plas.1996.0001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8693022</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rietsch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallet-Gely</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dove</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekalanos</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>ExsE, a secreted regulator of type III secretion genes in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source> 
<volume>102</volume>, 
<fpage>8006</fpage> (<year>2005</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0503005102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15911752</pub-id></citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank T. G. Bernhardt and N. T. Peters for suggestions on the use of fluorescence microscopy resources and B. Ho and K. Roberts for helpful discussions. This work was supported by National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Disease grants AI-018045 and AI-26289 to J.J.M.</p>
</ack></back>
</article>