<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1224352</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1224352</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Report</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Reports</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>reports</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>CELL BIOL</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Identification of the Cdc48&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> Proteasome as an Ancient AAA+ Proteolytic Machine</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barthelme</surname><given-names>Dominik</given-names></name></contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>Robert T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib>
<aff>Department of Biology, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:href="bobsauer@mit.edu">bobsauer@mit.edu</email>.</corresp></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>17</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6096</issue>
<fpage>843</fpage>
<lpage>846</lpage>
<history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>05</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>06</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>07</month><year>2012</year></date></history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="editor"><title>Take Another Cap</title><p>Selective cytosolic protein degradation is mediated primarily by the proteasome, which is comprised of a core peptidase and a regulatory cap. Current dogma holds that the 20<italic>S</italic> core peptidase of the proteasome functions exclusively with the 19<italic>S</italic> regulatory particle in eukaryotes, with PAN in archaea, and with Mpa in mycobacteria. <bold>Barthelme and Sauer</bold> (p. <related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="337" page="843">843</related-article>, published online 26 July 2012; see the Perspective by<related-article related-article-type="in-this-issue" vol="337" page="813" issue="6096"><bold>Matouschek and Finley</bold></related-article>) now suggest that another type of proteasome can assemble in archaea consisting of the double-ring AAA+ protein, Cdc48, in complex with the 20<italic>S</italic> core protease.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>The AAA+ enzyme Cdc48 combines with the 20<italic>S</italic> peptidase to function as an alternative type of proteasome.</p></abstract>
<abstract>
<p>Proteasomes are the major energy-dependent proteolytic machines in the eukaryotic and archaeal domains of life. To execute protein degradation, the 20<italic>S</italic> core peptidase combines with the AAA+ ring of the 19<italic>S</italic> regulatory particle in eukarya or with the AAA+ proteasome-activating nucleotidase ring in some archaea. Here, we find that Cdc48 and 20<italic>S</italic> from the archaeon <italic>Thermoplasma acidophilum</italic> interact to form a functional proteasome. Cdc48 is an abundant and essential double-ring AAA+ molecular machine ubiquitously present in archaea, where its function has been uncertain, and in eukarya where Cdc48 participates by largely unknown mechanisms in diverse cellular processes, including multiple proteolytic pathways. Thus, proteolysis in collaboration with the 20<italic>S</italic> peptidase may represent an ancestral function of the Cdc48 family.</p>
</abstract>
<custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>Editor</meta-name><meta-value>Stella Hurtley</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Barbara Ordway</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In all domains of life, protein-unfolding machines fueled by adenosine triphosphate (ATP) and self-compartmentalized peptidases carry out intracellular protein degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). The unfoldases belong to the AAA+ superfamily [adenosine triphosphatases (ATPases) associated with a variety of cellular activities] and function as hexameric rings. The barrel-shaped peptidases have an internal chamber containing the proteolytic active sites. All AAA+ proteases share common operating principles, including coaxial unfoldase-peptidase docking and translocation of unfolded substrates through the axial pores into the degradation chamber. The major degradation machine in eukaryotes is the 26<italic>S</italic> proteasome, consisting of the 20<italic>S</italic> core peptidase and 19<italic>S</italic> regulatory particles, which contain AAA+ Rpt<sub>1-6</sub> unfolding rings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). The 20<italic>S</italic> peptidase, which has an &#x03B1;<sub>7</sub>&#x03B2;<sub>7</sub>&#x03B2;<sub>7</sub>&#x03B1;<sub>7</sub> architecture, is also ubiquitous in archaea, where it functions with the hexameric AAA+ proteasome-activating nucleotidase (PAN) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>). Paradoxically, PAN is absent from some archaea (table S1) and is not required for viability of other archaea in which 20<italic>S</italic> is essential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). Thus, we reasoned that an unidentified pathway for proteasomal protein degradation must exist.</p>
<p>Cdc48/p97 is a double-ring AAA+ machine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>) that is highly conserved but has no clear function in archaea. By contrast, eukaryotic Cdc48 and specific adaptor proteins participate in diverse cellular processes, including proteolytic pathways, but by largely unknown molecular mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). It is intriguing that many archaeal and eukaryotic Cdc48 enzymes have C-terminal HbYX (hydrophobic residue, tyrosine, any residue) motifs, which are also present in PAN and Rpt<sub>1-6</sub> subunits and dock into binding pockets on the 20<italic>S</italic> &#x03B1; ring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>).</p>
<p>The single AAA+ module of PAN is highly homologous to both AAA+ modules of Cdc48, but these proteins have distinct N domains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>). Searches of complete archaeal genomes revealed that ~15% contained no PAN genes but did contain 20<italic>S</italic> genes and at least one Cdc48 gene encoding an HbYX or related C-terminal sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref> and table S1). Docking the crystal structures of <italic>Thermoplasma acidophilum</italic> 20<italic>S</italic> and mouse Cdc48/p97 showed that the C-terminal tails could be positioned to interact with the HbYX-binding clefts in the 20<italic>S</italic> &#x03B1; ring (fig. S1).</p>
<fig id="F1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption>
<p>Cdc48 binds the 20<italic>S</italic> peptidase. (<bold>A</bold>) PAN and Cdc48 have distinct N domains but homologous AAA+ modules and HbYX motifs. (<bold>B</bold>) Examples of archaea in which PAN was absent but 20<italic>S</italic> and Cdc48 were present. Red Cdc48 tripeptides match HbYX or related sequences. (<bold>C</bold>) Sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) showed that purified <italic>T. acidophilum</italic> His<sub>6</sub>-Cdc48<sup>EQ/EQ</sup> pulled down two proteins from a <italic>T. acidophilum</italic> cell extract, which were identified as the 20<italic>S</italic> &#x03B1; and &#x03B2; subunits (fig. S2). (<bold>D</bold>) Using purified <italic>T. acidophilum</italic> proteins, 20<italic>S</italic> with a His<sub>6</sub>-tagged &#x03B2; subunit pulled down a roughly stoichiometric quantity of untagged Cdc48<sup>EQ/EQ</sup> in the presence of 2 mM ATP but not ADP.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_843_F1"></graphic></fig>
<p>For interaction studies, we used <italic>T. acidophilum</italic> His<sub>6</sub>-Cdc48<sup>EQ/EQ</sup>, a hexahistidine-labeled variant with E291Q/E568Q substitutions (glutamine for glutamic acid at positions 291 and 568) in the Walker-B motifs of the D1 and D2 rings to prevent ATP hydrolysis. When His<sub>6</sub>-Cdc48<sup>EQ/EQ</sup> was added to a <italic>T. acidophilum</italic> cell extract, it pulled down two proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>), identified as the 20<italic>S</italic> &#x03B1; and &#x03B2; subunits (fig. S2). Using purified His<sub>6</sub>-tagged 20<italic>S</italic> and purified untagged Cdc48<sup>EQ/EQ</sup>, we also observed a direct and approximately stoichiometric interaction in the presence of ATP but not adenosine diphosphate (ADP) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>).</p>
<p>The N termini of the &#x03B1; subunits gate or restrict entry of peptides longer than five to seven residues into free 20<italic>S</italic>, and such peptides are cleaved at enhanced rates by PAN&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> or the 26<italic>S</italic> proteasome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>). With ATP present, Cdc48 also had gate-opening activity, stimulating 20<italic>S</italic> cleavage of a nonapeptide but not a tetrapeptide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref> and fig. S3). When the gate residues were deleted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>), 20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x0394;&#x03B1;2-12</sup> alone cleaved the nonapeptide at a rate similar to that of Cdc48&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic>, and added Cdc48 did not increase 20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x0394;&#x03B1;2-12</sup> activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup>, which lacks the N domain, stimulated nonapeptide cleavage in the presence of ATP and two poorly hydrolyzable analogs, ATP&#x03B3;S (adenosine 5&#x2032;-[&#x03B3;-thio]triphosphate and AMP-PNP (adenosine 5&#x2032;-[&#x03B2;,&#x03B3;-imido]triphosphate), whereas these analogs supported very weak gate opening by Cdc48 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="F2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption>
<p>Cdc48 activates 20<italic>S</italic> gate opening. (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>T. acidophilum</italic> Cdc48 (0.4 &#x03BC;M) and 20<italic>S</italic> (10 nM) cleaved a nonapeptide (10 &#x03BC;M) rapidly as assayed by increased fluorescence with 2 mM ATP. Cleavage by Cdc48 alone was undetected and by 20<italic>S</italic> alone was slow. (<bold>B</bold>) Cdc48 or Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup> (0.4 &#x03BC;M) stimulation of nonapeptide cleavage by 20<italic>S</italic>, 20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x2206;&#x03B1;2-12</sup>, or 20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B1;K66A</sup> (10 nM) in the presence of different nucleotides (2 mM). Values are averages &#x00B1; SD (<italic>N</italic> &#x2265; 3) divided by the 20<italic>S</italic> cleavage rate. (<bold>C</bold>) Nonapeptide cleavage by 20<italic>S</italic> or 20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B1;K66A</sup> (10 nM) as a function of increasing concentrations of Cdc48 or variants. Solid lines (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> &#x2265; 0.98) are fits to a hyperbolic equation for all curves except Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic>, which was fit to a quadratic equation for near-stoichiometric binding. (<bold>D</bold>) Values for the maximum stimulation of cleavage and the apparent dissociation constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>app</sub>) were calculated from the fits in (C) or fig. S4.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_843_F2"></graphic></fig>
<p>Apparent equilibrium dissociation constants of ~160 nM for Cdc48&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> and ~300 nM for PAN&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> were determined by measuring the Cdc48/PAN dependence of 20<italic>S</italic> nonapeptide cleavage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref> and fig. S4). Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup> bound 20<italic>S</italic> substantially more tightly, with an affinity of ~2 nM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>).</p>
<p>A Cdc48 variant with the Y753A mutation (alanine replacing Tyr<sup>753</sup>) in the HbYX motif bound 20<italic>S</italic> and stimulated peptide cleavage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>) but with decreased affinity (~580 nM) and only 14% of the maximum activity of Cdc48 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>). Thus, binding and gate opening are not fully coupled in this mutant. In the binding pocket on 20<italic>S</italic>&#x03B1;, Lys<sup>66</sup> forms a salt bridge with the &#x03B1;-carboxylate of PAN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>). Cdc48 or Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup> stimulated nonapeptide cleavage by 20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B1;K66A</sup> poorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2, B and C</xref>), which suggests that interactions involving the Cdc48 tail and Lys<sup>66</sup> facilitate gate opening.</p>
<p><italic>T. acidophilum</italic> Cdc48 unfolds green fluorescent protein (GFP) bearing the ssrA degron, with unfolding and ATP hydrolysis being stimulated by 120 mM Mg<sup>++</sup> or N-domain deletion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>). We found that Cdc48&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> completely degraded native GFP-ssrA in the presence of ATP and 120 mM Mg<sup>++</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> also efficiently degraded GFP-ssrA with ATP and 20 mM Mg<sup>++</sup>, but no degradation was observed with ATP&#x03B3;S, without Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup>, or with proteolytically inactive 20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B2;T1A</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). Michaelis-Menten analysis of GFP-ssrA degradation by Cdc48&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> showed that the Michaelis constant <italic>K</italic><sub>M</sub> was ~2 &#x03BC;M in high and low Mg<sup>++</sup>, whereas the maximum initial velocity of the enzyme-catalyzed reaction, <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>, increased from 0.07 to 0.39 min<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> enzyme<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> as Mg<sup>++</sup> was raised (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref> and table S2). For Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> in low Mg<sup>++</sup>, <italic>K</italic><sub>M</sub> was 0.15 &#x03BC;M and <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> was 3.2 min<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> enzyme<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>. Thus, the N domain of Cdc48 represses proteolytic activity both by increasing <italic>K</italic><sub>M</sub> and decreasing <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>. For comparison, PAN&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> degraded GFP-ssrA with a <italic>K</italic><sub>M</sub> of 0.15 &#x03BC;M and <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> of 0.35 min<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> enzyme<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref> and table S2).</p>
<fig id="F3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption>
<p>Protein degradation by the Cdc48&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> proteasome. (<bold>A</bold>) SDS-PAGE assay of GFP-ssrA (10 &#x03BC;M) degradation by Cdc48 (1 &#x03BC;M) and 20<italic>S</italic> (2 &#x03BC;M) with 2 mM ATP, 120 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and an ATP regeneration system. (<bold>B</bold>) (Top) SDS-PAGE assay of GFP-ssrA (5 &#x03BC;M) degradation by 20<italic>S</italic> (0.9 &#x03BC;M) and Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup> (0.3 &#x03BC;M), 2 mM ATP, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and a regeneration system. (Bottom strips) GFP-ssrA in otherwise comparable assays using 2 mM ATP&#x03B3;S (no regeneration), without Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup>, or with catalytically inactive 20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B2;T1A</sup>. (<bold>C</bold>) Michaelis-Menten plots of GFP-ssrA degradation by 20<italic>S</italic> (0.9 &#x03BC;M) and Cdc48 (0.3 &#x03BC;M; left) or 20<italic>S</italic> (0.9 &#x03BC;M) with Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup> or PAN (0.3 &#x03BC;M; right). Values are averages &#x00B1; SD (<italic>N</italic> &#x2265; 3). Fitted parameters are listed in table S2. (<bold>D</bold>) Degradation of 10 &#x03BC;M native titin<sup>I27</sup>-ssrA or denatured CM-titin<sup>I27</sup>-ssrA. The top two gel strips show degradation by Cdc48 (1.2 &#x03BC;M) and 20<italic>S</italic> (0.4 &#x03BC;M) in 120 mM Mg<sup>++</sup> buffer. The next four strips show degradation by Cdc48<sup>&#x0394;N</sup> or Cdc48<sup>&#x0394;N/EQ/EQ</sup> (1.2 &#x03BC;M) and 20<italic>S</italic> (0.4 &#x03BC;M) in 20 mM Mg<sup>++</sup> buffer. The bottom strip shows degradation by 20<italic>S</italic> (0.4 &#x03BC;M) in 20 mM Mg<sup>++</sup> buffer. Reactions contained 5 mM ATP and a regeneration system or 5 mM ATP&#x03B3;S without regeneration.</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_843_F3"></graphic></fig>
<p>Cdc48&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> degraded CM-titin<sup>I27</sup>-ssrA, a variant denatured by carboxymethylation of normally buried cysteines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13"><italic>13</italic></xref>), faster than native titin<sup>I27</sup>-ssrA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> also degraded the denatured substrate more rapidly, in a reaction that required ATP hydrolysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). In principle, Cdc48 might unfold and release substrates into solution for subsequent capture and degradation by free 20<italic>S</italic>. However, degradation of unfolded CM-titin<sup>I27</sup>-ssrA by 20<italic>S</italic> alone was much slower than degradation with Cdc48 or Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>), which suggested that ATP-fueled translocation from Cdc48 into the associated 20<italic>S</italic> peptidase is responsible for most degradation. Moreover, a PAN variant that unfolded GFP-ssrA, but did not bind 20<italic>S</italic>, failed to support degradation (figs. S4 and S5). Thus, folded and unfolded substrates are only degraded efficiently by complexes of 20<italic>S</italic> with Cdc48 or PAN.</p>
<p>A &#x2206;HbYX Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup> variant that terminates with Asp-Gln-Gly supported a low level of gate opening (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>) and 20<italic>S</italic> degradation of GFP-ssrA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Although the affinity of Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N/&#x2206;HbYX</sup> for 20<italic>S</italic> was reduced compared with that of Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup>, it was still surprisingly strong (40 nM). Because the HbYX motif stabilizes but is not required for 20<italic>S</italic> binding, other Cdc48 regions must make major contributions to binding. We also observed weak gate opening (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>) and GFP-ssrA degradation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>) when we used 20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B1;K66A</sup> in combination with either Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup> or Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N/&#x2206;HbYX</sup>, showing that K66 recognition of an &#x03B1;-carboxylate is not essential for binding and degradation. Moreover, the affinity effects of the Cdc48 &#x2206;HbYX and 20<italic>S</italic> &#x03B1;K66A mutations were nonadditive, as expected for interacting groups. How can the protein degradation activities of Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N/&#x2206;HbYX</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic>, Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B1;K66A</sup>, and Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N/&#x2206;HbYX</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B1;K66A</sup>, which require an open 20<italic>S</italic> gate, be reconciled with the poor stimulation of peptide cleavage by these enzymes? The 20<italic>S</italic> gate dynamically adopts a variety of conformations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>), and an actively translocating polypeptide might trap a transiently open gate with the spooling chain preventing closure.</p>
<fig id="F4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption>
<p>The HbYX motif is not required for 20<italic>S</italic> binding and degradation. (<bold>A</bold>) Stimulation of peptide cleavage by 20<italic>S</italic> or 20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B1;K66A</sup> (10 nM) as a function of Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N/HbYX</sup> or Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup> concentration. Values are averages (<italic>N</italic> = 3) &#x00B1; SD. Solid lines (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> &#x2265; 0.948) are fits to a quadratic equation for near-stoichiometric binding, yielding <italic>K</italic><sub>app</sub> values of 41 &#x00B1; 4 nM for Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N/HbYX</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic>, 21 &#x00B1; 9 nM for Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B1;K66A</sup>, and 15 &#x00B1; 6 nM for Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N/HbYX</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B1;K66A</sup>. (<bold>B</bold>) Gel strips showing ATP-dependent degradation of GFP-ssrA (5 &#x03BC;M) by Cdc48<sup>&#x0394;N/&#x2206;HbYX</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic>, Cdc48<sup>&#x0394;N</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B1;K66A</sup>, or Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N/HbYX</sup>&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B1;K66A</sup>. Assays were performed in 20 mM Mg<sup>++</sup> using 5 mM ATP and regeneration or 5 mM ATP&#x03B3;S; 20<italic>S</italic>/20<italic>S</italic><sup>&#x03B1;K66A</sup> (0.4 &#x03BC;M); Cdc48<sup>&#x0394;N</sup>/Cdc48<sup>&#x2206;N/HbYX</sup> (1.2 &#x03BC;M).</p>
</caption><graphic xlink:href="337_843_F4"></graphic></fig>
<p>We find that archaeal Cdc48 binds to the proteasomal 20<italic>S</italic> peptidase, induces gate opening, and unfolds and actively translocates protein substrates into the 20<italic>S</italic> chamber for proteolysis. Cdc48 is the only 20<italic>S</italic> partner in ~15% of archaea, and Cdc48 and PAN are both present in the remaining ~85%. On the basis of their C-terminal sequences (table S1), the fact that Cdc48 binding is not strictly HbYX-dependent, and our finding that Cdc48 and PAN bind 20<italic>S</italic> with similar affinities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>), it appears that either enzyme could combine with 20<italic>S</italic> to form alternative proteasomes in most archaea. The N domain of Cdc48 is a tethering site for adaptors and possibly substrates, and there is evidence that it controls hexamer conformation and ATP-hydrolysis rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17"><italic>17</italic></xref>). In our experiments, deleting the N domain of <italic>T. acidophilum</italic> Cdc48 strengthened 20<italic>S</italic> binding and increased proteolytic activity. Thus, N-domain modification or N-domain binding of substrates and adaptors may regulate intracellular degradation by the Cdc48&#x2022;20<italic>S</italic> proteasome.</p>
</body>
<back><app-group><app>
<title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/science.1224352/DC1">www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/science.1224352/DC1</ext-link></p>
<p>Materials and Methods</p>
<p>Figs. S1 to S5</p>
<p>Tables S1 and S2</p>
<p>References (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18"><italic>18</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23"><italic>23</italic></xref>)</p></supplementary-material></app></app-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References and Notes</title>
<ref id="R1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>AAA+ proteases: ATP-fueled machines of protein destruction</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source> 
<volume>80</volume>, 
<fpage>587</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-biochem-060408-172623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21469952</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voges</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwickl</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The 26S proteasome: A molecular machine designed for controlled proteolysis</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source> 
<volume>68</volume>, 
<fpage>1015</fpage> (<year>1999</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.68.1.1015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10872471</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Complete subunit architecture of the proteasome regulatory particle</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> 
<volume>482</volume>, 
<fpage>186</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22237024</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zwickl</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klenk</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>An archaebacterial ATPase, homologous to ATPases in the eukaryotic 26 S proteasome, activates protein breakdown by 20 S proteasomes</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>274</volume>, 
<fpage>26008</fpage> (<year>1999</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.37.26008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10473546</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalczyk</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Humbard</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohatgi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maupin-Furlow</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Proteasomal components required for cell growth and stress responses in the haloarchaeon <italic>Haloferax volcanii</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source> 
<volume>190</volume>, 
<fpage>8096</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01180-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18931121</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bug</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Emerging functions of the VCP/p97 AAA-ATPase in the ubiquitin system</article-title>. <source>Nat. Cell Biol.</source> 
<volume>14</volume>, 
<fpage>117</fpage> (<year>2012</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb2407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22298039</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stadtmueller</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Proteasome activators</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source> 
<volume>41</volume>, 
<fpage>8</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2010.12.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21211719</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunger</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>W. I.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Improved structures of full-length p97, an AAA ATPase: Implications for mechanisms of nucleotide-dependent conformational change</article-title>. <source>Structure</source> 
<volume>16</volume>, 
<fpage>715</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.str.2008.02.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18462676</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Structural insights into the regulatory particle of the proteasome from <italic>Methanocaldococcus jannaschii</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source> 
<volume>34</volume>, 
<fpage>473</fpage> (<year>2009</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2009.04.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19481527</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>ATP binding to PAN or the 26S ATPases causes association with the 20S proteasome, gate opening, and translocation of unfolded proteins</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source> 
<volume>20</volume>, 
<fpage>687</fpage> (<year>2005</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2005.10.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16337593</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stadtmueller</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Structural models for interactions between the 20S proteasome and its PAN/19S activators</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>285</volume>, 
<fpage>13</fpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.C109.070425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19889631</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerega</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>VAT, the thermoplasma homolog of mammalian p97/VCP, is an N domain-regulated protein unfoldase</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>280</volume>, 
<fpage>42856</fpage> (<year>2005</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M510592200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236712</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kenniston</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Linkage between ATP consumption and mechanical unfolding during the protein processing reactions of an AAA+ degradation machine</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> 
<volume>114</volume>, 
<fpage>511</fpage> (<year>2003</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00612-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12941278</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Religa</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprangers</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Dynamic regulation of archaeal proteasome gate opening as studied by TROSY NMR</article-title>. <source>Science</source> 
<volume>328</volume>, 
<fpage>98</fpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1184991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20360109</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilt</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchberger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Cdc48: A power machine in protein degradation</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source> 
<volume>36</volume>, 
<fpage>515</fpage> (<year>2011</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibs.2011.06.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21741246</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W. K.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>A novel ATP-dependent conformation in p97 N-D1 fragment revealed by crystal structures of disease-related mutants</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source> 
<volume>29</volume>, 
<fpage>2217</fpage> (<year>2010</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2010.104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20512113</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>The role of the N-domain in the ATPase activity of the mammalian AAA ATPase p97/VCP</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> 
<volume>287</volume>, 
<fpage>8561</fpage> (<year>2012</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.302778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22270372</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benaroudj</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>PAN, the proteasome-activating nucleotidase from archaebacteria, is a protein-unfolding molecular chaperone</article-title>. <source>Nat. Cell Biol.</source> 
<volume>2</volume>, 
<fpage>833</fpage> (<year>2000</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35041081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11056539</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Protein unfolding by a AAA+ protease is dependent on ATP-hydrolysis rates and substrate energy landscapes</article-title>. <source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source> 
<volume>15</volume>, 
<fpage>139</fpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsmb.1380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18223658</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>N&#x00F8;rby</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Coupled assay of Na+,K+-ATPase activity</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol.</source> 
<volume>156</volume>, 
<fpage>116</fpage> (<year>1988</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0076-6879(88)56014-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2835597</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baykov</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evtushenko</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Avaeva</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A malachite green procedure for orthophosphate determination and its use in alkaline phosphatase-based enzyme immunoassay</article-title>. <source>Anal. Biochem.</source> 
<volume>171</volume>, 
<fpage>266</fpage> (<year>1988</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-2697(88)90484-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3044186</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zwickl</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleinz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Critical elements in proteasome assembly</article-title>. <source>Nat. Struct. Biol.</source> 
<volume>1</volume>, 
<fpage>765</fpage> (<year>1994</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsb1194-765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7634086</pub-id></citation></ref>
<ref id="R23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><etal /></person-group>., 
<article-title>Docking of the proteasomal ATPases&#x2019; carboxyl termini in the 20S proteasome&#x2019;s alpha ring opens the gate for substrate entry</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source> 
<volume>27</volume>, 
<fpage>731</fpage> (<year>2007</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2007.06.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17803938</pub-id></citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank C. Hill, A. Horwich, H. Huber, S. Kim, K. Schmitz, B. Stinson, and M. Wohlever for materials and discussions. Supported by NIH grant AI-16892. The data reported in this manuscript are presented in the main paper and supplementary materials.</p>
</ack></back>
</article>