<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="news" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENCE</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="pubmed">Science</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0036-8075</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1095-9203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &amp; Analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>n-analysis</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>SCI POLICY</subject><subject>VIROLOGY</subject><subject>MEDICINE</subject></subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Public Health</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Policy Shifts on Emergency Use of Cholera Vaccines</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Enserink</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<day>17</day>
<month>08</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>337</volume>
<issue>6096</issue>
<fpage>785</fpage>
<lpage>786</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2012, American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>American Association for the Advancement of Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>This week, the World Health Organization is set to publish a report advocating for the creation of a global stockpile of cholera vaccines that would be rushed to countries when an outbreak begins.</p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>Many experts have argued that in outbreak situations&#x2014;especially in the poor, messy places where cholera often strikes&#x2014;existing vaccines are too expensive, not effective enough, and too impractical to roll out; they might even make matters worse, some fear, because they distract health workers from treating patients or improving water and sanitation, the cornerstones of cholera control. But now, the tide appears to have turned. This week, a technical working group at the World Health Organization is set to publish a report advocating for the creation of a global stockpile of cholera vaccines that would be rushed to countries when an outbreak begins.</p></abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<caption>
<title>Fighting without vaccines.</title>
<p>Cholera patients in a treatment center in Port-au-Prince in November 2010.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="337_785_F1"></graphic>
<attrib>CREDIT: JOE RAEDLE/GETTY IMAGES</attrib>
</fig>
<p>Nobody disputes that cholera can be a fast and vicious killer. But whether vaccination can do much to stop an outbreak once it has begun has been vigorously debated for years. Many experts have argued that in outbreak situations&#x2014;especially in the poor, messy places where cholera often strikes&#x2014;existing vaccines are too expensive, not effective enough, and too impractical to roll out; they might even make matters worse, some fear, because they distract health workers from treating patients or improving water and sanitation, the cornerstones of cholera control.</p>
<p>But now, the tide appears to have turned. This week, a technical working group at the World Health Organization (WHO) is set to publish a report advocating for the creation of a global stockpile of cholera vaccines that would be rushed to countries when an outbreak begins. WHO has already adopted the recommendations, and if donors can be persuaded to come up with the money, some $10 million per year, the stockpile could be established in 2013, setting the stage for a much broader use of cholera vaccines.</p>
<p>The report reflects a gradual change of opinion that may also have a big impact in Haiti. After a devastating cholera outbreak erupted in 2010, the Haitian government, advised by the Pan American Health Organization (PAHO), decided against vaccination. But in June, Partners In Health (PIH), a Boston-based charity, completed what it says was a successful 3-month pilot campaign, set up with the government&apos;s blessing, to vaccinate 100,000 people. The program showed that vaccination is feasible even in very difficult circumstances, the group says. After <italic>Science</italic> went to press this week, an expert group at PAHO was scheduled to discuss the campaign; PAHO Deputy Director Jon Andrus said on Monday that he was &#x201C;very confident&#x201D; that the group will advise the Haitian government to start expanding vaccination.</p>
<p>&#x201C;I have the feeling that the world is coming around on this issue,&#x201D; says John Clemens, who, as director of the International Vaccine Institute in Seoul, helped develop Shanchol, the cholera vaccine used in Haiti. (Shanchol is produced by Shantha, an Indian subsidiary of vaccinemaker Sanofi Pasteur.) Clemens, now at the University of California, Los Angeles, has long been frustrated by the resistance to cholera vaccines; a paper he co-authored last year argued that in the 2008&#x2013;2009 cholera outbreak in Zimbabwe, vaccination could have saved almost 1700 of the more than 4200 patients who died.</p>
<p>But at the time, WHO and some aid organizations said Zimbabwe was in no position to run a cholera vaccination campaign; its weak health care system was already overburdened by trying to contain the outbreak and treat patients. The fact that cholera vaccines come in two doses given 1 to 2 weeks apart was seen as another obstacle, because it can be hard to make sure people get their second dose. Vaccination might also give people a false sense of safety, opponents said, because the existing vaccines are only between 60% and 85% effective. Another concern was that vaccines would divert attention from the most important way to prevent cholera and many other waterborne diseases: keeping drinking water and human feces separate.</p>
<p>At the start of the outbreak in Haiti, similar discussions split the scientific and public health communities. The shortage of vaccine was another argument against vaccination; the Haitian government worried that vaccinating a small part of the population could spark discontent and social unrest. As a result, vaccination was left out of the package of control measures.</p>
<p>But as the number of cases mounted in Haiti, the issue soared to prominence on international political agendas. In 2011, the World Health Assembly, an annual meeting of health ministers in Geneva, adopted a resolution calling for more effective cholera control, including the use of vaccines &#x201C;where appropriate.&#x201D; After further consultations, WHO asked the technical working group to come up with an implementation plan for a global stockpile.</p>
<p>WHO&apos;s approval of Shanchol for use in 2011 also helped bring about the change. At about $1.85 per dose, Shanchol is cheap compared with its main rival, Dukoral, made by Dutch biotech Crucell and mostly used as a travelers&apos; vaccine. It&apos;s also easier to ship and distribute, because unlike Dukoral, it doesn&apos;t need to be co-administered with 150 milliliters of a buffer solution.</p>
<p>Clemens says perhaps the clearest sign that views on vaccination are changing is that the Swiss arm of Doctors Without Borders (MSF)&#x2014;a group that has long had reservations about the introduction of cholera shots&#x2014;responded to an outbreak in the West African nation of Guinea by vaccinating about 200,000 people this year. Iza Ciglenecki, an epidemiologist at MSF Switzerland, says standard control methods&#x2014;which include finding patients and treating them with a solution of sugar and salt to keep them hydrated&#x2014;can drive down mortality but don&apos;t have much impact on the number of cases; vaccination does.</p>
<p>In the two coastal regions of Guinea where the campaign was carried out, 75% of the population received two shots, she says. &#x201C;Maybe that doesn&apos;t sound fabulous, but this area has a very mobile population,&#x201D; making it harder to catch people twice.</p>
<p>In Haiti, PIH and a local NGO called GHESKIO started their pilot program in April after many delays. It involved 50,000 people in a slum in the capital Port-au-Prince, says PIH&apos;s Louise Ivers, and another 50,000 in a rural area in the Artibonite valley. More than 90% of people came for their second shot in both places. &#x201C;We&apos;ve shown that the problems are not insurmountable if you&apos;re very dedicated,&#x201D; Ivers says. There&apos;s no evidence that the vaccine led people to abandon precautionary measures such as washing hands and purifying water, and PIH has brought up the importance of clean water and sanitation in every discussion about the program, she adds, to convey the message that vaccines are no excuse for neglecting infrastructure.</p>
<p>Even for countries that want to use vaccines to stem the spread of a cholera epidemic, availability has long been an issue. Currently, the two vaccine manufacturers have very limited amounts of the vaccine on the shelf, and they cannot easily ramp up production when demand surges. That&apos;s where the plan for a global stockpile comes in. It&apos;s modeled on similar caches of meningitis and yellow fever vaccines, and it would be run by the International Coordinating Group, a quartet consisting of MSF, WHO, the U.N. Children&apos;s Fund, and the Red Cross, which also controls those stockpiles.</p>
<p>Under the plan, countries that have a confirmed cholera outbreak can ask for vaccines to be shipped; a special committee will have to decide within 48 hours. It can refuse if a vaccine isn&apos;t going to make much difference, says WHO scientist and working group member Alejandro Costa, for instance, because the outbreak is unlikely to become big, or it has already peaked. Governments will also have to produce a feasible strategy to carry out a campaign.</p>
<p>The working group suggests that the European Union, the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, the GAVI Alliance, and the U.K. and U.S. governments fund the stockpile; Costa says WHO is already talking to them, and some are interested. &#x201C;This report is a big jump,&#x201D; he says. &#x201C;We are moving fast with this.&#x201D;</p>
</body>
</article>